<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: wine | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/wine/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-20T13:16:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[gvSIG and Wine]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/26/gvsig-and-wine/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/26/gvsig-and-wine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I mean <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wine">wine</a>, not <a href="http://www.winehq.org/">Wine</a>.</p>

<p>I've got to give kudos for innovative marketing on this one. I found this interesting announcement from gvSIG in my inbox this morning:</p>

<blockquote>
Enosat, in collaboration with the Association gvSIG, is going to carry  
out an online course on Geographic Information Systems (GIS) and  
Remote Sensing applied to vine-growing for the English-speaking  
community.

This new edition of the course is launched in English, hoping to  
repeat the success of the previous edition in Spanish.

The GIS software used for this course is free software (gvSIG Desktop).

This course covers the basic concepts of GIS and Remote Sensing.  
Furthermore, it enables students to apply these concepts to their  
professional area. This course is aimed at the wine sector, that is,  
technicians in charge of wineries, vine growers, etc.

Places on the course are limited and the admission is in order of  
registration. The syllabus and course details can be found at  
<a href="http://www.enosat.com/formation.php">http://www.enosat.com/formation.php</a>
For further information, please contact: <a href="mailto:course.enosat@gmail.com">course.enosat@gmail.com</a>
</blockquote>


<p>I really hope this takes off as I am already envisioning a host of implementation services built around this market. Now I've just got to translate my rates into bottles per hour. ;-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
