<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gvSIG | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/gvsig/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-18T14:17:38-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[gvSIG 1.9 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/12/gvSIG-1.9-Released/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/12/gvSIG-1.9-Released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just ahead of the <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/eng/inicio-gvsig/">gvSIG</a> <a href="http://jornadas.gvsig.org/home/view?set_language=en">conference</a> in Valencia, <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/eng/gvsig-desktop/all-versions/download/gvsig-19/downloading-the-program/">version 1.9</a> has been released. gvSIG is an open-source desktop GIS developed in Java. The new features in 1.9 are summarized <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/eng/gvsig-desktop/all-versions/download/gvsig-19/version-notes/new-features/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Some of the new features, including SLD import/export, are pretty interesting. gvSIG seems to be flourishing a bit under the wing of <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/gvsig">OSGEO</a>. It's a tool that I have gone back to periodically over the years, and I'll probably take a deeper dive this time given some of the new features. I suggest giving gvSIG a go if you haven't tried it.</p>

<p><img alt="gvSIG 1.9 released" src="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/uploads/pics/Logo-gvSIG_150_03.gif" /></p>

<p>UPDATE: The gvSIG download site seems to be having some serious bandwidth issues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Communication Proposal Deadline for gvSIG Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/09/Communication-Proposal-Deadline-for-gvSIG-Conference/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/09/Communication-Proposal-Deadline-for-gvSIG-Conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2009/06/30/5th-gvsig-conference-announced/">posted before</a>, the 5th <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/index.php?id=gvsig&amp;L=2">gvSIG</a> conference is scheduled for December 2-4, 2009 in Valencia. I got an e-mail reminder that communication proposals (presentations, posters, etc.) are due by September 21st. From the e-mail:</p>

<blockquote>
We remind you that we are now expecting communication proposals for the 5th gvSIG Conference (Valencia, 2nd-4th December 2009) [1]. The deadline is September 21st.

You just have to send an abstract, following the template provided on the Reports section of the Conference web page [2] to contacto-jornadas-gvsig@gva.es and the scientific committee will evaluate it to be in the conference programme.

There are two types of communications: presentation and poster. The communications have to be preferably related to the gvSIG project and the following issues will be also be considered in the evaluation:

  * Innovation.
  * Usefulness for the GIS community.
  * Usefulness for the free open source community.
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5th gvSIG Conference Announced]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/06/30/5th-gvSIG-Conference-Announced/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/06/30/5th-gvSIG-Conference-Announced</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I got this announcement in my inbox today regarding <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/index.php?id=gvsig&amp;L=2">gvSIG</a>, an open-source GIS desktop <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/gvsig">currently in</a> the <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/">OSGEO</a> <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/incubator">incubator</a>. If you are a gvSIG user, the 5th gvSIG Conference will be held this year in Valencia, Spain. See below for the full text:</p>

<blockquote>
The 5th Edition of the gvSIG Conference [1], organized by the Regional Ministry of Infrastructure and Transport (CIT), will be held from December 2nd until December 4th at the Feria Valencia Convention and Exhibition Center, and will once again host the eclipseDay.

In these difficult times when collaboration is most important, we cope with the adversities together with the aim of coming out strengthened by them. We continue moving ahead together. This is part of the gvSIG project and through this approach we keep on growing. This is our slogan for the fifth edition of the gvSIG Conference: We keep growing.

The call for papers for the Fifth Edition of the gvSIG conference is now open. As of today communication proposals can be sent to the email address: <a href="mailto:contacto-jornadas-gvsig@gva.es">contacto-jornadas-gvsig@gva.es</a>; they will be evaluated by the scientific committee as to their inclusion in the conference program. There are two types of communication: paper or poster. Information regarding to regulations on communication presentations can be found in the report's section [2]. Abstracts will be accepted until September 21st .

Organizations interested in collaborating in the event can find information in the section: How to collaborate? [3]


[1] <a href="http://jornadas.gvsig.org/home/view?set_language=en">http://jornadas.gvsig.org/home/view?set_language=en</a>
[2] <a href="http://jornadas.gvsig.org/reports">http://jornadas.gvsig.org/reports</a>
[3] <a href="http://jornadas.gvsig.org/how-to-collaborate">http://jornadas.gvsig.org/how-to-collaborate</a>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
