<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gvSIG | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/gvsig/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-27T14:29:09-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[gvSIG Case Studies Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/10/04/gvsig-case-studies-available/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/10/04/gvsig-case-studies-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/gvsig">gvSIG (open-source desktop GIS)</a> project now has a site listing gvSIG implementation case studies. It is available at:</p>

<p><a href="http://casestudies.gvsig.org/">http://casestudies.gvsig.org/</a></p>

<p>A quick perusal of the site shows a few case studies covering a variety of application areas. This type of thing could be a good way to showcase (and market) the power of gvSIG to a wider audience. It looks like you have to fill out a standardized form in order to submit a project, which gives the resulting case studies consistent and fairly clean structure.</p>

<p>There's no indication of the acceptance criteria for a case study but it looks like something to keep an eye on for a while.</p>

<p>So, if you're a gvSIG user or consultant, then here's a place to toot your horn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[gvSIG and Wine]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/26/gvsig-and-wine/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/26/gvsig-and-wine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I mean <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wine">wine</a>, not <a href="http://www.winehq.org/">Wine</a>.</p>

<p>I've got to give kudos for innovative marketing on this one. I found this interesting announcement from gvSIG in my inbox this morning:</p>

<blockquote>
Enosat, in collaboration with the Association gvSIG, is going to carry  
out an online course on Geographic Information Systems (GIS) and  
Remote Sensing applied to vine-growing for the English-speaking  
community.

This new edition of the course is launched in English, hoping to  
repeat the success of the previous edition in Spanish.

The GIS software used for this course is free software (gvSIG Desktop).

This course covers the basic concepts of GIS and Remote Sensing.  
Furthermore, it enables students to apply these concepts to their  
professional area. This course is aimed at the wine sector, that is,  
technicians in charge of wineries, vine growers, etc.

Places on the course are limited and the admission is in order of  
registration. The syllabus and course details can be found at  
<a href="http://www.enosat.com/formation.php">http://www.enosat.com/formation.php</a>
For further information, please contact: <a href="mailto:course.enosat@gmail.com">course.enosat@gmail.com</a>
</blockquote>


<p>I really hope this takes off as I am already envisioning a host of implementation services built around this market. Now I've just got to translate my rates into bottles per hour. ;-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[gvSIG Extensions Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/01/21/gvsig-extensions-available/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/01/21/gvsig-extensions-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My inbox has been busy this week with announcements from <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/inicio-gvsig/">gvSIG</a>. New builds of the network extension and the 3D extension have been released.</p>

<p>New features of the network extension are described as:</p>

<blockquote>
"- Create and define network topology (using velocities, or sense of direction, modified costs, barriers, turn costs ...)
- Calculate shortest path
- Travelling Salesman Problem (TSP)
- Origin - Destination matrices
- Service Areas
- Emergency / Nearest facilities provider
- Minimum Spanning Tree (MSP)
- Trace (back and forward) the network and find events on the network."
</blockquote>


<!--more-->


<p>The new build of the 3D extension fixes some instabilities on Vista/Win7 and support for Leopard and Snow Leopard on the Mac. Its new features are described as:</p>

<blockquote>
"- New kernel version integrated (osgVP-2.2.0).
- Improved memory management .
- Added new symbology system.
- Various display modes, including stereo and fullscreen."
</blockquote>


<p>As always, more information can be found on the <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/inicio-gvsig/">gvSIG site</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[gvSIG 1.9 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/12/gvsig-1.9-released/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/12/gvsig-1.9-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just ahead of the <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/eng/inicio-gvsig/">gvSIG</a> <a href="http://jornadas.gvsig.org/home/view?set_language=en">conference</a> in Valencia, <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/eng/gvsig-desktop/all-versions/download/gvsig-19/downloading-the-program/">version 1.9</a> has been released. gvSIG is an open-source desktop GIS developed in Java. The new features in 1.9 are summarized <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/eng/gvsig-desktop/all-versions/download/gvsig-19/version-notes/new-features/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Some of the new features, including SLD import/export, are pretty interesting. gvSIG seems to be flourishing a bit under the wing of <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/gvsig">OSGEO</a>. It's a tool that I have gone back to periodically over the years, and I'll probably take a deeper dive this time given some of the new features. I suggest giving gvSIG a go if you haven't tried it.</p>

<p><img alt="gvSIG 1.9 released" src="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/uploads/pics/Logo-gvSIG_150_03.gif" /></p>

<p>UPDATE: The gvSIG download site seems to be having some serious bandwidth issues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Communication Proposal Deadline for gvSIG Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/09/communication-proposal-deadline-for-gvsig-conference/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/09/communication-proposal-deadline-for-gvsig-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2009/06/30/5th-gvsig-conference-announced/">posted before</a>, the 5th <a href="http://www.gvsig.gva.es/index.php?id=gvsig&amp;L=2">gvSIG</a> conference is scheduled for December 2-4, 2009 in Valencia. I got an e-mail reminder that communication proposals (presentations, posters, etc.) are due by September 21st. From the e-mail:</p>

<blockquote>
We remind you that we are now expecting communication proposals for the 5th gvSIG Conference (Valencia, 2nd-4th December 2009) [1]. The deadline is September 21st.

You just have to send an abstract, following the template provided on the Reports section of the Conference web page [2] to contacto-jornadas-gvsig@gva.es and the scientific committee will evaluate it to be in the conference programme.

There are two types of communications: presentation and poster. The communications have to be preferably related to the gvSIG project and the following issues will be also be considered in the evaluation:

  * Innovation.
  * Usefulness for the GIS community.
  * Usefulness for the free open source community.
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
