<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: GiveCamp | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/givecamp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-25T22:30:00-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking For Something To Do In March April?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/13/looking-for-something-to-do-in-march-april/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/13/looking-for-something-to-do-in-march-april</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second annual <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/Homepage.aspx">Southern Maryland GiveCamp</a> will be held on <del datetime="2011-01-23T00:42:57+00:00">March 25</del> April 1, 2011. Once again, it will occur on the campus of <a href="http://www.smcm.edu/">St. Mary's College of Maryland</a>. One of a number of GiveCamps that occur around the country, this one will <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/NonProfits/GiveCamp_2011.aspx">benefit several non-profits</a> of all stripes in the Southern Maryland area.</p>

<p><img alt="Maryland's original State House in St. Mary's City" src="http://www.smcm.edu/studentevents/_assets/images/state_house_lawn.jpg" /></p>

<p>The concept behind GiveCamp is simple and elegant: "GiveCamp is a weekend-long event where software developers, designers, and database administrators donate their time to create custom software for non-profit organizations."</p>

<p>Last year's event drew volunteers from up and down the East Coast. The organizers are still looking for volunteers for this year's event. As a lifelong resident of Southern Maryland, I'd like to encourage my colleagues in the software development community, especially in the greater DC area, to consider coming down in March to <a href="http://somdgc.org/Volunteers.aspx">lend a hand</a>.</p>

<p>Having spoken to a few people that participated last year, I understand that requirements ranged from simple to rather challenging. Regardless of the complexity of a requirement to those of us who develop software professionally, the value of a working web site or database or other such thing to a small organization with limited resources cannot be overstated.</p>

<p>And if Southern Maryland is a bit far for you but you like the concept, there <a href="http://somdgc.org/AboutUs/WhoWeAre/OtherGiveCamps.aspx">may be a GiveCamp in your area</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks to <a href="http://somdgc.org/AboutUs/WhoWeAre/PlanningCommittee.aspx">Jim Pendarvis and the rest of the planning committee</a> for putting this together.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attention Developers - Southern Maryland GiveCamp This Weekend]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/03/17/attention-developers-southern-maryland-givecamp-this-weekend/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/03/17/attention-developers-southern-maryland-givecamp-this-weekend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/Default.aspx">Southern Maryland GiveCamp</a> is happening this weekend at <a href="http://www.smcm.edu/">St. Mary's College of Maryland</a> in <a href="http://www.stmaryscity.org/">St. Mary's City</a> for the benefit of <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/Request.aspx">19 local non-profits</a>. If you are unfamiliar with the concept of a GiveCamp, the web site sums it up but here is an excerpt:</p>

<blockquote>
GiveCamp is a weekend-long event where software developers, designers, and database administrators donate their time to create custom software for non-profit organizations. This custom software could be a new website for the nonprofit organization, or a small data-collection application to keep track of members. The only limitation is that the project should be scoped to be able to be completed in a weekend.
</blockquote>


<p>The Southern Maryland GiveCamp is being put together by <a href="http://jpendarvis.blogspot.com/">Jim Pendarvis</a>, who is putting an enormous amount of work into it. I had planned to participate but events have conspired to prevent that, although three of my <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a> co-workers will be there.</p>

<p><strong>Jim still needs volunteers</strong>. If you are a developer in the Washington, DC area, I strongly encourage you to volunteer your time (<a href="http://www.somdgc.org/Tech.aspx">technical</a> and <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/NonTech.aspx">non-technical</a> volunteers are being sought). In addition to helping the community, you'll also get the added benefit of spending the weekend in one of the <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Saint+Marys+City,+St.+Mary's,+Maryland&amp;sll=-33.76676,150.774015&amp;sspn=0.039529,0.077162&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;cd=1&amp;geocode=FT6wRgIdJLRx-w&amp;split=0&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=Saint+Marys+City,+St.+Mary's,+Maryland&amp;ll=38.193942,-76.434288&amp;spn=0.074742,0.154324&amp;z=13&amp;iwloc=A">most beautiful locales in the region</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
