<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: arcgis | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/arcgis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-24T11:12:24-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Still Jonesing for zigGIS? Try this OGR Plug-In for ArcGIS.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I've actually noticed a surprising uptick in traffic related to <a href="https://code.google.com/p/ziggis/" target="_blank">zigGIS</a> lately? We also had someone asking about <a href="http://www.st-links.com/Pages/default.aspx" target="_blank">ST-Links</a> on the zigGIS mailing list last week. Clearly, there's still a level of interest out there for the problem that zigGIS was designed for.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank"><img alt="ArcGIS and SpatiaLite" height="65%" src="https://a248.e.akamai.net/camo.github.com/c1c86347c63522cb0f5f449b7b9df4209923c3ed/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f53767a6a702e706e67" width="65%" /></a></p>

<div style="font-size: 70%;"><strong>ArcGIS reading SpatiaLite natively, thanks to OGR and Ragi Burhum</strong></div>


<br />


<p>Along those lines, <a href="http://twitter.com/rburhum" target="_blank">Ragi Burhum</a> posted an <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank">OGR Workspace plug-in for ArcGIS</a> up on GitHub. Using OGR is really the magic ticket and the project is available under a BSD license (which Ragi explains very well). The only word to the wise is that pre-built binaries and installers aren't available yet so you Windows/<a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> users will need to get your hands dirty.</p>

<p>I haven't used it yet but I plan to within the next week or so. Stay tuned for a follow up post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prince George's County, Maryland Posts 3-D Planning Model Videos]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/21/prince-georges-county-maryland-posts-3-d-planning-model-videos/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/21/prince-georges-county-maryland-posts-3-d-planning-model-videos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/MichaelShean" target="_blank">Michael Shean</a> of the <a href="http://www.mncppc.org/Commission_Home.html" target="_blank">Maryland-National Capital Parks and Planning Commission</a> (M-NCPPC) announced the availability of videos of 3-D terrain models created to support Planning Board activities in <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;cp=26&amp;gs_id=7&amp;xhr=t&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.,cf.osb&amp;biw=1280&amp;bih=638&amp;ion=1&amp;q=prince+george's+county&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=0x89b64bcdfea9f6a7:0x68f24b5f98fbb7fc,Prince+George's,+MD&amp;gl=us&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=1FzjT_H1Iq-t0AHasqikAw&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CJABELYD" target="_blank">Prince George's County, Maryland</a>. The videos have been made available via Google+ here: <a href="https://plus.google.com/105701421300090504528/posts" target="_blank">https://plus.google.com/105701421300090504528/posts</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/pgcounty.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2703" height="187" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/pgcounty.png?w=300" title="pgcounty" width="300" /></a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I followed up to inquire how the models were created. M-NCPPC analyst Chris Rotondo gave me the following information:</p>

<blockquote>"We build our 3D models in Google SketchUp, using measurements from the site plan images submitted by the developers. Their architectural elevation images are also the source for our model textures. The building model is then loaded into Google Earth Pro, where we complete the scene by adding simple models of adjacent 3D buildings (based on our LiDAR data) and landscaping. We use the video capture tool within Google Earth Pro to record a video showing all perspectives of the potential development, and the same video that is presented to the Prince George?s County Planning Board is the one available on our Google Plus website. We have also worked with ESRI ArcScene 10 to create more complex terrain models and perform 3D viewshed analysis."</blockquote>


<p>The use of <a href="http://www.google.com/earth/index.html" target="_blank">Google</a> (and/or <a href="http://sketchup.google.com/" target="_blank">Trimble</a>) and <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> tools in combination is a theme I see popping up more often in all levels of government. Many shops have long-standing Esri-based workflows but the power of Google for information dissemination and visualization is proving compelling. M-NCPPC does a good job here of making use of both to create good visualizations in support of their core mission. Additionally, I really like the use of a social media channel for dissemination and I'd love to learn more about what drove the decision to use <a href="http://plus.google.com" target="_blank">Google+</a> as opposed to some other channel. (I have no issues with Google+, but am curious what drivers affected the choice.)</p>

<p>This is a great example of the kind work many local governments are doing every day with traditional as well as not-so-traditional geospatial tools. Kudos to the Planning Department GIS staff at M-NCPPC.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS 10.0 and 10.1 Deprecation Plan Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/19/arcgis-100-and-101-deprecation-plan-released/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/19/arcgis-100-and-101-deprecation-plan-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/mikehogan">Mike Hogan</a> tweeted that the Esri deprecation plan for ArcGIS 10.0 and 10.1 is now available. It can be found <a href="http://downloads2.esri.com/support/TechArticles/ArcGIS_10_and__101_Deprecation_Plan.pdf">here</a>. Much of what it contains is not new as Esri has been pretty good about getting information related to 10.x out. Some of the more interesting things (to me) include (comments in parens are mine):</p>

<blockquote>

ArcGIS Server 10.0 is the last release with support for 32-bit operating systems. The next release of ArcGIS Server (10.1) will run natively as a 64-bit application, requiring 64-bit operating systems. (I heard about the native 64-bit move at the Esri UC but I didn't know that included dropping 32-bit. It's not a big deal for me but I can imagine it'll be an impact for many.)

ArcGIS Server 10.0 is the last release supporting publishing non-optimized map documents (MXD files). The next major release will only support publishing optimized maps (MSDs) as that is the best practice for map publishing. (There you have it, no more serving from MXDs after 10.0.)

ArcGIS Server 10.1 will be the last planned release for the ArcGIS Server Web ADFs (Application Developer Framework) for both Microsoft .NET and Java. (We had a small "wake" in San Diego for the ADFs. I won't shed a tear when it's "official.")

ArcGIS Server 10.1 will no longer support local connections (DCOM connections) from Web ADF applications. ArcGIS Server 10.1 will be a web services (REST and SOAP) server only. (This is actually pretty major and the document details the impacts. <strong>If you have any ADF code doing editing and such, read this!</strong>)
</blockquote>


<p>There's a lot of good information in the document, especially pertaining to ArcGIS Server so it's definitely worth a read.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS 9.3.1 SP1]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/09/arcgis-931-sp1/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/09/arcgis-931-sp1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So the <a href="http://support.esri.com/index.cfm?fa=knowledgebase.documentation.viewDoc&amp;PID=17&amp;MetaID=1555">upcoming release</a> of ArcGIS 9.3.1 SP1 <a href="http://downloads2.esri.com/support/documentation/ao_/9.3.1_SP1_Announcement9_1.pdf">addresses a lot of issues</a>. I am somewhat curious why it's not being called 9.3.2. Calling it a service pack seems to be mixing metaphors. Hopefully, ESRI will reconsider before it hits the street.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
