<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Southern Maryland | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/southern-maryland/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:40:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attention Developers - Southern Maryland GiveCamp This Weekend]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/03/17/Attention-Developers-Southern-Maryland-GiveCamp-This-Weekend/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/03/17/Attention-Developers-Southern-Maryland-GiveCamp-This-Weekend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/Default.aspx">Southern Maryland GiveCamp</a> is happening this weekend at <a href="http://www.smcm.edu/">St. Mary's College of Maryland</a> in <a href="http://www.stmaryscity.org/">St. Mary's City</a> for the benefit of <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/Request.aspx">19 local non-profits</a>. If you are unfamiliar with the concept of a GiveCamp, the web site sums it up but here is an excerpt:</p>

<blockquote>
GiveCamp is a weekend-long event where software developers, designers, and database administrators donate their time to create custom software for non-profit organizations. This custom software could be a new website for the nonprofit organization, or a small data-collection application to keep track of members. The only limitation is that the project should be scoped to be able to be completed in a weekend.
</blockquote>


<p>The Southern Maryland GiveCamp is being put together by <a href="http://jpendarvis.blogspot.com/">Jim Pendarvis</a>, who is putting an enormous amount of work into it. I had planned to participate but events have conspired to prevent that, although three of my <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a> co-workers will be there.</p>

<p><strong>Jim still needs volunteers</strong>. If you are a developer in the Washington, DC area, I strongly encourage you to volunteer your time (<a href="http://www.somdgc.org/Tech.aspx">technical</a> and <a href="http://www.somdgc.org/NonTech.aspx">non-technical</a> volunteers are being sought). In addition to helping the community, you'll also get the added benefit of spending the weekend in one of the <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Saint+Marys+City,+St.+Mary's,+Maryland&amp;sll=-33.76676,150.774015&amp;sspn=0.039529,0.077162&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;cd=1&amp;geocode=FT6wRgIdJLRx-w&amp;split=0&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=Saint+Marys+City,+St.+Mary's,+Maryland&amp;ll=38.193942,-76.434288&amp;spn=0.074742,0.154324&amp;z=13&amp;iwloc=A">most beautiful locales in the region</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
