<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Atanas Entchev | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/atanas-entchev/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-23T21:23:04-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Great News About Atanas!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/12/09/great-news-about-atanas/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/12/09/great-news-about-atanas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/atanas">Atanas</a> tweeted this last night:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Out on day 65. Thank you all for everything. Details later on tenthcave.com. <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23freeatanas">#freeatanas</a></p>&mdash; Atanas Entchev (@atanas) <a href="https://twitter.com/atanas/status/144991222040231936" data-datetime="2011-12-09T04:06:15+00:00">December 9, 2011</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>This is the best news possible. I, like many others, will await details on his <a href="http://www.tenthcave.com/">blog</a>. I couldn't be happier for Atanas and his family.</p>

<p>It's good to have you back, my friend.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE</strong>: Here's a little more information from Atanas himself: <a href="http://www.tenthcave.com/2011/12/out-on-day-65.html">http://www.tenthcave.com/2011/12/out-on-day-65.html</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Have a Good Weekend and Remember Atanas]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/21/have-a-good-weekend-and-remember-atanas/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/21/have-a-good-weekend-and-remember-atanas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm about to head out for the weekend. As we get ready to go about our weekend activities, let's not forget that Atanas Entchev and his family are <a href="http://njgeo.org/2011/10/17/colleague-in-need-atanas-entchev/">still</a> being <a href="http://www.cecintl.com/facilities_rr_nj_006.html">detained</a>. If you have not yet donated to the <a href="http://www.tenthcave.com/2011/10/plea-for-help.html">Entchev legal fund</a>, please take time to do so before you head out. Please keep them in your thoughts and <a href="https://writerep.house.gov/writerep/welcome.shtml">take action</a> on their behalf.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="" height="300" src="http://mapbrief.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/atanas.jpg" title="Atanas Entchev" width="300" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Geospatial professional Atanas Entchev<br/><br/></div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Support Atanas Entchev]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/17/support-atanas-entchev/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/17/support-atanas-entchev</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> Atanas' daughter, Christina, is now using his Twitter account to get information out. In addition, she posted a <a href="http://www.tenthcave.com/2011/10/plea-for-help.html">message from Atanas</a> on his blog. He and his son are currently being detained. Also, please see the comment stream to John's post (link below) for additional information about sending letters of support. Letters that are not signed may no be considered so, if sending an e-mail, be sure to send a signed, scanned copy as an attachment.</p>

<hr />


<p><a href="http://njgeo.org/2011/10/17/colleague-in-need-atanas-entchev/">John Reiser posted this piece</a> on the situation of our colleague, Atanas Entchev. Atanas, a native of Bulgaria, came to the United States in 1991, followed soon thereafter by his family. They applied for asylum and have been in litigation regarding their status ever since. The latest opinion, filed on June 23, 2011 by the US Third Circuit Court of Appeals <a href="http://www.ca3.uscourts.gov/opinarch/104369np.pdf">may be found here</a> (.pdf). Says John:</p>

<blockquote>
After emigrating here with his family over twenty years ago to escape political persecution, the US Government is now planning to deport the Entchevs.
</blockquote>


<p>My dealings with Atanas have been almost exclusively through social media channels and I have never met him in person. Despite that, I feel I know him as a result of his open participation in those arenas. His knowledge of the applications of GIS, especially at the municipal level, is top-notch. His contributions to the GIS community, such as the publications listed in his <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=8637855&amp;authType=name&amp;authToken=eUA1&amp;locale=en_US&amp;pvs=pp&amp;trk=ppro_viewmore">LinkedIn profile</a>, as well as his <a href="http://www.directionsmag.com/authors/atanas-entchev/121956">contributions to Directions Magazine</a> and his <a href="http://blog.entchev.com/">blog</a> demonstrate active engagement in his (our) professional community. He is also a small business owner, having founded <a href="http://entchev.com/index.htm">his own GIS services company</a> in 2005.</p>

<p>Of course, legal opinions are only meant to focus on relevant law. As a result, this tapestry of the Entchevs life in America becomes obscured. At one point, the opinion says (LPR = Legal Permanent Resident):</p>

<blockquote>
Although the daughter's adjustment to LPR status may slightly strengthen Entchev's ties to the community, and as a matter of discretion the Department of State may therefore be more inclined to grant a waiver, it is far from clear that the status of Entchev's daughter as an LPR would result in a different outcome for a new waiver application.
</blockquote>


<p>Not being a lawyer, I can't comment on the legal content but this is a very sterile reduction of the Entchevs' life. Those of us who have been linked to Atanas through social media know of his love of sailing, tennis and biking and have seen photos of the Entchevs enjoying the arts around the New York region. So, during two decades of litigation, the legal merits of which have left the Third Circuit Court of Appeals unmoved, the Entchevs have built a rich, textured, wholly American life.</p>

<p>As Atanas's wife Mayia says:</p>

<blockquote>
If you are willing and able to write a letter of recommendation, your contribution will be invaluable to our case, and would be greatly appreciated by our family.
</blockquote>


<p>If you know Atanas, please take time to write a letter in support of him and his family. Instructions are in John's post.</p>

<p>Please also see posts from <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2011/10/17/stand-up-for-atanas-entchev/">James Fee</a>, <a href="http://blog.entchev.com/2011/10/17/a-call-for-help-for-atanas.aspx">Randal Hale</a> and <a href="http://gislounge.com/help-support-geospatial-professional-atanas-entchev/">Caitlin Dempsey</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
