<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: arcgis explorer | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/arcgis-explorer/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-19T06:48:18-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS Explorer Build 900 Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/08/13/arcgis-explorer-build-900-available/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/08/13/arcgis-explorer-build-900-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looks like ArcGIS Explorer 900 has dropped. It was pretty nice in beta and it's good to see that it's out now. It can be downloaded <a href="http://resources.esri.com/arcgisexplorer/900/index.cfm?fa=download">here</a>. The ribbon interface is nice. I've always liked the ribbon but I wasn't a fan of how it was unceremoniously dropped on us in Office.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AGX Build 480 is Corny]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/06/25/agx-build-480-is-corny/"/>
    <updated>2008-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/06/25/agx-build-480-is-corny</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Or maybe it's just this post.</p>

<p>It's always fun in tools such as ArcGIS Explorer and Google Earth to browse around your local area and check out the familiar sites, especially when there is an update. In my case, that means browsing around Southern Maryland. The imagery in build 480 for my area was apparently captured in the fall since corn mazes can be see pretty clearly. Here are the approximate coordinates of a couple:</p>

<p>-76.698488, 38.323529
-76.720778, 38.411094</p>

<p>The second is of particular interest. I took my daughter to that one in Pre-K. I know this because the owners helpfully carved the words "Forrest Hall Farm 2005" into the field. This is all the more interesting since the copyright statement at the corner of the screen would lead you to believe you are looking at 2007 imagery.</p>

<p>This kind of like looking for the errors in movies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coming Up For Air]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/04/30/coming-up-for-air/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/04/30/coming-up-for-air</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Work has a funny way of intruding on blogging. I've been writing a LOT of proposals lately. The funny part is that so have a lot of others that I know. Federal, state, local...they seem to have gotten their budgets all at the same time. There are worse problems to have.</p>

<p>During this period (which I am calling my "Word Period") I have been watching as <a href="http://abegillespie.blogspot.com">Abe</a> and <a href="http://www.paolocorti.net">Paolo</a> get <a href="http://obtusesoft.com">zigGIS</a> out the door. I was able to confirm that I indeed introduced a bug a couple of versions back. I guess you can't win 'em all.</p>

<p>I have been keeping my sanity by slinging a little code here and there. I am hoping to finish up an experimental <a href="http://twitter.com">Twitter</a> client for <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/explorer/index.html">ArcGIS Explorer</a>. Mainly, it's an exercise to get me familiar with the Twitter and <a href="http://twittervision.com/">Twittervision</a> APIs. Plus, it's been a while since I've done anything with AGX. The upcoming builds look exciting so I want to get comfortable with it again.</p>

<p>There's light at the end of tunnel on the proposal stuff so I'm hoping to get a little more technical again here in the next couple of weeks. Until then, I'll have to accept the fact that Word, Paint.Net, Acrobat and Twhirl (all work and no play) have pushed Visual Studio and anything GIS related off my recently used list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS 9.4 Mentioned at FedUC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/02/20/arcgis-9.4-mentioned-at-feduc/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/02/20/arcgis-9.4-mentioned-at-feduc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my first time posting from my Moto Q so forgive any typos.</p>

<p>I just sat through the FedUC opening talk by Jack. There was a lot of talk about 9.3, as would be expected. There was also a lot of talk about positioning AGS support the GeoWeb, including a compelling demo of an AGS-based drive-time analysis in AGX, GE, VE and GMaps. More on that later.</p>

<p>Jack also mentioned some of the work being done to extend the geodatabase at 9.4. Not a whole lot was said about 9.4 (intentionally) except a little about beefed up 3D support in the geodatabase but he did mention the end of the year as a release target.</p>

<p>That's the first concrete thing I had heard about a 9.x release beyond 9.3.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finally Upgrading to 9.2...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/03/08/finally-upgrading-to-9-2/"/>
    <updated>2007-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/03/08/finally-upgrading-to-9-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm a little behind the curve on this but I've had one customer holding out until recently. Now I can finally take the plunge. Who needs sleep? See you on the other side...  ;-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
