<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: navteq | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/navteq/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-08T22:59:36-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Navteq MapReporter]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/11/15/navteq-mapreporter/"/>
    <updated>2007-11-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/11/15/navteq-mapreporter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was attending a working group meeting yesterday and learned of Navteq's <a href="http://mapreporter.com">MapReporter</a> site. It is a system they have implemented to allow users to report data errors to Navteq. The interface seems very intuitive. It even does a good job of picking locations from partial addresses. The image below shows that map interface:</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/11/navteq_mapreporter1.png" title="Navteq MapReporter map interface"><img alt="Navteq MapReporter map interface" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/11/navteq_mapreporter1.thumbnail.png" /></a></p>

<p>Once in, there is a standard form so that you can report the nature of the data error. Here is a screen shot (the address in the map above is not the same one I used in the form, which is why it's blurred here):</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/11/navteq_mapreporter2.png" title="Navteq MapReporter entry from"><img alt="Navteq MapReporter entry from" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/11/navteq_mapreporter2.thumbnail.png" /></a></p>

<p>I was able to pretty quickly report an error. One nice feature is that the system gives you a tracking number so you can check the status of your issue. You can submit a report as a guest or you can create an account. I have not created an account yet to see what that does for you because the page that allows you to create an account (supplying your personal info) does not use SSL (although the login page for those who have accounts does). They may want to fix that. Otherwise, it seems like a nice tool and a good way to keep the database up to date.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
