<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-18T13:37:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off to TUGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/18/off-to-tugis/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T12:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/18/off-to-tugis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow, I&#8217;ll be heading up to the <a href="http://www.towson.edu/tugis/">Towson University GIS (TUGIS) conference</a> with 500 or so of my closest Maryland geo-friends. It has been restructured into a one-day event and the program seems to be very content-rich as a result. I am particularly happy to see more open-source content this year. There&#8217;s an intro session featuring <a href="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</a>, <a href="http://www.postgis.org">PostGIS</a>, <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a>, and <a href="http://geoserver.org">GeoServer</a> presented by <a href="http://www.salisbury.edu/">Salisbury State University</a>. Salisbury was once known as a bastion of <a href="http://www.manifold.net/">Manifold</a> so they&#8217;ve got a long history of thinking outside the Arc. Additionally, there is a session (by Towson University) discussing the use of <a href="http://www.gdal.org">GDAL</a>, <a href="http://www.gdal.org/ogr/">OGR</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/sgillies/shapely">Shapely</a> in the development of a spatial service.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/mdflag.png" alt="Brian Timoney's favorite state flag" title="Brian Timoney's favorite state flag" /></p>

<p>One thing I like about regional GIS conferences like this is that they tend to focus more on solutions to real-world problems instead of the latest technological bells and whistles. I spend so much of my time with my head in Federal requirements that it&#8217;s nice do a reset and get different perspectives on how geospatial technologies are used. I am particulary interested to hear the keynote from <a href="http://twitter.com/learondalby">Learon Dalby</a> of <a href="http://www.sanborn.com/">Sanborn</a> and formerly of the <a href="http://www.gis.state.ar.us/">Arkansas GIO office</a>. I had the pleasure of working with Learon and the AGIO team on a project a couple of years ago and am impressed with what they accomplished.</p>

<p>I appreciate the new format of TUGIS as a one-day event is much easier to fit into the schedule. I&#8217;m looking forward to it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A #LazyWeb Compendium of Python Resources for Beginners]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/17/a-lazyweb-compendium-of-python-resources-for-beginners/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-17T15:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/17/a-lazyweb-compendium-of-python-resources-for-beginners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A friend who is in the midst of a career change and moving into the GIS world asked me for some pointers to resources for getting started with Python. I threw the question out to Twitter (with a similar variation also posted to Google+):</p>

<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Can anyone recommend any good online Python training sources for beginners? Asking for a friend in the midst of a career change.</p>&mdash; Bill Dollins (@billdollins) <a href="https://twitter.com/billdollins/status/313263420923338753">March 17, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async src="http://blog.geomusings.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>I got a couple of requests to summarize any information I received, which seemed reasonable. I got quite a few responses and here are some links:</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://learnpythonthehardway.org/">Learn Python the Hard Way</a> - This one got the most mentions<br/>
<a href="http://inventwithpython.com/">Invent With Python</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.greenteapress.com/">Green Tea Press</a><br/>
<a href="http://newcoder.io/">New Coder</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.codecademy.com/tracks/python">Codecademy</a><br/>
<a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/science/computer-science">Khan Academy</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.diveintopython.net/">Dive Into Python</a> - Note: I heard positive and negative on this one.<br/>
<a href="http://www.realpython.com/e-book/">Real Python</a><br/>
<a href="http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-00-introduction-to-computer-science-and-programming-fall-2008/index.htm">MIT Introduction to Computer Science and Programming</a><br/>
<a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/cs101">Udacity</a></p>

<p>I can&#8217;t claim to have checked out all of them, but I consider the recommendations to have come from trusted sources. So, if you&#8217;re <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/30/yes-you-need-to-code/">looking to expand your GIS expertise by adding some Python knowledge</a>, these may be a good place to start. Not all of them are free-of-charge since that wasn&#8217;t one of my friend&#8217;s requirements.</p>

<p>Additionally, Dan Dye informs me that the PyBulls Python interest group at the University of South Florida will take up this question and post a document with a list of resources on GitHub. Be sure to keep an eye on <a href="https://github.com/pybulls/">https://github.com/pybulls/</a> . Thank you!</p>

<p>Many thanks to <a href="http://twitter.com/hugoestr">Hugo Estrada</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/DonMeltz">Don Meltz</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/IndyGIS">Aaron Burgess</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/JCSanford">Jason Sanford</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/dandye">Dan Dye</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/swfoundry">Christopher Moore</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/scw">Shaun Walbridge</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/jmwdesign">Jason Wheatley</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/102903916051293271489/posts">Wes Herche</a>, and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/110136604428694315510/posts">Jorge Sanz</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any other good online resources for getting started with Python, feel free to leave them in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc2Earth: Choose Your 'Cloud']]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/02/28/arc2earth-choose-your-cloud/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-28T06:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/02/28/arc2earth-choose-your-cloud</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For various reasons, I can&#8217;t attend today&#8217;s inaugural <a href="http://fedgeoday.com/">FedGeoDay</a> at the Woolly Mammoth Theatre in Washington, DC, though I&#8217;ll be watching the hashtag with great interest. Jack Flood of <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/">Arc2Earth</a>, however, has already posted his slides to SlideShare:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/16811994" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jflood3/fedgeodays-022013" title="Fedgeodays 022013" target="_blank">Fedgeodays 022013</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jflood3" target="_blank">Jack Flood</a></strong> </div></p>

<!--more-->


<p>While neither <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcMap</a> nor Arc2Earth are open-source themselves, Jack points out that Arc2Earth acts as a bridge between ArcMap and several geospatial hosting platforms that are built on open-source technology but, also just as important, are successful at making data more openly available. These platforms include <a href="http://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> and <a href="http://mapbox.com/">MapBox</a>, among many others.</p>

<p>Many people use, and prefer, ArcMap has their desktop cartography and analysis tool. I view Arc2Earth as an enabling technology that allows users to continue to be productive with ArcMap while also allowing them to retain control of how they direct their GIS investments in terms of publishing and hosting their maps and data.</p>

<p>Disclaimer: <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">My company</a> is an Arc2Earth reseller.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yes, You Need to Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/30/yes-you-need-to-code/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T14:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/30/yes-you-need-to-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past year, I&#8217;ve been involved in searching for GIS analysts a number of times. As a result, I&#8217;ve noticed a few patterns:</p>

<ol>
<li>There are a lot of analysts out there looking for jobs. Every time I run an ad, I get at least 100 resumes from people of various levels of experience and education.</li>
<li>The vast majority of those that I call to pre-screen have not done any meaningful coding of any kind. This includes Python, which has been shipping with ArcGIS for several versions now.</li>
<li>Of those that do have some coding experience, many do not show it on their resumes. I find this particularly interesting as I can&#8217;t imagine why a person would choose not to list all relevant skills or experience.</li>
</ol>


<p>I am very publicly on the record that I think some form of coding skill is essential for any GIS analyst entering the workforce today. My reasoning here is fairly straightforward.</p>

<ol>
<li>The &#8220;IS&#8221; in &#8220;GIS&#8221; stands for &#8220;information system.&#8221; This means &#8220;computers.&#8221; Actually, according to one of my professors in the late &#8217;80s, an information system doesn&#8217;t technically have to involve computers but this is 2013 and even brewing a cup of coffee involves a computer.</li>
<li>The &#8220;G&#8221; in &#8220;GIS&#8221; stands for &#8220;geography.&#8221; (Don&#8217;t worry, the revelations will keep coming.) Geography is intensely mathematical. I suppose, in the interest of accuracy, I should state that some segments of geography are less mathematical than others but I think it&#8217;s safe to say that the elements of the science that are addressed by GIS involve a lot of math. Take, for instance, coordinate reference systems. That one small but important part of geography can separate the wheat from the chaff quickly.</li>
<li>Computers use code to do math.</li>
</ol>


<p>Modern GIS software is complicated and comes with a lot of capability by default. Just look at the default UI for ArcMap or QGIS and you&#8217;ll see a lot of tools at your fingertips. In other words, there are a lot of buttons to push. This is fine but I&#8217;d wager that these software tools expose less than 10% of their full capability through their default interfaces.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The reason for that is that there are simply too many use cases in geography to design into a piece of software by default. That is why these tools, and most other GIS software, ship with APIs. (&#8220;Ship&#8221; is a loose concept with open-source but please grant me license.) These APIs expose the full capability of the software so that users may customize it to their needs. That means coding. For both <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcGIS</a> and <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a>, that can mean Python but there are lots of other choices as well.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;">
<img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/globalmaptiles.png" />
</div>


<br/><br/>


<p>If you choose to get by with just using the GUI tools, you are doing yourself two disservices:</p>

<ol>
<li>You are placing yourself at the mercy of others who can code to get around to building the customizations you need.</li>
<li>You are allowing your skills to erode by not using a significant amount of capability.</li>
</ol>


<p>So you need to code to some extent. You need to in order to automate complicated tasks you do regularly, or read in data that&#8217;s in some oddball format, or use some capability of your GIS-du-jour that isn&#8217;t exposed out of the box, or to make that web map sing, or for any of a number of other reasons. Luckily, you have a wealth of information at your fingertips. It is called open-source geospatial software. I can already hear the protests: You learned on ArcGIS in school. You are comfortable with ArcGIS and you like it. Fine, keep using it.</p>

<p>But while you&#8217;re using ArcGIS, also check out the source code for open-source libraries like <a href="https://github.com/sgillies/shapely">Shapely</a> or <a href="http://trac.osgeo.org/geos/">GEOS</a> or <a href="http://www.gdal.org/">GDAL</a> or other commonly used (even under the hood of ArcGIS) tools. You learned the math in school. You toughed out these concepts and you understand them. Now look at the compiled knowledge of a lot of smart programmers to see how the concepts are concretely implemented in code. The process will, at a minimum, make you a better ArcGIS user because you&#8217;ll understand what&#8217;s going on under the hood. The truth is, even if ArcGIS isn&#8217;t directly using one of those open-source libraries, it&#8217;s probably using an ESRI-developed implementation of a standard algorithm. It&#8217;s similar enough that you&#8217;ll be able to understand the behavior and that will help you better bind your own customizations to their closed-source API.</p>

<p>I say this because it worked for me. I am a programmer by training and passion. I heard the phrase &#8220;GIS&#8221; once, in passing, during a lecture in college. Yet, my first job was in the GIS field. Needless to say, I had a lot of learning to do. Most of it came at the hands of some very patient geographers. The first tools I was exposed to were the proprietary tools of MapInfo and ESRI (with a smattering of Intergraph). I was able to soak in what the geographers were telling me and bang against those APIs to build some useful tools but the light bulb really came on for me when I began reading the source code of open-source projects. There, laid out before me, was what the software was <em>really</em> doing.</p>

<p>Today, I work with a mixture of open-source and proprietary tools but the majority of my paying work is still in the Esri realm. My exposure to open-source has, however, made me better with it because it has deepened my understanding.</p>

<p>Not everyone can be a professional software developer as it takes a certain mindset to do it all of the time. But, in the GIS market of 2013, everyone needs to have some understanding of some kind of coding, whether <a href="http://python.org/">Python</a> or <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R</a> or <a href="http://d3js.org/">Javascript</a> or something else.</p>

<p>One other side note: Over the past year, I have also advertised for software developers with results that are opposite of what I see with analysts. There are very few applicants and many that I see have been out of work for a while, have no GIS background and spent a lot of years working with older tools. These are &#8220;blue bird&#8221; applicants hoping to catch on. In short, there is a gulf between the high demand for GIS-literate programmers and the miniscule supply. Having the ability to code, and showing it on your resume, can be what separates you from the pack of 100 other analysts applying for the same position.</p>

<p>So, yes, you need to code.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Checking out the GDAL/OGR Plugin for ArcGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/22/checking-out-the-gdal-slash-ogr-plugin-for-arcgis/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-22T13:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/22/checking-out-the-gdal-slash-ogr-plugin-for-arcgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back, I <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis/">blogged</a> the availability of a <a href="http://www.gdal.org/">GDAL/OGR</a> <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/">plug-in for ArcGIS</a> desktop by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=14926439&amp;locale=en_US">Ragi Burhum at AmigoCloud</a>. At the time, I was hoping to dig into it fairly quickly but that didn&#8217;t happen and I&#8217;m finally getting to it. Anyone who has followed this blog for a while knows that I have had <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2006/12/17/postgis-and-arcgis-9.1/">more</a> than a <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/07/10/consuming-georss-in-arcmap-with-inmemoryworkspacefactory/">passing</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/03/cutting-tiles-for-arcgis-server-using-tilemill/">interest</a> in <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/02/importing-data-from-geocommons-into-arcmap/">integrating</a> new <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/">data</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/24/togeojson-and-towkt-for-the-esri-fgdb-api/">sources</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/08/09/taking-a-look-at-pgmap/">with</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/11/15/fgeojson/">ArcGIS</a> over the years. This comes from the fact that, as a technology geek, I am fascinated by all forms of technology and enjoy the process of integration and, as a consultant providing services to the Federal Government, most of my customers have standardized on Esri tools. Integrations such as GeoRSS, PostGIS, GeoCommons and GeoJSON have directly benefitted my customers for real-world applications so I continue look for ways to remove the barriers between them and the data they seek.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://images-mediawiki-sites.thefullwiki.org/07/3/6/0/1583563936968042.png" /></div>




<!--more-->


<p>The GDAL/OGR plug-in caught my attention because it purports to add support for any format supported by GDAL and OGR, similar to the way <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a> leverages them for a wide variety of format support. To get going with it, I downloaded the source and built it in Visual Studio 2010. I only ran into a couple of minor issues. First, a had previously installed the Windows build of OGR on my machine using the <a href="http://www.gisinternals.com/sdk/PackageList.aspx?file=release-1600-gdal-1-9-2-mapserver-6-2-0.zip">distribution from GIS Internals</a>. The project as it came down from GitHub couldn&#8217;t find the OGR and OSR bindings for C#, so I had to resolve that trivial issue. Next, the plug-in was built for use in ArcGIS 10.1 but I was using 10.0. Because some new interfaces were introduced, the <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/blob/master/src/OGRPlugin/OGRPlugin/ogrplugin_utils.cs">current code</a> contains a declaration of  type ISpatialReferenceFactory4, which is a 10.1 interface. I needed to change that to ISpatialReferenceFactory3 to make it work with 10.0. That has been the only change I have needed to make so far to account for the version differences. I plan to add a compiler directive in my fork of the project to account for that and submit it back once I can test it.</p>

<p>As I said before, I previously had installed GDAL/OGR so it was already on my machine and my GDAL_DATA environment variable was set. When I built the plug-in and attempted to use it in ArcMap, it threw an error when I tried adding a GeoJSON layer (also with SpatiaLite) that it could not find my gcs.csv file, which is in my GDAL_DATA location. With a little investigation, I found that the code was resetting that variable at runtime to point to the location of the plug-in binary. I copied the files there and it worked well from then on. I&#8217;ll probably try to add a way to check for the existence of that variable before setting it. None of these issues were major and I think they were reasonable design choices up front so I am not concerned by them.</p>

<p>At that point, I was able to quickly add GeoJSON and SpatiaLite layers to my data frame in ArcMap. This is pretty exciting to me since the ability to support a wide range of data types was a long-standing goal of zigGIS and I&#8217;m glad that Ragi has conquered that with this work.</p>

<p>Because the layers are added using a plug-in workspace, they are full read-only citizens inside ArcGIS. For example, I was able to wire up a couple of models using ModelBuilder and execute clips (clipping a GeoJSON layer with a SpatiaLite layer) and buffers and simple tests. I&#8217;m really not a huge ModelBuilder user but I thought it would be a good way to test things out.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;">
<img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/buffer.png" />
<div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Model to test a simple buffer<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>The model above produced a 50-foot buffer around Amtrak rail lines from NTAD 2012 in GeoJSON format. The resultant buffer was written to a file geodatabase. As you can see from the image below, it worked like a charm.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;">
<img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/buffer_result_small.png" />
<div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Results of the buffer model.<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>I achieved similar success with a clip operation so I&#8217;m sufficiently confident in trying to package the plug-in up and put it in the hands of some of the analysts with whom I work. All-in-all, the plug-in is a nice piece of work. It&#8217;s still not fully baked but it&#8217;s a very solid start and deserves a closer look if you&#8217;re looking to expand the reach of your ArcGIS investment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[js.geo Day One]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/14/js-dot-geo-day-one/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-14T18:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/14/js-dot-geo-day-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I attended the <a href="http://geojs.eventbrite.com/">JS.geo</a> conference at the Colorado University Denver campus. It looked like about 100 or so came out for the event. I was able to catch up with <a href="http://twitter.com/cwhelm">Chris Helm</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/briantimoney">Brian Timoney</a> the night before and they told me the event took off faster than they had originally expected. I think this speaks to two things: 1) the level of interest in Javascript as a solution for geospatial applications and 2) the fast pace of innovation in the Javascript community that has a lot of people looking for ways to stay abreast of the latest developments.</p>

<p>What follows is an overview based on some of the notes I took. I wasn&#8217;t always writing as I sometimes just stopped to listen and I&#8217;ll probably follow up with more details later.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/jsgeo13.png" /></div>


<p>Data reduction was strong current running under the day. With the rise of newer libraries that enable more sophisticated capabilities in the browser, there is increased recognition of the need to reduce the amount of data passing over the wire. For geometry, <a href="https://github.com/mbostock/topojson">TopoJSON</a> is getting a lot of attention here. It delivers topologically correct data which reduces data by removing redundant geometry such coincident arcs between polygons and such. The output reminds me of an old <a href="http://www.gdal.org/ogr/drv_avcbin.html">ARC/INFO coverage</a> and is providing stunning results in reducing the size of geometries when compared to <a href="http://geojson.org">GeoJSON</a> or Esri JSON. <a href="http://twitter.com/andrewxhill">Andrew Hill</a> of <a href="http://vizzuality.com">Vizzuality</a> mentioned that <a href="http://cartodb.com">CartoDB</a> currently has support for TopoJSON in staging. He also discussed strategies they use to reduce the size of feature and attribute data. This &#8220;data cubing&#8221; strategy turns out to similar to approaches that are commonplace in the financial industry. This serves as a reminder to look around and see what others are doing to solve similar problems.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>One a related note, the reduction of application code being delivered to the browser is also a focus. This was probably best illustrated by <a href="http://twitter.com/mattpriour">Matt Priour&#8217;s</a> talk on <a href="http://openlayers.org">OpenLayers</a>. The fact that there are now three builds (full, mobile, light) as well as a focus on being more modular in version 3. <a href="http://twitter.com/pmbatty">Peter Batty</a>, in his demo of <a href="http://www.ubisense.net/en/">Ubisense</a>, made a good case for intelligent balance between server-side and client-side processing to achieve good performance.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.khronos.org/webgl/">WebGL</a> got a lot of attention from a number of speakers, with <a href="http://twitter.com/brendankenny">Brendan Kenny</a> of Google showing work he has done, including a Javascript port of GLUTessellation. Jeremy Bartley of Esri gave a lightning talk about <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/cityengine">CityEngine</a>, which is based on WebGL. WebGL is widely seen as the open solution to graphics performance that may finally kill the need for plug-ins. In side discussions, Jeremy talked about how WebGL will figure more into the previously discussed data reduction problem. The reality is that both servers and clients are getting much better at handling large data sets but the same can&#8217;t necessarily be said for the wires that connect them.</p>

<p>GeoJSON continues to get a lot of love. It continues to be, in my opinion, the motor oil for the engine that is web mapping. It will be interesting see how the separation of concerns between GeoJSON and TopoJSON evolves, but I think GeoJSON will continue to be an important syntax.</p>

<p>While the majority of the discussion focused on browsers, <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> got significant attention. <a href="http://twitter.com/willwhitedc">Will White</a> of <a href="http://mapbox.com">MapBox</a> gave a good talk about the evolution of Node and the advantages of its non-blocking I/O model. One statistic he gave was surprising: he said 6 of the top 12 contributors on GitHub are Node contributors. That speaks loudly to the rapid evolution of Node as well as the interest in Javascript. Will put out a call to the geospatial community to build out the geospatial capabilities of Node. Later in the day, we saw a good lightning talk that showed Node processing real-time data and feeding a number of D3 visualizations.</p>

<p>While Matt Priour and <a href="https://twitter.com/atogle">Aaron Ogle</a> opened with great talks on OpenLayers and <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</a>, respectively, the clear star of the client-side show was <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3</a> (although Aaron&#8217;s walkshed analysis in Leaflet was cool). There were lots of great visualizations (as well as nods to TopoJSON). While the D3&#8217;s support for projections is getting a lot of attention from geospatial developers, I am more interested in its holistic approach to data visualization. In D3, geo is one way to look at data, but not the central way. Because of this, D3 provides an integrated capability to have multiple data visualizations in an application without overloading with a ton of libraries.</p>

<p>I am already well past tl;dr on this post and I have to catch a plane. Many of the URL talks were great but I&#8217;ll follow up with some more details. All-in-all, I think the event was quite a success and I&#8217;m glad I came.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment Period Open for GeoPackage Specification Draft]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/09/comment-period-open-for-geopackage-specification-draft/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-09T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/09/comment-period-open-for-geopackage-specification-draft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) has <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/pressroom/pressreleases/1756">published a draft GeoPackage specification for comment</a>. The GeoPackage specification attempts to create a non-proprietary means for packaging and exchanging all geospatial data in all its forms (vector, raster, and tiles). A couple of things that jump out at me:</p>

<ul>
<li>It calls out <a href="https://sqlite.org/">SQLite</a> as the reference implementation of a GeoPackage container</li>
<li>It calls out <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/">SpatiaLite</a> 4 as the reference implementation of a vector feature store</li>
<li>It does not call out a reference implementation for rasters or tiles</li>
<li>It does not mention exchange of cartography.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Although the draft references the <a href="http://mapbox.com/developers/mbtiles/">MBTiles</a> specification and uses it as an example of a pure SQL method of storing tiles, it does not call out MBTiles as the chosen storage approach nor does it mention MBTiles as a reference implementation. The draft should not be read as &#8220;SpatiaLite + MBTiles.&#8221;</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://www.publicdomainpictures.net/view-image.php?image=9097&picture=empty-cardboard-boxes"><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/boxes.png" /></a></div>


<p>I think, in 2013, anything that attempts to do what GeoPackage sets out to do should have some provision for cartography. I would prefer CSS-like approach (such as <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/">CartoCSS</a>) and will say so when I submit comments but I would suspect that future discussion of cartography, if any, will probably start with SLD. For now, tiles can fill the gap.</p>

<p>So comments are open, give it a look and tell OGC what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Ready for JS.geo]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/08/getting-ready-for-js-dot-geo/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T15:50:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/08/getting-ready-for-js-dot-geo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m looking forward to next week&#8217;s <a href="http://geojs.eventbrite.com/">JS.geo</a> event in Denver. It is a small event, spearheaded by <a href="http://twitter.com/cwhelm">Chris Helm</a> of <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a>, that focuses on the use of Javascript in geospatial applications. Although I have been more vocal in my <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/python/">recent explorations with Python</a>, I&#8217;ve probably done as much, if not more, work with Javascript over the past 18 months.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://mapbrief.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/no_plugin.jpg" /></div>


<p>The pace of innovation with Javascript in the geospatial area has been staggering. It seems like only a short time ago that the options for working with geospatial applications were <a href="http://openlayers.org/">OpenLayers</a> and the <a href="http://help.arcgis.com/en/webapi/javascript/arcgis/">Esri Javascript API</a>. The rapid advent of tools such as <a href="http://www.geoext.org/">GeoExt</a>, <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</a>, and many others has really lead to a explosion of capability. Of course, the recent buzz has been about <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3</a>, which tackles a wide range of data visualization problems, including geo. D3 is of particular interest because it is tackling the issue of projection in the browser, freeing applications from the dominance of Web Mercator.</p>

<p>Of course, it&#8217;s not been all about the browser, either as <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> has made abundantly clear. One of the most effective desktop applications for cartographic design, <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/">TileMill</a>, is built with Node, among other tools.</p>

<p>The maturity of Javascript as a tool for geospatial development is such that I am at the point that, if it weren&#8217;t for government customers that are <a href="http://mapbrief.com/2011/10/13/web-mapping-continues-to-pay-for-the-sins-of-internet-explorer/">still standardized on Internet Explorer 8</a> or older, a plug-in-based environment would not be my first choice for a new application.</p>

<p>As for the JS.geo event itself, I am intrigued by its small, focused nature. It doesn&#8217;t seem to be as informal as an unconference but may be easier to digest than the typical geo event. It will also be great to catch up with the Front Range crowd.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite 4.1.0 Beta Preview Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/03/spatialite-4-dot-1-0-beta-available/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T08:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/03/spatialite-4-dot-1-0-beta-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/spatialite-users">SpatiaLite Google Group</a> this morning, Sandro Furieri announced the availability of a beta preview of SpatiaLite 4.1.0. The primary focus of this preview is to get early comment on new capabilities supporting the storage, validation, and query of XML documents.</p>

<p>More information about this update <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=XmlBlob+and+VirtualXPath">can be found here</a>. Says Sandro:</p>

<blockquote>
The main goals of these recently introduced enhancements are:<br/>
- storing XML Documents directly within the DBMS <br/>
- supporting XML validation<br/>
- supporting plain SQL queries on behalf of XML Documents <br/>
  via canonical XPath expressions<br/>
<br/>
Implementing directly into the Spatial DBMS a common core of 
XML-oriented features surely is an interesting and useful option,
just considering that ISO- and INSPIRE-Metadata or SLD/SE Styles 
are fully based on XML.
</blockquote>


<p>Although I find myself working more with <a href="http://geojson.org">GeoJSON</a> and <a href="http://developmentseed.org/blog/2011/feb/09/introducing-carto-css-map-styling-language/">CartoCSS</a> these days, I think support for XML is a good step for SpatiaLite. There are some very mature use cases based on XML, as Sandro points out. While <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/sld">SLD</a> is not my favorite, this may keep it on my radar. Also, it would be interesting to see how this new capability would possibly affect the evolution of the <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/projects/groups/geopackageswg">OGC GeoPackage draft specification</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Center for Spatial Law and Policy Announces Geospatial Data Licensing Workshop]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/12/27/center-for-spatial-law-and-policy-announces-geospatial-data-licensing-workshop/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-27T08:50:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/12/27/center-for-spatial-law-and-policy-announces-geospatial-data-licensing-workshop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Kevin Pomfret announced this morning that the <a href="http://www.spatiallaw.com/">Center for Spatial Law and Policy</a> will be hosting a workshop on geospatial data licensing.</p>

<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Centre for Spatial Law and Policy to host a Geospatial Data Licensing Workshop <a href="http://t.co/rYFXysrK" title="http://tinyurl.com/d6e6mgm">tinyurl.com/d6e6mgm</a></p>&mdash; SpatialLaw&amp;Policy (@kpomfret) <a href="https://twitter.com/kpomfret/status/284292999792447489" data-datetime="2012-12-27T13:41:47+00:00">December 27, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script async src="http://blog.geomusings.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>Data licensing has always been an important issue but seems to be <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2012/12/26/this-isnt-the-road-network-you-are-looking-for/">moving to the forefront</a> as demand for quality spatial data grows. This workshop could prove to be timely. It is being held on 24 January 2013 in Tysons Corner, VA. Details can be found on the <a href="http://spatiallaw.blogspot.com/2012/12/geospatial-data-licensing-workshop.html">Spatial Law and Policy blog</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[geoMusings Has Moved - Please Update Your Links]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/12/24/geomusings-has-moved-please-update-your-links/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/12/24/geomusings-has-moved-please-update-your-links</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At long last, I have finally completed the transition of this blog from Wordpress (hosted on wordpress.com) to <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> (hosted for now on Github Pages). As I indicated <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/05/06/this-blog-has-a-new-address/">sometime back</a>, I have been planning this for a while. The move is now complete and, although the old site will remain up for the foreseeable future, no new content will be posted there.</p>

<p>Links to the old &#8220;geobabble.wordpress.com&#8221; URL will no longer automatically forward to &#8220;blog.geomusings.com&#8221;. Those links will go to the old Wordpress site, rather than the new location. While this may not be the worst thing in the world, I highly recommend updating any links you may have to point to this URL. I have taken pains to ensure that links using &#8220;blog.geomusings.com&#8221; redirect correctly but there may be some hiccups. If you notice issues with links to older posts, please feel free to contact me using the information on my &#8220;About&#8221; page and I&#8217;ll try to help resolve it.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Wordpress.com had perfectly justifiable restrictions on what you could do with a blog (no embedded Javascript, for instance). Over time, I began to feel those limitations more and more. I had originally just planned to move to a self-hosted Wordpress site but I began to reconsider that earlier this year. A <a href="http://spatiallyadjusted.com">couple</a> of <a href="http://geojason.info/">blogs</a> I follow were running on Octopress/<a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> and I was impressed with the performance of the static content. Additionally, I decided I wanted to use a platform that could help stretch me as a programmer. I was not particularly interested in becoming more proficient at PHP (Wordpress) but I was interested in getting more comfortable with Ruby (Octopress/Jekyll), as well as Javascript and CSS.</p>

<p>There were other considerations but I won&#8217;t belabour the point. Thanks for your continued support and please update any links that you may still have pointing to the old &#8220;geobabble&#8221; URL.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Put Planet Geospatial to Work for You]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m happy to see that <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2012/11/24/planet-geospatial-the-way-forward/" target="_blank">James has decided keep Planet Geospatial going</a>. It&#8217;s been one of the more consistently valuable resources in the community since its inception and it&#8217;s good that it will continue.</p>

<p>While I&#8217;m looking forward to seeing how <a href="http://twitter.com/cageyjames" target="_blank">James</a> evolves <a href="http://planetgs.com" target="_blank">Planet Geospatial</a>, there are ways to more efficiently extract value out of its current state right now. At its core, Planet Geospatial is an RSS feed. RSS can safely be called &#8220;venerable&#8221; nowadays, but it still does what it does very well.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3002" height="400" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/postgis_evernote1.png" title="PostGIS items from Planet Geospatial in Evernote" width="640" /></p>

<p>Two of my favorite tools for culling down the firehose that is Planet Geospatial are <a href="http://ifttt.com" target="_blank">IFTTT</a> (the title of this post is a riff on the IFTTT motto) and <a href="http://evernote.com/" target="_blank">Evernote</a>. If you&#8217;re not familiar with IFTTT, you should be. It reminds me of a more-intuitive Yahoo Pipes and it allows you to mix channels, triggers, and actions to automate processes of your choosing. It&#8217;s become by preferred method of synchronizing my blog with social media and for filtering data sources. It also drives the <a href="http://twitter.com/QGISInfo" target="_blank">Unofficial QGIS Info</a> Twitter account. <!--more--></p>

<p>Evernote is becoming a key tool for me to store and access notes and other kinds of information. The fact that it runs on every device I own in addition to browsers makes it very useful for me as I move between customer locations.</p>

<p>When James first posted that he was wondering what to do with Planet Geospatial, I shared with him an IFTTT recipe that inserts posts from Planet Geospatial about <a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> into an Evernote notebook. He kindly tweeted it.</p>

<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Try this IFTTT Recipe: Log PostGIS Items from Planet Geospatial to Evernote. <a href="https://t.co/z5hOxPqH" title="https://ifttt.com/recipes/67215">ifttt.com/recipes/67215</a></p>&mdash; James Fee (@cageyjames) <a href="https://twitter.com/cageyjames/status/272025049526050816" data-datetime="2012-11-23T17:13:20+00:00">November 23, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script src="http://blog.geomusings.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>I usually have three to four such filters running, depending upon topics that I&#8217;m watching. Currently, I&#8217;m grabbing posts about PostGIS, <a href="http://geojson.org" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>, and <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/" target="_blank">CartoCSS</a>. These filters allow me to peruse the posts at my leisure without worrying about missing them. I can delete them from my notebook or save them as I see fit. For me, it&#8217;s like having a DVR for Planet Geospatial.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Planet Geospatial is an information source. It just happens to be an information source that&#8217;s based on a mature, open, well-documented, and widely adopted standard. As such, there&#8217;s no need to wait for James to evolve it into something else. We can take it and transform it to meet our needs and then share it back. It&#8217;s been a great community resource for a long time; it will be fun to see what the community can do with it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite for Android Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-for-android-available/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-for-android-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On what seems to be turning into <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> Monday, Sandro Furieri also announced on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/spatialite-users?pli=1" target="_blank">SpatiaLite Google Group</a> the availability of a stable version of SpatiaLite for Android.</p>

<p>I am happy to see that this version was developed and contributed back by the <a href="http://www.agc.army.mil/" target="_blank">US Army Geospatial Center</a>. The fact that they contributed back to the project under a standard open-source license is a nice step from a DoD organization.</p>

<p>The message is quoted below:</p>

<blockquote>
Hi List,

I&#8217;m really proud to announce you all that finally a rock solid stable and really easy-to-be-deployed binary porting of SpatiaLite for the Android platform is now available for download [1].

[1] <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=splite-android" target="_blank">https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=splite-android</a>

Many thanks to the U.S. Army Geospatial Center [2] who very generously contributed this highly appreciated and really useful resource under a genuine free software license (LGPLv3).

[2] <a href="http://www.agc.army.mil/" target="_blank">http://www.agc.army.mil/</a>

A detailed tutorial [3] explaining how-to deploy and use SpatiaLite on Android platforms has been kindly contributed by Andrea Antonello, who spent many long hours during the last week while performing a thorough testing of SpatiaLite-Android, then deciding to publicly share his experiences with the SpatiaLite community. Feel absolutely free to pay a beer to Andrea; he&#8217;ll surely appreciate ;-)

[3] <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=spatialite-android-tutorial" target="_blank">https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=spatialite-android-tutorial</a>

enjoy, Sandro
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite 4.0 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-4-0-released/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-4-0-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It looks like it was a busy weekend for Sandro Furieri and the rest of the <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/index" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> team as version 4.0 was announced on Sunday. There are a number of changes, so it&#8217;s best to <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=switching-to-4.0" target="_blank">catch up on them</a> before switching over.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.manningltg.com/fixture_show.php?f_id=GCQ-164&amp;f_desc=Spatialite%20(Quartz%20Halogen)"><img alt="" height="300" src="http://www.manningltg.com/product_imgs/web/GCQ-164_1.jpg" title="Not this SpatiaLite" width="490" /></a><div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">Not this SpatiaLite</div></div>


<p>I have a couple of Federal customers that are integrating SpatiaLite into their workflows so I&#8217;ll need to take a day or so to assess impacts any impacts there. Looks like the perfect way to slide back into work after a long weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Biggest News You May Have Missed...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/19/the-biggest-news-you-may-have-missed/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/19/the-biggest-news-you-may-have-missed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you missed it, this tweet floated across the Twitters last week:</p>

<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Blogged: TileMill Connect - Open Mxd Documents in @<a href="https://twitter.com/mapbox">mapbox</a> TileMill <a href="http://t.co/hDicr4z0" title="http://bit.ly/WbBOKW">bit.ly/WbBOKW</a></p>&mdash; Arc2Earth (@Arc2Earth) <a href="https://twitter.com/Arc2Earth/status/269194049230102528" data-datetime="2012-11-15T21:43:57+00:00">November 15, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script src="http://blog.geomusings.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>Yes, the team at <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> is apparently working on a new feature in <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/services/sync/">Arc2Earth Sync,</a> called TileMill Connect, that will link <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcMap</a> MXDs with <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/">TileMill</a>. This will allow users to migrate their ArcMap cartography into TileMill to take advantage of the rich tools there as well as the potential for version control and cut/paste sharing of techniques and best practices enabled by <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/">CartoCSS</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/bFlood">Brian Flood</a> followed that up today with a short video showing it in action.</p>

<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>quick TileMill Connect demo video showing how it works. <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23mapbox">#mapbox</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23arcgis">#arcgis</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23tilemill">#tilemill</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23arc2earth">#arc2earth</a> <a href="http://t.co/8WFdqCqH" title="http://bit.ly/QTWqpH">bit.ly/QTWqpH</a></p>&mdash; Arc2Earth (@Arc2Earth) <a href="https://twitter.com/Arc2Earth/status/270631991110692865" data-datetime="2012-11-19T20:57:49+00:00">November 19, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script src="http://blog.geomusings.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>No word on a timetable for this feature, but I can&#8217;t wait to kick the tires. I am especially intrigued by the pseudo <a href="http://www.postgis.org">PostGIS</a> proxy service that enables connections to ArcGIS data sources.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A GIS Day Map for World Diabetes Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/14/a-gis-day-map-for-world-diabetes-day/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/14/a-gis-day-map-for-world-diabetes-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is World Diabetes Day. It also happens to be GIS Day so I thought a map (not mine) of new diagnoses would be in order:</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.idf.org/diabetesatlas/5e/diabetes-in-the-young"><img alt="" height="80%" src="http://www.idf.org/sites/default/files/da5/Map%202.5%20New%20cases%20of%20type%201%20diabetes.jpg" title="New cases of Type 1 diabetes in children, 2011" width="80%" /></a><div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">Source: International Diabetes Federation Diabetes Atlas, Fifth Edition (Click image to visit)</div></div>


<br/>


<p>To learn more about Type 1 Diabetes, <a href="http://www.jdrf.org/index.cfm?page_id=101982" target="_blank">please visit the JDRF</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Geospatial Workflows]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve had a couple of people ask me recently about the geospatial tools I use. Year-over-year, that answer changes but here&#8217;s how I answer that right now:</p>

<p>As a Federal contractor, I spend a lot of time working with the <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> stack during my work day. A few years ago, I added a few open-source geospatial tools into my tool set and, since then, have also done a respectable amount to consulting work them as well. The balance between the two varies over time, depending on the requirements of individual customers and projects. Lately, commercial customers have seemed much more interested in open-source tools while my government customers are sticking with Esri. Since those observations are based on the the extremely heavy filter of my own recent experience, I&#8217;d be hesitant to draw any larger conclusions from them.</p>

<p><img alt="" height="264" src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/duct-tape.jpg" title="Duct Tape" width="300" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve always believed that proficiency with a wide range of tools makes me a better consultant and integrator, so I am always exploring and trying new things. With those commercial customers, and in my own personal side projects, my recent workflows have gelled around a core set of tools, both commercial and open-source: <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> - I am very comfortable with SQL and tend to use <a href="http://www.postgresql.org" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> and PostGIS for a lot of my vector data processing. Lately, this has mainly involved joining up geometries with attributes and doing aggregations and similar things. For example, the vector data in this <a href="http://geobabbler.github.com/mdq62012.html" target="_blank">map of the county-level Maryland Question 6 results</a> was processed in PostGIS. Very simply, I have a baseline table of the counties of Maryland which I will use to create new data sets. In this case, I imported a CSV of the election results, created a view that joined up the data and then selected the view into a new table. This is workflow is much easier with PostGIS 2.x thanks to the <a href="http://blog.opengeo.org/2012/03/06/postgis-2-0-new-features-typmod/" target="_blank">use of typmod</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a> - In the case of the map mentioned above, the data set is ultimately going to be static so it makes sense to serve it as static content, rather than bringing a heavyweight geospatial server such as <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgisserver/" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> or <a href="http://geoserver.org/display/GEOS/Welcome" target="_blank">GeoServer</a> into the mix. In these cases, I lean toward <a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>. QGIS makes it very easy to export any vector layer out to GeoJSON so it&#8217;s become my go-to tool for that. QGIS also has great analytical tools and I consider it a complete functional match for ArcMap but, having said that, I&#8217;m actually very comfortable with the spatial SQL functions in PostGIS so I end up doing most of my analytical work there.</p>

<p><a href="http://leafletjs.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a>/<a href="http://www.openlayers.org/" target="_blank">OpenLayers</a> - Most of the web maps I&#8217;m doing are single-use and pretty straightforward. When that&#8217;s the case, I prefer to use Leaflet as it&#8217;s a pretty lightweight library. That said, I keep OpenLayers in the mix if the GIS-like requirements get a little more complex. OpenLayers does more &#8220;out of the box&#8221; than Leaflet but Leaflet is trimmer so it really depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/" target="_blank">Arc2Earth</a>/<a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill </a>- Arc2Earth is a commercial extension to ArcGIS and I lean on it to make tiles, although it does a lot more than that. I also use TileMill for this purpose but it really depends on where my cartography resides. There&#8217;s a lot of good cartography locked up in MXDs and Arc2Earth is just a great way to capitalize on that. It&#8217;s also nice that Arc2Earth works in ArcMap, eliminating the need for a license of Server.  If I&#8217;m building my cartography from scratch, which is not really my strong suit, I&#8217;ll lean toward TileMill because it more easily connects directly to PostGIS, which is where my data tends to reside if I have my druthers. Again, it depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.python.org/" target="_blank">Python</a>/Javascript - I&#8217;m doing a lot more work in Python these days. It&#8217;s become the <em>lingua franca</em> of GIS development in my book. Additionally, the capabilities of Javascript for web maps is evolving at a stunning pace. I can&#8217;t see being productive in the long term in the geospatial field without proficiency in these two languages.</p>

<p>So these are the tools that I&#8217;m using most often these days as part of my personal workflows. The stable of tools that I use evolves over time, as should be evident if you peruse this blog. In general, I&#8217;m finding it very easy to be productive with these tools right now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How long until the ads stop?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/how-long-until-the-ads-stop/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/how-long-until-the-ads-stop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In celebration of this day when the non-stop political ads, robo-calls, junk mail, and social media posts <em>should</em> finally come to an end. I threw together a little map to show the latest time at which polls close in each state. This should represent, state-by-state, the time (EST) at which you can safely go back to answering your phones. Click the image below to go there (the data takes a couple of seconds to load).</p>

<p><a href="http://demo.zekiah.com/polls"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2947" height="331" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/pollmap.png" title="pollmap" width="640" /></a></p>

<p>Democracy is a wonderful thing, but it will be nice to have this campaign season behind us.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/K1vaEweJUUk?color=white&theme=light"></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilson Center to Discuss FCC National Broadband Map]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/09/wilson-center-to-discuss-fcc-national-broadband-map/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/09/wilson-center-to-discuss-fcc-national-broadband-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most compelling recent success stories for open-source geospatial tools in the Federal Government has been the <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/" target="_blank">Federal Communications Commission</a> (FCC) <a href="http://broadbandmap.gov/" target="_blank">National Broadband Map</a> initiative. It has been a very visible example of the stability, scalability, flexibility, and power of open-source geospatial tools.</p>

<p>The Woodrow Wilson Center will be hosting <a href="http://www.wilsoncenter.org/event/the-national-broadband-map-case-study-open-innovation-for-national-policy" target="_blank">a case study of National Broadband Map</a> on October 15th, 2012. The event&#8217;s page also includes a link to the full paper (PDF), authored by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=113470334" target="_blank">Zachary Bastian</a> of the Wilson Center and <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=10690378" target="_blank">Michael Byrne</a> of the FCC.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2933" height="285" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/nbm.png" title="nbm" width="640" /></p>

<p>The full paper, in my opinion, is recommended reading for anyone working with geospatial technologies in the government space. While the Broadband Map has rightfully garnered significant attention based upon its success, especially in terms of performance and scalability, the paper does a good job of reminding us that the map is not an end goal in itself, but a step toward the larger policy goal of expanding broadband access. The paper does an excellent job of illustrating how top-level policy goals were broken down into actionable parts that resulted in a concrete product such as the Broadband Map. In so doing, it walks us through the introduction and fostering of an open culture within the FCC that resulted not only in the Broadband Map but also in the development of open APIs and the availability of FCC tools as open-source projects themselves.</p>

<p>In its conclusions, the paper also makes compelling observations about the power of focused policy goals to drive the use of technology standing in stark contrast to generic overarching technical policies, such as the National Spatial Data Infrastructure (NSDI) which are disconnected from specific policy goals and achieve little traction.</p>

<p>If you are interested not only in geospatial technologies, but also the link between policy and technology implementation, and the cultural change that can be brought about by open-source technologies, you should consider attending the event at the Wilson Center on the 15th. While not a universal blueprint, the National Broadband Map makes a compelling case study.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cutting Tiles for ArcGIS Server Using TileMill]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/03/cutting-tiles-for-arcgis-server-using-tilemill/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/03/cutting-tiles-for-arcgis-server-using-tilemill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&#8217;s been a lot of talk about <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill</a> and <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/" target="_blank">CartoCSS</a> lately, with good cause. TileMill makes it very easy generate beautiful map tiles using the <a href="http://mapnik.org/" target="_blank">Mapnik</a> engine and CartoCSS provides a familiar method to author the cartographic representation of spatial data. <a href="http://mapbrief.com/2012/09/27/gis-cartography-the-latest-best-opportunity-to-bridge-the-chasm/" target="_blank">As Brian Timoney points out</a>, CartoCSS has the added bonus of making best practices shareable via copy-and-paste.</p>




<p>Naturally, the best way to take advantage of TileMill is to export your tiles to <a href="https://github.com/mapbox/mbtiles-spec" target="_blank">MBTiles</a> and use <a href="http://mapbox.com/" target="_blank">MapBox</a> hosting. If that&#8217;s not an option, you can pretty easily self-host with <a href="https://github.com/mapbox/tilestream" target="_blank">TileStream</a>. That said, there are some organizations that, due to larger GIS workflows, IT policies, and a host of other legitimate reasons, need or choose to use <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">ArcGIS Server</a> to do map hosting. For those organizations, TileMill is still an option to create attractive basemaps, within certain constraints.</p>


<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2911" height="295" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/tilemill_screen.png" title="tilemill_screen" width="640" /></p>

<p>So I set out to see if I could bridge the gap between the two. Two blog posts pointed the way. A while back, <a href="http://www.weogeo.com/blog/Create_WeoGeo_Tilepack_from_MBTiles_SQLite_database_with_mbutil.html" target="_blank">Dan Dye blogged about how he had forked mb-util</a> and added support for exporting WeoGeo tilepacks from MBTiles. Also, a co-worker of mine, Eric Mahaffey, had blogged some time ago about <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2011/08/03/using-arc2earth-tile-caching-across-air-gapped-networks" target="_blank">how to use Arc2Earth to manage tile caches across air-gapped networks</a>. Using these posts for guidance, I was pretty sure I had all the pieces I needed. <!--more--></p>

<p>First, I decided to fork Dan&#8217;s code (I love GitHub) and add support for exporting ArcGIS tiles. Essentially, I followed Dan&#8217;s pattern and added a choice for an ArcGIS schema as a command-line option. My forked version <a href="https://github.com/geobabbler/mbutil" target="_blank">can be found on GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>I then fired up TileMill (0.10.0 for Windows) and created some tiles at zoom levels 4 through 8 using the &#8220;Control Room&#8221; sample that comes with TileMill. I chose this for two reasons: First, I am not very good at cartography and this sample looks attractive and distinct from the generic ArcGIS sample I used. Second, it&#8217;s very well-known to TileMill users so it worked well for this demo. I won&#8217;t go into how I created the tiles as this post is not intended to be a TileMill tutorial.</p>

<p>Once I had exported the tiles to an MBTiles file, I ran the updated mb-util Python utility to export the tiles in an ArcGIS structure. The command-line usage is shown below. One note: I did not generate the &#8220;level&#8221; folders in accordance with ArcGIS convention. If you are familiar with ArcGIS, you know that the level numbers are relative so that, if your service only contains levels 3, 4 , and 5, the will be levels L00, L01, L02 respectively. Instead, the utility names them according to their original TMS levels (L03, L04, L05 in this case). So, you may need to rename your level folders when you rehost to ArcGIS Server but this should entail a maximum of 19 manual edits, which seemed like a reasonable compromise.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/mbutil_cmd.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2897" height="311" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/mbutil_cmd.png" title="mb-util usage" width="640" /></a></p>

<p>So mb-util created the &#8220;_alllayers&#8221; folder and its child file system for us. Because I&#8217;m not creating a conf.xml yet, I can create it by hand or use ArcGIS to create some dummy tiles with a configuration. Once that&#8217;s done, we are simply engaged in a file copy  operation (picking up at step 4 of Eric&#8217;s post). For this demo, I created an actual map using one of the ArcGIS samples so that it would be apparent that the operation worked. In practice, I wouldn&#8217;t go to that much trouble up front. The image below shows the map service using the original tiles.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill1.png"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-2901" height="370" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill1.png" title="ArcGIS map service before TileMill tiles" width="640" /></a> <div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">ArcGIS map service as created from the original MXD.</div></div>


<p>After I copied the tiles from TileMill into the correct location, I was able to refresh the window and see the boundary between the original tiles and the those from TileMill. Again, this was just for demo purposes. In practice, the whole cache would be from TileMill. The image below shows the updated cache, displayed using the ArcGIS Javascript API.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill2.png"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-2902" height="370" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill2.png" title="ArcGIS map service after TileMill tiles" width="640" /></a> <div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">ArcGIS map service showing tiles from TileMill.</div></div>


<p>I apologize for screenshots but my EDN license precludes making my ArcGIS Server public for a live demo.</p>

<p>So, it&#8217;s perfectly possible to create nice basemaps using TileMill for use in ArcGIS server, provided you adhere to two constraints: 1) You use Web Mercator for your spatial reference and 2) You make sure your ArcGIS cache is the &#8220;exploded&#8221; variety.</p>

<p>Why would you do this? It is certainly possible to build great cartographic representations in ArcGIS but those representations are locked away in ArcGIS map documents, styles, layer packages and such; all of which are some proprietary binary format such as persisted COM objects. While this may not be the worst thing in the world, CartoCSS, being a text format, more easily lends itself to configuration control. Organizations that want to maintain configuration control over map templates and such can take advantage of standard tools such as git or SVN to do so. I have found that organizations with strict IT policies are also exactly the same kinds of organizations that to maintain control over content and styling so this is actually a surprisingly important factor.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll probably play with this more as time and customer demand allow, but it&#8217;s good to know this option is available for providing flexibility with ArcGIS Server.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
