<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Flex | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/flex/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-08T22:21:05-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[uZard Browser Runs Flash on BlackBerry]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/07/11/uzard-browser-runs-flash-on-blackberry/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/07/11/uzard-browser-runs-flash-on-blackberry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the festivities for the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/user-conference/index.html">2010 ESRI User Conference</a> already underway, I stumbled across a new browser, called <a href="http://www.uzard.com/en/main/main.asp">uZard</a>, that BlackBerry users (depending on how old your model is) can use to browse the web and which also supports Flash. <!--more-->The native browser on the BlackBerry is notoriously inadequate so many users I know (including me) are always looking for alternatives. I have tried <a href="http://www.opera.com/mobile/">Opera Mini</a> and find it to be somewhat clunky. Of course, one of the other big problems with the native browser is its lack of support for anything really modern from a UI perspective (Flash, Silverlight, HTML5, etc.). It has decent javascript support but you can hit those limits pretty quickly.</p>

<p>uZard is still in beta and the BlackBerry version is "<a href="http://www.uzard.com/en/solutions/uzardweb_p.asp">uZard Web P</a>". From what I can tell (the site is not clear), I think this means that it does not use Webkit, whereas "uZard S" does. I could be wrong about that.</p>

<p>Anyway, I installed it and immediately went to the <a href="http://resources.arcgis.com/">ArcGIS Resource Center</a> to try the sample apps and they do run. The photo below is my BlackBerry Tour 9630 showing one of the <a href="http://help.arcgis.com/en/webapi/flex/">Flex API</a> sample apps from the Resource Center. They are a little hard to use but I suspect that's because the apps themselves haven't been optimized for mobile users. Nonetheless, the BlackBerry users kicking around San Diego this week may want to give uZard a try in order to test all the new Flex stuff that ESRI will be showing off.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/07/uzard_flex.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-997" height="224" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/07/uzard_flex.jpg?w=300" title="uzard_flex" width="300" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
