<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Maryland | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/maryland/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-29T10:24:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maryland Department of Planning Bundles Property Data with QGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/10/07/maryland-department-of-planning-bundles-property-data-with-qgis/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T12:38:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/10/07/maryland-department-of-planning-bundles-property-data-with-qgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past week, I got an e-mail from Jim Cannistra, Director of Data Planning Services and the <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/home.shtml">Maryland Department of Planning</a> (MDP), alerting me to a new product available from MDP called <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/FINDERProduct.shtml">FINDER Quantum</a>. This product bundles Maryland property data and related products with <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a> software to provide users with a fully-functional, free-standing system for interacting with the data. It is designed to replace an older, custom software product, capitalizing on an industry-standard open-source system.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>From the MDP site, the bundled data includes:</p>

<blockquote cite="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/FINDERProduct.shtml">The product DVD includes the State's computerized property (tax) maps; the x,y linkages (point or polygon) to the Parcel, Computer Assisted Mass Appraisal (CAMA) and Sale datasets; Parcel, CAMA and Sale data, including Sale data via download from the Subscriber Website, from the Maryland State Department of Assessments and Taxation (SDAT); reference grids including a grid for the property (tax) maps, an ADC map book grid, a grid for the Maryland State Highway Administration (SHA) road, stream and feature maps and a grid for USGS 7.5' Topographical quad maps; and additional SHA files including a digital centerline roads file, data derived from SHA digital grid maps, an SHA major roads file and a county boundary file.<br/>
<br/>
Also included are land use/land cover data; congressional and legislative district boundary files; census geography and census demographic data; ZIP code boundary files; Priority Funding Area (PFA) designations; floodplain data, including DFIRM data for selected jurisdictions; protected lands boundaries; watershed data; generalized zoning designations; sewer service area boundaries; public water service area boundaries for selected jurisdictions; National Register of Historic Places (NRHP) Maryland coverage; residential Sales x,y point and summary files derived from SDAT Parcel and Sale data; large-scale, high resolution color digital-ortho imagery and a custom Quantum GIS project file (.qgs).</blockquote>


<p>The MDP site indicates there is a <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/pdf/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/Finder/CstFnd.pdf">licensing fee</a> (PDF), which I assume is to cover the management of the data sets and the <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/pdf/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/Finder/LicFnd.pdf">license agreement</a>, while acknowledging the GPL license of QGIS itself, seems to place the actual FINDER extension itself outide of any open-source license. (I am not a lawyer so I'll accept guidance on that interpretation.) That said, bundling QGIS with data that the statewide user community values and an application to help exploit it is a great way to get more users on board with QGIS.</p>

<p>To that end, users that choose to take advantage of FINDER Quantum will want to keep in mind that great <a href="http://www.esrgc.org/training/">QGIS-related resources</a> are available via <a href="http://www.salisbury.edu/geography/">Salisbury State University</a> and that training is also available from <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=14036437">Randal Hale</a> of <a href="http://www.northrivergeographic.com/introduction-to-quantum-gis">North River Geographics</a>. Once you have this powerful application installed, you can start to tap into a <a href="http://boundlessgeo.com/solutions/solutions-software/quantum-gis/">deep pool</a> of <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/search_profile">resources</a> to build your expertise.</p>

<p>So kudos to MDP for bundling their data with a powerful mapping, visualization, and analysis tool in QGIS. I hope that, in the near future, MDP considers making the FINDER application itself open-source but this is a great first step.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Thing I Saw at TUGIS 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/20/the-best-thing-i-saw-at-tugis-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-20T12:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/20/the-best-thing-i-saw-at-tugis-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent the day yesterday at <a href="http://www.towson.edu/">Towson University</a> attending the <a href="http://www.towson.edu/tugis/">TUGIS 2013</a> conference. The new one-day format was a firehose that showcased the diversity of geospatial work occurring across the State of Maryland. The keynote by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=44978536">Learon Dalby</a> was well-received and the content of the conference was generally substantive. While the day was a sprint, there was one workshop that really caught my attention more so than I would have thought from its title.</p>

<p>The photo below shows 40 participants of an "Introduction to Free and Open Source GIS Software" workshop getting hands-on experience with <a href="http://www.qgis.org">QGIS</a> and <a href="http://www.postgis.org">PostGIS</a> by working through prepared but realistic scenarios. These scenarios included doing multi-user editing and performing spatial analysis to assess the effects of a potential toxic release over a small town.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/tugis2013_workshop.jpg" /></p>

<p>The workshop was put together by <a href="http://faculty.salisbury.edu/~ajlembo/">Dr. Arthur Lembo</a> of <a href="http://www.salisbury.edu/">Salisbury University</a> and conducted by him and a team of his students, who not only led portions of the workshop but were also stationed around the room to provide guidance to participants. The scenarios were prepared in printed workbooks that the participants were free to take with them, along with information about how to download the tools. All-in-all, I thought the workshop was very well-designed and presented a thorough overview of the capabilities of these two tools.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>To be sure, the workshop was not all unicorns and rainbows. There were typical glitches such as file system and database permission issues that required on-the-fly adjustments, which Dr. Lembo and his students handled well. Some participants were clearly stumped at points while others were making good headway with the examples.</p>

<p>Many of the participants probably remain committed <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcGIS</a> users after the workshop while others may very well dig in and more thoroughly explore QGIS and PostGIS, but that's really beside the point. Regardless of what the individual participants decide to do with the information from the workshop, all left with hands-on exposure to the tools that was presented in a manner that was free of hyperbole, FUD, or market-speak. They now have more first-hand information with which to make their own educated decisions as to how they want to proceed with their geospatial technology choices; and that, in my opinion, may have been the most valuable outcome of the workshop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off to TUGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/18/off-to-tugis/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T12:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/18/off-to-tugis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow, I'll be heading up to the <a href="http://www.towson.edu/tugis/">Towson University GIS (TUGIS) conference</a> with 500 or so of my closest Maryland geo-friends. It has been restructured into a one-day event and the program seems to be very content-rich as a result. I am particularly happy to see more open-source content this year. There's an intro session featuring <a href="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</a>, <a href="http://www.postgis.org">PostGIS</a>, <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a>, and <a href="http://geoserver.org">GeoServer</a> presented by <a href="http://www.salisbury.edu/">Salisbury State University</a>. Salisbury was once known as a bastion of <a href="http://www.manifold.net/">Manifold</a> so they've got a long history of thinking outside the Arc. Additionally, there is a session (by Towson University) discussing the use of <a href="http://www.gdal.org">GDAL</a>, <a href="http://www.gdal.org/ogr/">OGR</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/sgillies/shapely">Shapely</a> in the development of a spatial service.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/mdflag.png" alt="Brian Timoney's favorite state flag" title="Brian Timoney's favorite state flag" /></p>

<p>One thing I like about regional GIS conferences like this is that they tend to focus more on solutions to real-world problems instead of the latest technological bells and whistles. I spend so much of my time with my head in Federal requirements that it's nice do a reset and get different perspectives on how geospatial technologies are used. I am particularly interested to hear the keynote from <a href="http://twitter.com/learondalby">Learon Dalby</a> of <a href="http://www.sanborn.com/">Sanborn</a> and formerly of the <a href="http://www.gis.state.ar.us/">Arkansas GIO office</a>. I had the pleasure of working with Learon and the AGIO team on a project a couple of years ago and am impressed with what they accomplished.</p>

<p>I appreciate the new format of TUGIS as a one-day event is much easier to fit into the schedule. I'm looking forward to it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
