<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: visual basic | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/visual-basic/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-07T14:48:22-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MSDN Article on Mapping with WPF]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/18/msdn-article-on-mapping-with-wpf/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/18/msdn-article-on-mapping-with-wpf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/07/12/Maps/default.aspx">this article</a> today about using <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/express/vb/default.aspx">VB9</a> and <a href="http://windowsclient.net/Default.aspx">WPF</a> to draw thematic maps. It's a good walk-through of how to do it. The article admits that the coordinate transformation used is not terribly accurate but that can be rectified. This article is a good example of how to build a mapping application without any third-party components. The author converts Census boundary files to XML for this app. It shouldn't be a stretch to use <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/sql/2008/technologies/spatial.mspx">SQL 2008</a>, <a href="http://postgis.refractions.net">PostGIS</a> or some other database that can emit GML and has an OLEDB provider as a data source.</p>

<p>I've been using WPF with <a href="http://codeplex.com/SharpMap">SharpMap</a> on a project <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2007/08/14/sharpmap-and-wpf/">for a while</a> but my mapping code is about 5% of the overall project and I haven't had a chance to extract what I've done into something digestable to provide an example. I had to fit into the rendering paradigm of a previously developed GUI so it deviates from how it's shaping up in SharpMap 2.0.</p>

<p>So, if you're looking for an example of how to render spatial data in WPF, this is a good one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MO No Mo']]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/07/09/mo-no-mo/"/>
    <updated>2007-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/07/09/mo-no-mo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, there's nothing terribly surprising about ESRI's announcement regarding <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/mapobjects/index.html">MapObjects</a> in this <a href="http://support.esri.com/index.cfm?fa=knowledgebase.techarticles.articleShow&amp;d=31074">technical article</a>. I would have been more surprised if they had announced that it <em>would</em> be supported or that there would be another version or something like that. In truth, I haven't touched MapObjects in years. It was dead to me even if it was still on life support at ESRI. But there was something about seeing it in print:</p>

<blockquote>MapObjects Windows 2.4 and MapObjects-Java 2.2 and 2.3 are not supported on the Windows Vista. ESRI is not certifying any new environments for MapObjects-Windows and there are no plans to support Vista with MapObjects-Java.</blockquote>


<p>It brought back a lot of memories. I began programming when I was 10. I wrote a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_and_dragons">D&amp;D</a> character generator in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BASIC_programming_language">BASIC</a> on a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commodore_64">Commodore 64</a>. I guess that makes me an old geek. D&amp;D and computers might even be a double-down. ;-)? I've pretty much been doing some form of BASIC ever since (not so much VB.Net anymore, though, as I do most of my .Net in C#) along with a lot of other languages. I got interested in maps a few years later and discovered I could fuse maps and computers as I headed into the workforce.</p>

<p>Early on, I was able to do some <a href="http://extranet.mapinfo.com/products/Overview.cfm?productid=1063">MapBasic</a> stuff but that didn't get too far. So I suffered through AML and Avenue for a while in order to feed the GIS development jones. Then along came MO.</p>

<p>With MO, I was able to introduce an old friend (BASIC in the form of VB5 and later VB6) to a new friend (GIS, although it wasn't new to me by then). I was able to write real apps that fused mapping with databases and other cool tools. For one customer, I built a COM system that featured a core UI and provided a pluggable architecture and an API so others could write plug-ins. Then we converted a lot of stand-alone apps to work in the system. Sounds familiar huh?</p>

<p>From a GIS standpoint, MO wasn't the most powerful game in town but it was <em>fun</em>! And, if you needed an algorithm or something that MO didn't support, you could just implement it yourself in the language of your choice. There are operations that I originally implemented in MO/VB6 that I have migrated and still use in C#/ArcObjects/Others. In case I didn't get the point across earlier, it was just plain fun.</p>

<p>That was a while ago. GIS is still fun but I just don't use MO anymore (maybe that's the problem). ESRI's announcement is sort of like when you read that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_Centre">the arena where you went to all of your concerts in your youth got dynamited to make room for a shopping plaza</a>. So, much like I did that day, I'll pop a cold one, raise a glass and say "Thanks for the memories."</p>

<p><img alt="The better part of my hearing was left here." src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/07/cap_centre.png" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
