<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: WhereCampDC | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/wherecampdc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-09T09:30:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DC/MD/VA Area Geo-Event Scene Getting More Active]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/03/dcmdva-area-geo-event-scene-getting-more-active/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/03/dcmdva-area-geo-event-scene-getting-more-active</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There was a time only a few years ago when, if you lived in the DC/MD/VA area, planning your geo-conference schedule for the year went something like this: Register for the ESRI FedUC and then start booking plane tickets for everything else. That is no longer the case with more events occurring in the area. Here's a round-up of a few events that are on my 2012 schedule so far:</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="" height="536" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/foss4g_lanyard_small.png" title="foss4g_lanyard_small" width="495" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">You can never have too many of these...<br/><br/></div></div>


<p><a href="http://www.esri.com/events/fedcon/index.html">ESRI Federal GIS Conference</a> (formerly known as the Federal User Conference): 22 - 24 February. This is probably one of the longest-running and largest events in the area. This year features another <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/fedcon/agenda/dev-geo.html">DevGeo</a> session, focusing on developing applications with the various ESRI tools. Last year was the first time it was done at a FedUC and the room was packed all day. This conference is obviously an ESRI show but the last few years have included unofficial, after-hours gatherings of people working with a wide range of geospatial tools. Even if you are not an ESRI user, there may be something going on in the vicinity that would be worthwhile. <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://www.towson.edu/tugis/">TUGIS 2012</a>: 19 - 20 March. I hesitated to list this because the last thing you want to do is suggest to someone from Baltimore that they are in the DC area. So let me clarify: This is NOT technically a DC-area event but it draws a lot of attendees from the DC area. It's also probably the longest running GIS-related event in the region, celebrating its 25th year this year. The organizers at Towson do a good job of mixing up the program so it's not as overtly "Federal" as events farther down I-95 can be.</p>

<p><a href="http://foss4g-na.org/">FOSS4G North America</a>: 10 - 12 April. This event was the topic of my <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/23/foss4g-north-america-to-be-held-in-washington-dc/">previous post</a>. Clearly, it's intended to be a North American event and I would expect it to move around year-to-year so I'll just be happy for the good fortune that <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/">OSGEO</a> decided to inaugurate it in my back yard. It makes perfect sense as there is growing interest in, and adoption of, open-source geospatial tools in the Federal Government.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.wherecampdc.org/">WhereCampDC 2012</a>: Dates TBD. <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/kelsosCorner/status/156469857704083457">I have heard rumblings</a> but haven't seen details. Last year's event was great and I hope it is reprised this year.</p>

<p>There are also a couple of interesting recurring events that have taken root in the area:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.meetup.com/Geo-DC/">Geo DC Meetups</a> - This is an independent group that meets the first Wednesday of every month and covers a wide range of topics. Given that I live out in the provinces, I don't get into the city as much as I would like for these but the group has been gaining momentum. It seems to be doing a good job of building a community of geo-minded people in the area.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.meetup.com/DevMeetUpNortheast/">ESRI Dev Meetups</a>: These meetups are ostensibly focused on application development with ESRI tools but, in practice, the content of the talks cover a wide variety of issues and tools. There have been talks regarding integration of ESRI tools with other geospatial platforms, best practices, case studies, etc. The nice part about these events is that ESRI doesn't want their staff doing the talking. They just book the venue and put out the refreshments. These meetups occur as part of ESRI's Northeast regional effort to establish these events so they don't occur as frequently as the Geo DC events.</p>

<p>This level of activity in the region is good to see as the potential for a vibrant community has always been there. There are lots of people involved in making this happen but the people at <a href="http://developmentseed.org/">Development Seed</a>, <a href="http://www.geoiq.com">GeoIQ</a> and <a href="http://www.esri.com">ESRI</a> have been particularly proactive in energizing their respective constituencies and the results seem to be beneficial for all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GeoServices REST Specification and OGC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/16/geoservices-rest-specification-and-ogc/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/16/geoservices-rest-specification-and-ogc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So this is what I get for missing the Ignite sessions at WhereCampDC<sup>*</sup>:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Sorry, you are not authorized to see this status.</div></p>

<p><sup>*</sup>I got to dance with my daughter and help her chase fireflies so I win.</p>

<p>The worst-kept rumor/secret in recent memory is now "out there" so here are my thoughts:</p>

<!--more-->


<ol>
    
<li>It makes perfect sense for <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/">OGC</a>. They were caught completely flatfooted by REST and this provides an expedient (and already widely-deployed) way to catch up, if they adopt it. Esri's API works pretty well and is certainly a nice starting point for a spec.</li>

<li>It's also a no-brainer for <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a>. If adopted, they are automatically OGC-compliant and may even be able to call ArcGIS Server a reference implementation. There's no way that doesn't benefit them and they would probably be the biggest winner in this. What would be nice is if Esri followed this up with some demonstration of commitment to the community such as releasing one or more of their REST API clients as open-source.</li>

<li>I assume this includes the Esri JSON syntax (my term), which is the underpinning of the GeoServices REST Specification. That leaves me wondering about <a href="http://geojson.org">GeoJSON</a>. It's a community specification that's been <a href="http://wiki.geojson.org/Users">widely adopted</a> across the industry. It wouldn't be very hard to augment the GeoServices spec with "f=geojson" on the calls that are appropriate but I can't see OGC doing that for a spec they don't own (although, by doing so, they would live into the "open" part of their name). 

For what it's worth, I like GeoJSON and find it tighter and more focused than the Esri syntax for what it does and I think it should be part of the discussion somehow. It's not entirely a 1-to-1 match as GeoJSON is designed for transmitting geometries and features. The Esri JSON syntax is broader in scope, addressing not only geometries but also other functions such as listing available endpoints and fetching endpoint metadata and such. So GeoJSON, in its current form, would not address all of the needs of the GeoServices spec but would certainly be a viable option for functions such as returning the results of feature layer queries.</li>

<li>It would be interesting to see whether the spec gets implemented across the community. It has been available for months but there hasn't been a wide uptake. The only example I am aware of is <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/products/cloud/">Arc2Earth's cloud work</a> which <a href="http://ucdemos.appspot.com/a2e/ArcGIS/rest/services/NYC/NYC_Subways/MapServer/">implements it</a> on top of their Google-AppEngine-based services. Maybe OGC adoption would provide the kind of "top cover" that will give developers peace-of-mind. (Note: My company is an Arc2Earth reseller.)
</li>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="" height="202" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/06/a2e_esrisl.png" title="Arc2Earth Cloud Service in Esri Silverlight API" width="442" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Arc2Earth sample in Esri Silverlight demo application<br/><br/></div></div>

<li>If the <a href="http://www.esri.com/library/whitepapers/pdfs/geoservices-rest-spec.pdf">GeoServices REST Specification</a> (Beware, PDF) is adopted by OGC, it will continue a trend begun with the adoption of KML and GeoRSS in which they formally adopt community and de facto standards that have emerged and been proven in the industry. I think that's a valid approach that can exist alongside their usual standards development process. This case is a little different than those in that it was developed by a single vendor (like KML) and has been released and documented (like KML) but hasn't really been widely implemented outside its initial vendor base prior to consideration (unlike KML). That's a subtle but important difference that bears watching.
</li>
</ol>


<p>Those were some of my initial thoughts upon hearing this. If it happens, it's obviously of immediate benefit to both OGC and Esri. The lack of any viable presence by OGC in this area has left a void that has begun to be filled by other efforts, including Esri's. It'll be interesting to see the longer-term implications. I think <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2011/06/16/esri-rest-api-could-be-an-ogc-standard/">James</a> is correct that we can expect to see implementations on server platforms such as <a href="http://mapserver.org/">MapServer</a> and <a href="http://geoserver.org/display/GEOS/Welcome">GeoServer</a> but I wonder how relevant it will be in the emerging environment surrounding big data and hosted (i.e. cloud) infrastructures. An end-to-end GIS interface may be less relevant than a more atomic approach that allows support for spatial types to be injected as needed into a larger framework (for example, supporting use of GeoJSON on specific calls the way Twitter does). There's room for both approaches but distinct paths are beginning to emerge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Whirlwind Week Capped By WhereCampDC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/13/a-whirlwind-week-capped-by-wherecampdc/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/13/a-whirlwind-week-capped-by-wherecampdc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The week of June 6, 2011 seemed to be something of a whirlwind week for the Metro DC geo community. On June 7th, two meetups took place at about the same time, each with relevance to spatial technologies:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> continued their excellent "Dev Meetup" series with an event in DC. I had the honor of giving the leadoff talk, "5 Myths About GIS in 2011," which I will post in the near future. There were also five great lightning talks highlighting a range of projects and issues. It also gave me a chance to finally meet a lot of people, including many that I've known through Twitter. I like these meetups because they are fairly no-holds-barred. I was given two guidelines for my talk: 1) Don't make it a sales pitch and 2) Try not to trash Esri too badly. I was happy to see that most of the speakers used that latitude well, talking about larger concepts and integration of various technologies and not just "here's my ArcGIS Server site."</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter" height="222" src="http://files.meetup.com/315972/meetup_logo_1.png" title="Meetup" width="300" /></p>

<p>At about the same time, the DC Tech Meetup was happening. There, <a href="http://twitter.com/ajturner">Andrew Turner</a> of <a href="http://www.geoiq.com">GeoIQ</a> talked about "Big Data and the 4th Dimension," about what they are doing to analyze large data sets spatially and temporally. I was unable to attend this event as I was speaking at the other one but it seemed well-received. I find the increased exposure of the DC-area geo community exciting after so many years.</p>

<p>Of course, the week was capped by <a href="http://www.wherecampdc.org">WhereCampDC</a>, which spanned Friday night (with Ignite Spatial) and Saturday (with the unconference itself). I was unable to attend Ignite as I had previous personal commitments although people were still buzzing the next day about <a href="http://twitter.com/spara">Sophia Parafina</a>'s "WMS is Dead" talk. My understanding is that Slideshare will never be able to capture the true essence of the talk. :)</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter" height="200" src="http://evbdn.eventbrite.com/s3-s3/eventlogos/251723/675966835-4.jpg" title="WhereCampDC" width="255" /></p>

<p>WhereCampDC was my first experience with the unconference format and I may never view a traditional conference the same way again. I won't go into detail about how it works; I'll just say go to one if you get the chance. The event itself was eye-opening for me in a lot of ways. I work primarily in the US Federal government sector, and WhereCampDC gave me a chance to learn about some of the humbling work being done by people in the development, humanitarian and environment sectors. I was left with an overwhelming sense of gratitude for the work they are doing. <!--more--></p>

<p>I took a different tack with WhereCampDC than I tend to take with most conferences and I avoided the more strict technical discussions (although the one on spatial databases/Fusion Tables would have been fun) and stuck more to discussions of concepts and issues. The exception to this was a discussion of <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R</a>, in which I have both personal and professional interest and about which I trying to learn more. That discussion was helpful for me in giving me some places to start.</p>

<p>I also sat in on a discussion of digitizing historical data. The discussion focused a lot on ways to use crowd-sourcing to assist in digitizing old data that currently exists in in analog form. The need to do so is readily apparent as such data will support automated analysis of various kinds. Obviously, getting such data into digital form is a monumental task so the discussion focused on way to motivate people to participate in such efforts. This concept is perfectly illustrated by <a href="http://www.oldweather.org/">www.oldweather.org</a>, which was the topic of <a href="http://twitter.com/jatorre">Javier de la Torre</a>'s Ignite talk (which I also missed) and was still generating buzz the next day. To be honest, the discussion took a different direction than I expected but I found it more valuable also.</p>

<p>Next, I listened to <a href="http://twitter.com/druidsmith">Dave Smith</a> talk about how the EPA is implementing linked data. Dave is very knowledgeable on this subject and EPA seems to be making good headway.</p>

<p>The "NoGIS" discussion was another one that went a different direction than I expected and left me pleasantly surprised. Sophia Parafina kicked it off by defining NoGIS as a joke intended to get people talking about new tools and techniques centered around big data, time and other factors that have are not addressed well by GIS tools as they have evolved until now. The discussion gelled around the idea of taking a more people-centric view of the uses of spatial technologies (thus the tongue-in-cheek "SoylentGIS" term that popped up in the discussion). I was also happy to hear <a href="http://twitter.com/springmeyer">Dane Springmeyer</a> call for a positive discourse that doesn't divide people into camps or put them on the defensive (even unintentionally). I think he made a great point because there has already been some bristling about the term and that can impede thoughtful discussion. In general, I found the NoGIS discussion to be constructive and free of hyperbole.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="GIS is people!" height="221" src="http://www.trekcast.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/soylent-green-is-a-great-movie.png" title="GIS is people!" width="300" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">GIS is people!<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>Andrew Turner offered a thought exercise about being able to tap into the information stream (think social media, news, weather, etc.) about a place, which took the discussion to the challenges of doing such a thing. This is a different spin that is not readily addressable by GIS tools as we have known them. At the same time, the traditional use cases of GIS (land-use planning, cartographic production, etc.) are still necessary and valid. So the discussion wasn't so much about "this instead of that" as about recognizing that the nature of data, how we access it, how we produce it and what we expect from it is changing and that different tools are needed to better address this new relationship with information.</p>

<p>So, in the span of seven hours, we touched upon very old data, traditional GIS, emerging data streams and ways to exploit them. There's a lot of innovation going on that was exciting to see. This was probably the best "work-related" Saturday I've ever spent. I'll be reflecting on my WhereCampDC experience for a while.</p>

<p>The flowering of community in the DC-area geo scene represented by these events is long overdue and I hope the momentum continues. The primary industry in our region is government and I think the compartmentalization of the local geo community largely reflects the culture of that industry (and the defense and intelligence sectors in particular). That said, government will only gain the efficiencies it needs if individuals begin reaching across those boundaries to discuss tools, techniques and issues. For that reason, I think the organizers of WhereCampDC and the other events deserve a lot of credit for pushing that process forward in our segment of the tech community.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
