<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PostGIS | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/postgis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-24T12:51:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Put Planet Geospatial to Work for You]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm happy to see that <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2012/11/24/planet-geospatial-the-way-forward/" target="_blank">James has decided keep Planet Geospatial going</a>. It's been one of the more consistently valuable resources in the community since its inception and it's good that it will continue.</p>

<p>While I'm looking forward to seeing how <a href="http://twitter.com/cageyjames" target="_blank">James</a> evolves <a href="http://planetgs.com" target="_blank">Planet Geospatial</a>, there are ways to more efficiently extract value out of its current state right now. At its core, Planet Geospatial is an RSS feed. RSS can safely be called "venerable" nowadays, but it still does what it does very well.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3002" height="400" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/postgis_evernote1.png" title="PostGIS items from Planet Geospatial in Evernote" width="640" /></p>

<p>Two of my favorite tools for culling down the firehose that is Planet Geospatial are <a href="http://ifttt.com" target="_blank">IFTTT</a> (the title of this post is a riff on the IFTTT motto) and <a href="http://evernote.com/" target="_blank">Evernote</a>. If you're not familiar with IFTTT, you should be. It reminds me of a more-intuitive Yahoo Pipes and it allows you to mix channels, triggers, and actions to automate processes of your choosing. It's become by preferred method of synchronizing my blog with social media and for filtering data sources. It also drives the <a href="http://twitter.com/QGISInfo" target="_blank">Unofficial QGIS Info</a> Twitter account. <!--more--></p>

<p>Evernote is becoming a key tool for me to store and access notes and other kinds of information. The fact that it runs on every device I own in addition to browsers makes it very useful for me as I move between customer locations.</p>

<p>When James first posted that he was wondering what to do with Planet Geospatial, I shared with him an IFTTT recipe that inserts posts from Planet Geospatial about <a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> into an Evernote notebook. He kindly tweeted it.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Try this IFTTT Recipe: Log PostGIS Items from Planet Geospatial to Evernote. <a href="https://t.co/z5hOxPqH" title="https://ifttt.com/recipes/67215">ifttt.com/recipes/67215</a></p>&mdash; James Fee (@cageyjames) <a href="https://twitter.com/cageyjames/status/272025049526050816" data-datetime="2012-11-23T17:13:20+00:00">November 23, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>I usually have three to four such filters running, depending upon topics that I'm watching. Currently, I'm grabbing posts about PostGIS, <a href="http://geojson.org" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>, and <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/" target="_blank">CartoCSS</a>. These filters allow me to peruse the posts at my leisure without worrying about missing them. I can delete them from my notebook or save them as I see fit. For me, it's like having a DVR for Planet Geospatial.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Planet Geospatial is an information source. It just happens to be an information source that's based on a mature, open, well-documented, and widely adopted standard. As such, there's no need to wait for James to evolve it into something else. We can take it and transform it to meet our needs and then share it back. It's been a great community resource for a long time; it will be fun to see what the community can do with it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Biggest News You May Have Missed...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/19/the-biggest-news-you-may-have-missed/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/19/the-biggest-news-you-may-have-missed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you missed it, this tweet floated across the Twitters last week:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Blogged: TileMill Connect - Open Mxd Documents in @<a href="https://twitter.com/mapbox">mapbox</a> TileMill <a href="http://t.co/hDicr4z0" title="http://bit.ly/WbBOKW">bit.ly/WbBOKW</a></p>&mdash; Arc2Earth (@Arc2Earth) <a href="https://twitter.com/Arc2Earth/status/269194049230102528" data-datetime="2012-11-15T21:43:57+00:00">November 15, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>Yes, the team at <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> is apparently working on a new feature in <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/services/sync/">Arc2Earth Sync,</a> called TileMill Connect, that will link <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcMap</a> MXDs with <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/">TileMill</a>. This will allow users to migrate their ArcMap cartography into TileMill to take advantage of the rich tools there as well as the potential for version control and cut/paste sharing of techniques and best practices enabled by <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/">CartoCSS</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/bFlood">Brian Flood</a> followed that up today with a short video showing it in action.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>quick TileMill Connect demo video showing how it works. <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23mapbox">#mapbox</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23arcgis">#arcgis</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23tilemill">#tilemill</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23arc2earth">#arc2earth</a> <a href="http://t.co/8WFdqCqH" title="http://bit.ly/QTWqpH">bit.ly/QTWqpH</a></p>&mdash; Arc2Earth (@Arc2Earth) <a href="https://twitter.com/Arc2Earth/status/270631991110692865" data-datetime="2012-11-19T20:57:49+00:00">November 19, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>No word on a timetable for this feature, but I can't wait to kick the tires. I am especially intrigued by the pseudo <a href="http://www.postgis.org">PostGIS</a> proxy service that enables connections to ArcGIS data sources.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Geospatial Workflows]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've had a couple of people ask me recently about the geospatial tools I use. Year-over-year, that answer changes but here's how I answer that right now:</p>

<p>As a Federal contractor, I spend a lot of time working with the <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> stack during my work day. A few years ago, I added a few open-source geospatial tools into my tool set and, since then, have also done a respectable amount to consulting work them as well. The balance between the two varies over time, depending on the requirements of individual customers and projects. Lately, commercial customers have seemed much more interested in open-source tools while my government customers are sticking with Esri. Since those observations are based on the the extremely heavy filter of my own recent experience, I'd be hesitant to draw any larger conclusions from them.</p>

<p><img alt="" height="264" src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/duct-tape.jpg" title="Duct Tape" width="300" /></p>

<p>I've always believed that proficiency with a wide range of tools makes me a better consultant and integrator, so I am always exploring and trying new things. With those commercial customers, and in my own personal side projects, my recent workflows have gelled around a core set of tools, both commercial and open-source: <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> - I am very comfortable with SQL and tend to use <a href="http://www.postgresql.org" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> and PostGIS for a lot of my vector data processing. Lately, this has mainly involved joining up geometries with attributes and doing aggregations and similar things. For example, the vector data in this <a href="http://geobabbler.github.com/mdq62012.html" target="_blank">map of the county-level Maryland Question 6 results</a> was processed in PostGIS. Very simply, I have a baseline table of the counties of Maryland which I will use to create new data sets. In this case, I imported a CSV of the election results, created a view that joined up the data and then selected the view into a new table. This is workflow is much easier with PostGIS 2.x thanks to the <a href="http://blog.opengeo.org/2012/03/06/postgis-2-0-new-features-typmod/" target="_blank">use of typmod</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a> - In the case of the map mentioned above, the data set is ultimately going to be static so it makes sense to serve it as static content, rather than bringing a heavyweight geospatial server such as <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgisserver/" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> or <a href="http://geoserver.org/display/GEOS/Welcome" target="_blank">GeoServer</a> into the mix. In these cases, I lean toward <a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>. QGIS makes it very easy to export any vector layer out to GeoJSON so it's become my go-to tool for that. QGIS also has great analytical tools and I consider it a complete functional match for ArcMap but, having said that, I'm actually very comfortable with the spatial SQL functions in PostGIS so I end up doing most of my analytical work there.</p>

<p><a href="http://leafletjs.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a>/<a href="http://www.openlayers.org/" target="_blank">OpenLayers</a> - Most of the web maps I'm doing are single-use and pretty straightforward. When that's the case, I prefer to use Leaflet as it's a pretty lightweight library. That said, I keep OpenLayers in the mix if the GIS-like requirements get a little more complex. OpenLayers does more "out of the box" than Leaflet but Leaflet is trimmer so it really depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/" target="_blank">Arc2Earth</a>/<a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill </a>- Arc2Earth is a commercial extension to ArcGIS and I lean on it to make tiles, although it does a lot more than that. I also use TileMill for this purpose but it really depends on where my cartography resides. There's a lot of good cartography locked up in MXDs and Arc2Earth is just a great way to capitalize on that. It's also nice that Arc2Earth works in ArcMap, eliminating the need for a license of Server.  If I'm building my cartography from scratch, which is not really my strong suit, I'll lean toward TileMill because it more easily connects directly to PostGIS, which is where my data tends to reside if I have my druthers. Again, it depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.python.org/" target="_blank">Python</a>/Javascript - I'm doing a lot more work in Python these days. It's become the <em>lingua franca</em> of GIS development in my book. Additionally, the capabilities of Javascript for web maps is evolving at a stunning pace. I can't see being productive in the long term in the geospatial field without proficiency in these two languages.</p>

<p>So these are the tools that I'm using most often these days as part of my personal workflows. The stable of tools that I use evolves over time, as should be evident if you peruse this blog. In general, I'm finding it very easy to be productive with these tools right now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How long until the ads stop?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/how-long-until-the-ads-stop/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/how-long-until-the-ads-stop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In celebration of this day when the non-stop political ads, robo-calls, junk mail, and social media posts <em>should</em> finally come to an end. I threw together a little map to show the latest time at which polls close in each state. This should represent, state-by-state, the time (EST) at which you can safely go back to answering your phones. Click the image below to go there (the data takes a couple of seconds to load).</p>

<p><a href="http://demo.zekiah.com/polls"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2947" height="331" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/pollmap.png" title="pollmap" width="640" /></a></p>

<p>Democracy is a wonderful thing, but it will be nice to have this campaign season behind us.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/K1vaEweJUUk?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Still Jonesing for zigGIS? Try this OGR Plug-In for ArcGIS.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I've actually noticed a surprising uptick in traffic related to <a href="https://code.google.com/p/ziggis/" target="_blank">zigGIS</a> lately? We also had someone asking about <a href="http://www.st-links.com/Pages/default.aspx" target="_blank">ST-Links</a> on the zigGIS mailing list last week. Clearly, there's still a level of interest out there for the problem that zigGIS was designed for.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank"><img alt="ArcGIS and SpatiaLite" height="65%" src="https://a248.e.akamai.net/camo.github.com/c1c86347c63522cb0f5f449b7b9df4209923c3ed/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f53767a6a702e706e67" width="65%" /></a></p>

<div style="font-size: 70%;"><strong>ArcGIS reading SpatiaLite natively, thanks to OGR and Ragi Burhum</strong></div>


<br />


<p>Along those lines, <a href="http://twitter.com/rburhum" target="_blank">Ragi Burhum</a> posted an <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank">OGR Workspace plug-in for ArcGIS</a> up on GitHub. Using OGR is really the magic ticket and the project is available under a BSD license (which Ragi explains very well). The only word to the wise is that pre-built binaries and installers aren't available yet so you Windows/<a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> users will need to get your hands dirty.</p>

<p>I haven't used it yet but I plan to within the next week or so. Stay tuned for a follow up post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
