<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fulcrum | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/fulcrum/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-10T15:02:00-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Busy Day for Releases]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/04/04/a-busy-day-for-releases/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/04/04/a-busy-day-for-releases</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>3 April 2012 was a busy day for releases/announcements in the geospatial field:</p>

<p><a href="http://postgis.refractions.net/">PostGIS 2.0</a> - This long-anticipated major version of PostGIS was <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/node/1275">announced</a> with advanced features such as raster, topology, and 3D/4D indexing. Many have been using 2.0 for a while but the official release gives top-cover to organizations, such as some government agencies, that are not allowed to take systems "production" using software that is technically in beta.</p>

<p><a href="http://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> v1 - I've <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/13/cartodb-leaflet-easy/">blogged about CartoDB before</a> and it's an intriguing platform for hosting geospatial data and applications. It uses PostGIS 2.0 as its storage engine and exposes a lot of PostGIS capability through its API. It's a pretty elegant way to build interactive mapping applications. It's support of <a href="http://www.geojson.org/">GeoJSON</a> makes it easy to integrate with a number of mapping libraries</p>

<p><a href="http://graffitimapper.org">GraffitiMapper</a> - This is a location-based application built by <a href="http://spatialnetworks.com/">Spatial Networks</a> on their <a href="http://spatialnetworks.com/products/fulcrum/">Fulcrum</a> platform. It's a great example of a specialized crowd-sourcing application. In this case, capturing graffiti using location as a potential indicator of other activity. It also really showcases the flexibility of Fulcrum. The app is currently only available for iOS but rumor has it Android is in the works.</p>

<p>All-in-all, it was pretty exciting day. Congratulations to everyone involved in all of these releases.</p>

<p>Well, my toy box is now overflowing so it's time to start playing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
