<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sql server spatial | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/sql-server-spatial/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-23T08:37:59-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PgMap Is Now SpatialKit]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/25/pgmap-is-now-spatialkit/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/25/pgmap-is-now-spatialkit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/08/09/taking-a-look-at-pgmap/">I blogged a while back on PgMap</a>, a freeware ArcGIS extension for directly connecting to PostGIS. <a href="http://st-links.com/default.aspx">ST-Links</a>, the makers of PgMap, sent out an e-mail this morning announcing that PgMap and QMap (the equivalent technology for interacting with SQL Server 2008 spatial data) have been combined into a single tool called SpatialKit. This move comes as part of the 3.0 release of the tool.</p>

<p>The same announcement also mentioned a <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/spatialkit?hl=en">Google Group dedicated to SpatialKit</a>. When I took a look at PgMap before, it seemed to be a pretty nice tool so I'm looking forward to digging into this. If you were a previous user of zigGIS, or if you have experimented with ArcSquirrel for SQL Server 2008 access, you may want to check out SpatialKit.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQL Server SIG at the UC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/08/06/sql-server-sig-at-the-uc/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/08/06/sql-server-sig-at-the-uc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My blogging has been slower this time around because I've been doing a lot of booth duty. This is my thrid conference this year and some of our other staff are getting to go to the sessions. I did, however, go to the SQL Server SIG a little while ago.</p>

<p>Ed Katibah had a few tricks up his sleeve. First off, he dropped the news that, as of 11:00am, SQL Server 2008 is now in RTM. Very soon, the final version will be in our hands. That's great news to everyone who has been working with the CTPs and RCs.</p>

<p>Ed had few other nuggets. He described the stress-testing that SQL 2008 has undergone. In short, there has been about 375,000 hours of stress testing run against SQL 2008 so we should be able to expect it to be solid. Additionally, Microsoft has already been running on SQL 2008 for "a few months." To me, this is all great news that makes me feel even more confident about the product (which already had my confidence). When I first installed the November CTP, I felt that much of the platform was already production-ready but more testing and use can't have hurt.</p>

<p>Ed went on to describe the two spatial types and reationale for doing that. That discussion is well documented and I fall in the "it's a good thing category" mainly because of previous work with applications that had over-the-horizon requirements.</p>

<p>Ed gave props to Paul Ramsey during his talk when explaining the XY switching debate. It was great to see that kind of respect on display.</p>

<p>Some nuts and bolts: SQL 2008 limits spatial objects to about 250 million vertices. This greatly exceeds Ed's largest test case, which is a high-res vector data set of the world's oceans. Polygons are limited to about 65,000 holes. I think those limits leave a lot of wiggle room. He also discussed the significance of coordinate ordering for the geography data type. Basically, it's counter-clockwise for outer rings and clockwise for inner rings. This is consistent with implementations in Informix, DB2 and Oracle (those are what he mentioned). He did mention that this was an industry consensus but there was no official specification on this matter. Ed also mentioned it may be a topic of future discussion for OGC.</p>

<p>Ed also demonstrated the spatial results window in the SQL management Studio. This is a really nice tool that lets you visualize the results of your spatial SQL inside the management studio. As a developer, that will be a huge help because I won't have to do a test run to see if I got the query right. Ed just saved me a bunch of time!</p>

<p>Ed went on to announce a companion CodePlex site for SQL Server 2008 spatial tools: <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/sqlspatialtools">www.codeplex.com/SqlSpatialTools</a>. There are already some tools that Isaac has posted but Ed said that other tools will include shapefile and KML converters. The site will also be open to contribs from the community. All of the tools currently there were developed using the <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/isaac/archive/2008/05/30/our-upcoming-builder-api.aspx">Builder API</a> and full source code is available so they serve has great examples of working with the Builder API.</p>

<p>All in all, it was a great talk. Ed's one of the nicest guys ever and he is having a lot of fun with ArcSDE on SQL Server 2008.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upgrading to SQL Server 2008 February CTP]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/02/25/upgrading-to-sql-server-2008-february-ctp/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/02/25/upgrading-to-sql-server-2008-february-ctp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is no direct upgrade yet so you need to remove the November CTP. Apparently, the uninstall doesn't always work well (hey, it's beta). Luckily, <a href="http://dotnettim.spaces.live.com/blog/cns!4B800EB59FAEDC2A!152.entry">Tim's post</a> straightened me out. This worked for me. More accurately, the guidance in Michael's comment worked for me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQL Server 2008 and 2005 Side-By-Side]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/02/01/sql-server-2008-and-2005-side-by-side/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/02/01/sql-server-2008-and-2005-side-by-side</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Installing the the SQL Server 2008 November CTP side-by-side with SQL Server 2005 is very straightforward. On the previous build of my machine, I had them both running just fine. After my system crash, I began setting things up again. Because I had been working with 2008 before the crash, I installed that first and then got around to 2005 later.</p>

<p>It should have been obvious to me before I did that but installing them in that order seems to break a lot of stuff in 2008. Kinda makes sense. I was a little flustered at having to rebuild in the first place and perhaps rushing things a bit but here it is for the record: If you are installing both of them on a new box, put on 2005 first.</p>

<p>Generally the database engine worked well. Most of the issues I had came up in the management studio. After installing 2005, many of the dialogs and property pages in the Katmai management studio would no longer display. Attempting to invoke them usually resulted in a "class not registered" exception.</p>

<p>In order to fix that, I had to remove and then re-install 2008. Before doing that, I detached my databases and then re-attached them after I was done. Everything works fine now.</p>

<p>This probably says more about me than it does SQL Server ;) but I thought I'd share.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQL Server 2008 Spatial - One Month Later]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/28/sql-server-2008-spatial-one-month-later/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/28/sql-server-2008-spatial-one-month-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So it's been about a month since the release of the SQL Server 2008 November CTP. I've been dabbling with it and have made several posts about it. I still have a lot more digging to do with it but here are my impressions after a month:<!--more--></p>

<ol>
<li><p>Geography - I was a little dubious about the use of two different spatial data types when I first cracked it open but have gradually begun to come around to this concept. I like the idea of a data type dedicated to spherical data. I'm sure that's in there to meet requirement of Virtual Earth but I can think of a number of uses. Specifically, certain types of signals modeling/simulation and over-the-horizon visibility analysis could benefit from it. I will admit that I haven't dug into the geography data type as much as I'd like to, but I plan to focus more on that after the first of the year.</p></li>
<li><p>Spatial References - From a GIS perspective, support for spatial references could be seen as a little thin. Oracle, PostGIS and ArcSDE have spoiled me into expecting the database to do it all for me but MSFT seems to be taking a different view here. They've provided the geometry data type and you can specify an SRID but it's pretty much left to the application to know what to do with it. Taking the long view, there is an opportunity here for a third-party or open-source solution to provide the capability that the GIS community has come to expect. It's not a stretch to imagine something like <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/Wiki/View.aspx?ProjectName=MsSqlSpatial">MsSqlSpatial</a> modified to use the SQL2008 geometry type. So, I've decided to keep my mind open here.</p></li>
<li><p><del datetime="2007-12-28T00:12:11+00:00">WKT - The X/Y switching issue is the only thing I've seen so far that really needs to be addressed and changed. I think this will be a can of worms.</del> Microsoft listened. <a href="http://www.sharpgis.net/2007/12/27/TheCommunityWorks.aspx">Morten</a> said it best: the community works!</p></li>
<li><p>Buzz - No denying it, there was a huge amount of pent-up demand for spatial support in SQL Server. In addition to the commercial support (slightly unprecedented for a CTP, I think), there's been quite a bit of activity among independent developers. It's important to remember that this is the first CTP in which spatial support has been included (although commercial partners had earlier access) so I would expect things to grow from here.</p></li>
<li><p>Spatial Indexing - I haven't dug into this too deeply except to note that a spatial index does (unsurprisingly) increase performance. I need to benchmark it more (like at all) from this standpoint. I'm also curious about behavior of spatial indices across table partitions. There were some deficiencies (IMHO) with spatial indices and partitioning with Oracle Spatial so I'm curious here.</p></li>
<li><p>Data Loading tools - There aren't any included that support spatial data. There is always <a href="http://www.safe.com/">FME</a> but I think there should at least be support for importing from a shapefile (and maybe GML or KML) in the 'SQL Server Import and Export Wizard' so that you have something to get going with. That may come in a later CTP but there's nothing there now.</p></li>
<li><p>Oh yeah, the rest of SQL Server. Kinda lost in all of the spatial discussion is that SQL 2008 is already pretty solid. As a whole, it's close to production quality now.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>In summation, I come away fairly impressed so far. I think that those of us who've been working with GIS (and spatial DB's) for a while will definitely need to change our mindsets when working with SQL Server. There are definitely some different viewpoints at work with it. Out of the box, it does less than you may be used to. That'll force your DBA's to get up to snuff with a lot of new concepts but it'll also present an opportunity in the 3rd party market.</p>

<p>So there's my two cents so far. This and $4.50 will get you...</p>

<p><img alt="You'll need it after staying up till 3:00 AM playing with SQL Server 2008" src="http://bigmarketing.files.wordpress.com/2007/05/starbucks_cup.jpg" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
