<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: MapServer | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/mapserver/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-08T22:59:36-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pre-FOSS4G Roundup]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/09/12/pre-foss4g-roundup/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/09/12/pre-foss4g-roundup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm getting ready to head out to Denver for the 2011 installment of <a href="http://2011.foss4g.org">FOSS4G</a>. It seems like my biggest problem will be figuring out how to clone myself in order to sit in every session. Open-source geospatial is such a vibrant and active area right now that there's just so much to see and learn.</p>

<p>A couple of things of note (to me) before I head out the door:</p>

<!--more-->


<ol>
<li>An announcement came through last week on the geowanking mailing list of a new tool called <a href="http://www.mxd2map.org/index.html">MXD2Map</a>, which purports to convert <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgis-for-desktop/index.html">ArcMap</a> MXD documents to <a href="http://mapserver.org/">MapServer</a> map files with corresponding <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/wms">WMS</a> and <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/wfs">WFS</a> services created. I have not had a chance to look at it yet (mainly because I don't have a current instance of MapServer running) but I'm excited to give it a go when I get a chance. From the MXD2Map site:</li>
</ol>


<blockquote>
What is MXD2map?
MXD2map has the ability to publish ArcGIS MXD-files as OGC webservices via UMN MapServer.

MXD2map combines the following advantages:

Create your maps within your accustomed working environment with ArcGIS Desktop
Convert your project into a UMN MapServer confiuration mapfile
Intranetwide publishing of your own data via OGC webservices (e.g. WMS/WFS)
MXD2map is actively supported by <a href="http://www.bsh.de/">Bundesamt fuer Seeschifffahrt und Hydrographie</a> in Hamburg.
</blockquote>


<ol>
<li><p>It seems to me that a greater number of questions on <a href="http://gis.stackexchange.com/">gis.stackexchange.com</a> are related to open-source GIS tools these days. Occasionally, questions from the site catch my eye in my Twitter timeline and it seemed like more and more were discussing open-source tools. As I wrote this post this morning, 17 of the first 50 questions were related to various open-source geospatial tools, ranging from desktop to web to database to libraries. This is a purely anecdotal observation on my part but the increase of questions on a forum like this seems to point to potentially greater activity in terms of using these tools to implement solutions.</p></li>
<li><p>A little <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Front_Range">Front Range</a> love. I watched the activity at <a href="http://stateofthemap.org/">SOTM11</a> via Twitter off and on this weekend. This leads into FOSS4G and follows less than two weeks after <a href="http://www.gisintherockies.org/GISITR2011/Home/Default.aspx">GIS in the Rockies</a> (also in Denver). I think the Front Range just effectively demonstrated that it is the leading region in the country in terms of all things spatial.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>That's it. I'm excited about catching up with old friends, meeting new ones, connecting Twitter avatars to real faces, and soaking up lots of FOSS4G knowledge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
