<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PIM | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/pim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-09T10:03:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meanwhile, Over at Zekiah...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/06/meanwhile/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T11:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/06/meanwhile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't usually cross-pollinate between this, my personal blog, and the company blog over at <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a>. One of the great things about working at a place like Zekiah, however, is the opportunity to work with smart people and see what they are doing. At times, my colleagues will share components of their work on the company blog. We encourage this, and the experimentation that leads to the posts, as a way to keep our technical capabilities fresh and to also showcase what we do in a way that goes beyond the typical capabilities statements that exist on every site. My colleagues have been pretty busy but have managed to take some time to write a few posts about their work:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/02/04/esri-cityengine-unity-40-and-oculus-rift">Esri CityEngine, Unity 4.0 and the Oculus Rift</a> - My colleague, <a href="http://twitter.com/DanEntzian">Dan Entzian</a>, is an avid gamer, a great developer, and a smart GIS guy. This post combines those interests by showing how to bring cities created in Esri's <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/cityengine/">CityEngine</a> into gaming environments like <a href="http://unity3d.com/">Unity</a> and integrate them with the <a href="http://www.oculusvr.com/">Oculus Rift</a> virtual reality display. It's a quick, but detailed, read that shows the interactions possible between geospatial tools and games.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/unity_ide.png" /></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/01/23/using-awk-ease-your-csv-manipulation">Using AWK to ease your CSV manipulation</a> - <a href="http://twitter.com/hugoestr">Hugo Estrada</a> shows how to use an old, but still effective, tool, <a href="http://www.grymoire.com/Unix/Awk.html">AWK</a>, to process GPS data for use in GIS software. This post is a great reminder that the best tool for the job may already be sitting there at our command prompt waiting for us.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2013/12/18/exporting-esri-silverlight-graphic-layer-google-earth-part-2">Exporting ESRI Silverlight Graphic Layer to Google Earth, Part 2</a> - While Silverlight is, politely speaking, passe, we have a few customers that are still attached to it. Generally, the systems that are using it are accredited systems of record so a rip-and-replace of Silverlight (or any other component) is simply not feasible without a significant paperwork drill. So we try to help our customers keep those systems as useful for their end users as possible. This post, also by Dan Entzian, illustrates how we did that in one case. A follow up to <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2011/10/11/exporting-esri-silverlight-graphic-layer-google-earth">an older post</a>, this post was done in response to an e-mail inquiry from a reader of the previous post.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2013/12/17/overview-clojure">An Overview of Clojure</a> - In this post, Hugo Estrada takes a look a <a href="http://clojure.org/">Clojure</a>, a variant of the Lisp programming language, and reports on his experience at Clojure Con. I found this particularly interesting since, as a lifelong programmer, I am always interested in new languages (even if it is getting harder to find the time to tinker with them myself).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/01/02/generating-physical-schemas-pim">Generating Physical Schemas From a PIM</a> - Okay, this one was written by me, but the work is pretty interesting and involved the efforts of a few co-workers, including Barry Schimpf and Dan Entzian. This post describes a tool that we developed as part of our overall approach to geospatial data model management. This script generator produces SQL scripts for either <a href="http://postgis.net/">PostGIS</a> or <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/">SpatiaLite</a> that enable a user to create spatial databases that are compliant with a data model. The information for the data model (which is always user-defined, not proscribed by us) is stored in what we call the platform independent model, or <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim">PIM</a>. We've used the PIM, its encapsulating API, and tools to good effect for a couple of customers now. This post attempts to provide a concrete picture of what can be an abstract concept.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Since Zekiah is a services company, rather than a platform company, we get to work with a broad range of technologies in support of our customers, in addition to our own internal research. This makes each day pretty interesting and can also make for lively conversation at company events. As the posts above showcase, my colleagues are working on some interesting things and it's a pleasure to work them each day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[File Geodatabase Schema Compare Tool]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/01/08/file-geodatabase-compare-tool/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T20:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/01/08/file-geodatabase-compare-tool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my work supporting various aspects of geospatial data modeling, I've spent a lot of time delving into concepts around configuration management of such data models. We've been able to apply a core tool set to perform various functions such as version managment, profiling, version-to-version migration, and validation in conjunction with a system we call the platform independent model (PIM). I gave quick overview of the PIM <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/01/02/generating-physical-schemas-pim">in this post over on the Zekiah blog</a> and the complete series on it <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim">can be found here</a>.</p>

<p>I've recently spent a bit of time consolidating code after a recent data delivery and decided to post a utility that was an outgrowth of that effort: <a href="https://github.com/Zekiah/ArcGISCompare">a tool to compare schemas of two Esri file geodatabases and report differences</a>. This lent itself to general use because it does not require any connection to a PIM.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="https://github.com/Zekiah/ArcGISCompare/raw/master/screenshot.png" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>The PIM deals mainly at the logical level with data models, but a full configuration management workflow must occasionally touch physical data sets. One use case we had to support, for which this tool was built, was the case where users in the field must compare separate data sets for eventual integration. Although these workflows start with a template data set, it is not unusal for changes to be made during collection, resulting in very similar but not identical schemas. This tool helps users identify such differences in order to make configuration management decisions based upon the actual state of the collected data.</p>

<p>The tool is fairly straightforward: choose a template data set, choose an implementation data set, run the compare, and examine the results. It contains ArcObjects dependencies although we may migrate it to the file geodatabase API in order to eliminate those.</p>

<p>We are also in the process of building a similar tool to work with SQLite/SpatiaLite data sets, which is the other format we commonly see used and will post that tool when it is complete. In the meantime, I hope you find this application useful.</p>

<p>An installer (10.1) <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6749645/PIM/setup_ArcGISCompare.zip">can be found here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ToGeoJson and ToWKT for the Esri FGDB API]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/24/togeojson-and-towkt-for-the-esri-fgdb-api/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/24/togeojson-and-towkt-for-the-esri-fgdb-api</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In support of some of our ongoing <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim" target="_blank">PIM</a> work, we've been integrating the <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> <a href="http://resources.arcgis.com/content/geodatabases/10.0/file-gdb-api" target="_blank">File Geodatabase (FGDB) API</a> into some tools. Without going into a level of detail that would hijack this post, one of the many functions performed by some of the tools is to validate physical spatial databases against established data models to analyze compliance and identify differences. These databases may be in Esri or non-Esri formats and we have traditionally handled Esri geodatabases through ArcObjects since it provides a relatively uniform interface across the various flavors of geodatabase.</p>

<p><img alt="" style="text-align: center;" height="300" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/fileapi2.png" title="FGDB API" width="287" /></p>

<p>Of course, ArcObjects requires an ArcGIS license of some sort and we are finding out that this is not always available to users in the field under many situations so the FGDB API gets past that for file geodatabases, at least. <!--more--></p>

<p>Since the PIM is really a configuration management system for spatial data models, the tools need to support a wide variety of scenarios, including data migration between platforms, versions, approved user-defined implementations, etc. in a manner that's compliant with the data model being managed. As a result, some ETL-like tools are built into the workflows, although ETL is not a primary focus of the PIM.</p>

<p>Since the PIM tools are written in .NET, I built a couple of extension methods to assist with some of the workflows in the existing tools. They enable outbound support for GeoJSON and WKT. The GeoJSON methods work on RowCollection, Row, and ShapeBuffer objects to create FeatureCollection, Feature, and Geometry types respectively. In practice, they'd be used something like this example from a very simple ASP.NET MVC sample application:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='csharp'><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">path</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">Server</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">MapPath</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/App_Data/mvc_samples.gdb&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">Geodatabase</span> <span class="n">gdb</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">Geodatabase</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Open</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">path</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">Table</span> <span class="n">statesTable</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">gdb</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">OpenTable</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;\us_states&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">RowCollection</span> <span class="n">rows</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">statesTable</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Search</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;*&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&quot;STATE_NAME LIKE &#39;M%&#39;&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">RowInstance</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Recycle</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">var</span> <span class="n">rval</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">rows</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ToGeoJson</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">gdb</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Close</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">Response</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ContentType</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">&quot;application/json&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">object</span> <span class="n">result</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">Content</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">rval</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">result</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">ActionResult</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>The WKT method only works on ShapeBuffer objects to export geometries. The code for the extension methods themselves can be found on <a href="https://github.com/geobabbler/FgdbExtensions" target="_blank">GitHub here</a>. It includes a five-minutes-or-less MVC sample from which the above code was lifted. I know I'll be doing some cleanup on the GeoJSON in the near future and I'll probably add support for EWKT to smooth our interactions with <a href="http://postgis.refractions.net/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> and <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> and may also add support for WKB.</p>

<p>As I said, I developed these to support workflows in existing applications. If you're looking to just perform data conversion or ETL, you should just use <a href="http://www.gdal.org/ogr/" target="_blank">OGR</a> or <a href="http://www.safe.com/" target="_blank">FME</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breaking Radio Silence]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/07/breaking-radio-silence/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/07/breaking-radio-silence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things have been kind of quiet on the blog lately due to things being busy at work. I call that a good problem to have. Since the beginning of the year, I've written a a lot of proposals for a mixture of potential customers. Interestingly, I'm seeing a lot more call for "GIS Analyst" work. One trend I've noticed, at least in the Federal sector, is that the time between proposal due dates and award announcements seems to be lengthening. That may be an indication of the ongoing flux in funding and organizations try to figure out how to fund their requirements. It will be interesting to see how it shakes out. Of course, it's good that the opportunities are there in the first place.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/microphone.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2664" height="413" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/microphone.jpg" title="microphone" width="413" /></a></p>

<p>One the technical side of things, I've been involved in a smattering of things that's made it hard to roll up one good post. I'm pretty heavily involved in the PIM efforts that my colleague, Barry Schimpf, <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim" target="_blank">has been blogging about</a> over on the <a href="http://www.zekiah.com" target="_blank">Zekiah</a> blog. <!--more--> Historically, the PIM data structures have been housed in Microsoft SQL Server, but we've been working on porting it to other platforms to provide options to end users. We've done an initial port to <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> but we've been spending most of our time on a <a href="http://www.sqlite.org/" target="_blank">SQLite</a>/<a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> version. This has taken two forms. First is the port of the PIM structure itself to SQLite to make it easier to provide some of the PIM services such as profiling, version-to-version migrations, dataset generation, and validation in remote, field-based settings. Second is the generation/validation of physical implementations in SpatiaLite. This is being done for a customer who is expecting to do field data collection using SpatiaLite and these services will be helpful in enhancing data quality at the point of collection. Additionally, the SpatiaLite aspect of this work has had me living within <a href="http://qgis.org/" target="_blank">QGIS</a> lately.</p>

<p>Another thing I've been experimenting with is the use of <a href="http://nodejs.org/" target="_blank">Node.js</a> for real-time data processing. Our long-standing work in the situational awareness realm has had us working with real-time data feeds for a long time. I'm interested in the possibility of using Node to tackle some of the feed collection tasks. I've used an event-driven approach for such tasks in the past so that aspect of Node is quite familiar to me but the use of Javascript, its ease of deployment and potential scalability are intriguing to me. I'm coming late to the party with Node, primarily due to my rustiness with Javascript, but I'm liking what I'm seeing so far.</p>

<p>Beyond those major things, I've had the opportunity to start working with <a href="http://postgis.org/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> 2.0 and play more with <a href="http://leaflet.cloudmade.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a> and <a href="http://mapbox.com/" target="_blank">MapBox</a>. On the development side of things, these efforts have had be jumping back and forth a lot between C#, Javascript and a little bit of Python, as well as between Windows and Linux, depending on the task.</p>

<p>You'll notice that I didn't mention any <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> tools. That's primarily because recent demand from my customers has led me to a different tool set. I expect that to level out somewhat in the near future since many of the outstanding proposals I mentioned have a strong Esri flavor. As always, having a broad toolbox can be an asset in consulting. I'll be skipping San Diego again this year. I'm finding that Esri's Federal Conference in DC is of such increasing quality each year that it fulfills my needs for Esri-related information. That's really okay with me because I'd rather spend as much of the summer with my family as possible. So it's not so much a down-vote of Esri as my taking advantage of options that fit into my life better.</p>

<p>I hope to be able blog in more detail about some of these efforts as I get farther along with them. Times like this make it exciting to work in the geospatial field. There's a lot of churn in the market right now with regard to tools and technologies. I'm not sure I can perceive any meaningful gap between the capabilities of open-source and proprietary geospatial tools anymore. As a result, there are a lot of options to choose from for building robust systems and applications. It looks to be a fun summer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Configuration Management for Geospatial Data Models]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/03/27/configuration-management-for-geospatial-data-models/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/03/27/configuration-management-for-geospatial-data-models</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to take a opportunity to do something I don't often do, and draw attention to a series of posts that's going on over on <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog">my company's blog</a>. About a year ago, my company, <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah Technologies</a> joined forces with Upper 90 Systems. Upper 90 was probably best known for their work building tools that supported the Spatial Data Standard for Facilities, Infrastructure, and Environment (SDSFIE), which is a data model that is used by the US DOD to standardize the representation of GIS data for the purpose of performing facilities management on military installations.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.acq.osd.mil/ie/bei/disdi/factsheet_sdsfie.pdf" target="_blank">SDSFIE</a> (PDF) has existed for some time, with several versions of the standard being rolled out to its diverse user community. Through that process, we've learned a thing or two about configuration management of widely-implemented geospatial data models. This understanding has been turned into a series of tools designed to help with the issues surround lifecycle management of a data model (as opposed to physical databases themselves). <!--more--></p>

<p>The approach and tools are loosely referred to as the "platform-independent model", or PIM. We call it that because the model defines the rules that govern how to create and manage a geospatial database in compliance with a given data standard, but the model is not the database itself. As a result, we can support physical implementations on any number of platforms (Esri, PostGIS, Oracle Spatial, SpatiaLite, Bentley, Autodesk, etc.). The tools give users the ability to perform version management, schema generation, compliance checking, profiling, development of migration paths between versions and many other functions.</p>

<p>Barry Schimpf, the former president of Upper 90 Systems and now my colleague at Zekiah, has been working on a series of posts describing this approach and, eventually, the tools. Three posts have gone up with others on the way:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2012/01/13/expanding-usefulness-geospatial-data-standards" target="_blank">Expanding Usefulness of Geospatial Data Standards</a>
<a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2012/03/19/applying-flexible-yet-standard-geospatial-conventions" target="_blank">Applying Flexible, Yet Standard, Geospatial Conventions</a>
<a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2012/03/24/understanding-geospatial-data-rules-platform-independent-model-pim" target="_blank">Understanding Geospatial Data Rules in the Platform Independent Model (PIM)</a></p>

<p>The approach Barry discusses has already been leveraged to support Federal data models beyond SDSFIE so we know it is transferable. We think it could have benefits for at the state, local, or regional levels as well. I encourage you to check out the posts and keep an eye out for more as they emerge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
