<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: DotSpatial | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/dotspatial/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-24T14:00:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MapWindow Open-Source Conference Coming Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/05/25/mapwindow-open-source-conference-coming-up/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/05/25/mapwindow-open-source-conference-coming-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to Twitter, I see that the <a href="http://www.mapwindow.org/conference/2012/" target="_blank">3rd annual MapWindow Open-Source GIS Conference</a> is coming up at the end of June. It is being held in Velp, The Netherlands. I call this conference out because it has a strong, but not exclusive, concentration on open-source GIS tools for the .Net environment, such as <a href="http://dotspatial.codeplex.com/" target="_blank">DotSpatial</a>, <a href="http://sharpmap.codeplex.com/" target="_blank">SharpMap</a>, and <a href="https://code.google.com/p/nettopologysuite/" target="_blank">NTS</a>. Additionally, there will be content on non-.Net tools such as PostGIS, OpenLayers and others. This makes sense as any complete stack usually contains a mix of technologies. <a href="http://postgis.org/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> is almost the <em>de facto</em> standard back-end for open-source geo stacks and <a href="http://qgis.org/" target="_blank">QGIS</a> is probably the best open-source editor for it so inclusion of such tools is quite necessary.</p>

<p><img alt="MapWindow" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/mapwindow.png?w=245" /></p>

<p>For a number of reasons, I can't attend but I'll be watching the live stream with interest. It's location in Europe makes a lot of sense. I've always noticed that my early posts on SharpMap get a large portion of traffic from Europe and a majority of the user base of <a href="https://code.google.com/p/ziggis/" target="_blank">zigGIS</a> was European so I suspect there is a lot of demand there for open-source tools built on .Net. This conference could be a good one-stop shop if you are interested in such tools.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
