<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: foursquare | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/foursquare/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-18T22:16:30-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Completing the Model]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/10/27/Completing-the-Model/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/10/27/Completing-the-Model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been a truism for some time that GIS enables us to build models of the Earth. Esri Press has even offered a book on geodatabase design called ?<a href="http://esripress.esri.com/display/index.cfm?fuseaction=display&amp;websiteID=27">Modeling Our World</a>? for a while. Traditionally, GIS has given us the ability to model the surface of the earth (in a broad sense), including our effect upon it. That can be extended to subsurface modeling and weather modeling and similar concepts but, in general, GIS has focused on the surface of the earth, plus or minus a few thousand meters or so. <!--more--></p>

<p>One important aspect of our world that has defied modeling with traditional GIS tools is us. While it?s true that we can use GIS to do demographic analysis that market analysis and the like, those applications have typically fallen into the sweet spot of traditional GIS in that they typically involve analyzing aggregations of data captured over a period of time. These applications, like most others that are well-handled by GIS, are slow-moving.</p>

<p><img alt="" height="308" src="http://bulgaria.usembassy.gov/uploads/sO/bX/sObXJ0cSW96V4g6DMGj4hA/earth.gif" title="Earth" width="303" /></p>

<p>All of these applications have a lot of value (or else most of us wouldn?t be doing our current jobs), but they present an incomplete picture. If we were to take the model of our world as represented by traditional GIS, turn it into reality and place that world in orbit; I suspect an alien visitor would come upon it and find a lifeless world with strong evidence that a people once lived there. GIS does a great job of showing the expansion of new subdivisions and their parcels, road networks, utility networks, the demographic makeup of their residents and the like. But, every day, each of those people leaves their homes and goes to countless locations throughout their day for brief time periods and myriad reasons. Such movements are fleeting and not well-handled by traditional GIS tools.</p>

<p>Over the last few years, the emergence of location-aware social media has given us a window into these fleeting aspects of human behavior. Tools such as <a href="http://foursquare.com">Foursquare</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com">Twitter </a>and <a href="http://facebook.com">Facebook</a>, combined with microformats such as <a href="http://www.georss.org/Main_Page">GeoRSS</a> and <a href="http://geojson.org/">GeoJSON</a> and wired into advanced smartphone platforms (and many other technologies) are building a ?story? that is profound. We can see who was doing what, where they did it and when. This clearly has some ?Big Brother? implications that we must consider. But, over time, it can provide a detailed picture of almost archaeological significance (imagine the value of the Twitter stream of one day in Republican Rome).</p>

<p>The exploitation of these information streams is still in its infancy. We?ll see a lot of micro-targeting of content such as advertising (cast a smaller net more precisely) and other such applications. Geo-fencing has also gotten a lot of press lately. That?s a concept that has been worked with great value over the years in the defense and security worlds, but may have found its ?killer app? with location-aware social media. Many other applications and tools are on the way; I?m sure, as more people turn their imagination to them.</p>

<p>So, while there?s been a lot of churn regarding the value of such streams (?Don?t clutter my Twitter timeline with your check-ins!?), they are here to stay. They help us complete the model by enabling us to model ourselves; the way we live, at the pace we live.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Foursquare - Teetering On the Edge of YASN]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/12/30/Foursquare-Teetering-On-the-Edge-of-YASN/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/12/30/Foursquare-Teetering-On-the-Edge-of-YASN</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I read with interest this <a href="http://www.thebigmoney.com/articles/0s-1s-and-s/2009/12/28/im-mayor-latte-stand">article</a> that was brought to my attention by <a href="http://twitter.com/gis_Todd">@gis_Todd</a> on Twitter. I have been playing with <a href="http://www.foursquare.com">Foursquare</a> for a few weeks now and I think this article is in sync with some observations I have had about it but also misses the mark on one key point.<!--more--></p>

<p>I am one of the older, non-urban users mentioned in the article and I have found Foursquare extremely cumbersome to use. That is compounded by the fact that it does not have a BlackBerry app so I am confined to using the mobile web page. Given that very few places I visit are already listed in Foursquare, I find that I need to ?add a venue? a lot. In the mobile web page, this process is cumbersome to the point of being a deterrent. So my GPS-enabled phone is of no use in this case.</p>

<p>I have had good experiences with applications like <a href="http://www.tripit.com/">TripIt</a> in terms of alerting networks of friends/colleagues to my travel plans. In the case of TripIt, each time I have updated it via <a href="http://www.linkedin.com">LinkedIn</a>, it has led to a good business meeting while I was on travel. As a result, I see the value in broadcasting location. I am less interested in being ?mayor? of someplace or earning badges and the like but, if that sort of thing works for someone, so be it.</p>

<p>It is here that I find a major shortcoming of Foursquare. Despite the fact that I have built networks in LinkedIn, <a href="http://twitter.com">Twitter</a> and <a href="http://www.facebook.com">Facebook</a>, Foursquare seems to want me to build another one and doesn?t seem to have any obvious way to link into networks that already exist. This is where Foursquare borders on <a href="http://acronyms.thefreedictionary.com/Yet+Another+Social+Networking+Service">YASN</a>.</p>

<p>Quite frankly, TripIt has already demonstrated far more of a value proposition for me than Foursquare. Why? Because it plugs directly into LinkedIn and notifies my LinkedIn connections when I am about to be in their vicinity and/or when I am currently in their vicinity. Of course, you may define value differently than me but I see that as more powerful than knowing that my friend is currently at a Thai restaurant across town. For one thing, ?across town? in the DC area can be 75 miles and, for another, I?m not going to drop whatever I?m doing to go meet them there.</p>

<p>So, as it stands right now, Foursquare rings rather hollow to me. It comes across as a one-trick pony that could easily be made obsolete by one good update to Facebook. Either that, or it is bait for an acquisition. In case you?re wondering, I have the same opinion of <a href="http://brightkite.com/">BrightKite</a>.</p>

<p>I stated earlier that the article misses the mark in one key area and it is with this statement: <em>?However, the biggest barrier to Foursquare?s omnipotence in the location-based app world is not its reliance on gaming mechanics, but its lack of a revenue stream.?</em> This statement is followed later by this one:<em> ?Maybe there is still a way to monetize that small sector of young, urban, male Foursquare obsessives, even if it doesn?t mean complete location-based dominance.?</em></p>

<p>This is primarily where, as <a href="http://twitter.com/ajturner">Andrew Turner</a> put it, the article is shortsighted. While it may be true that Foursquare doesn?t have a revenue stream yet, that doesn?t mean it lacks value. Foursquare leverages crowd-sourcing to build a constantly updated database of businesses and/or points of interest. I will, inevitably, add the new Chinese restaurant that is opening near my house and Foursquare will probably end up with that record before many of the standard business demographics providers. As we know, being first counts. Combine the venue information with the demographic information about who is checking in and you have a dataset of potentially great interest to marketers, advertisers and others. Of course, this value will only increase if the Foursquare application can broaden its appeal to begin generating meaningful demographic cross-sections.</p>

<p>When viewed from this standpoint, it makes sense that we can play Foursquare for free. We are, after all, providing the data that is its ultimate value.</p>

<p>So, yes, Foursquare needs to become valuable to rural and suburban residents. It needs to become relevant to older users and it needs to become easier to use for people who don?t have an iPhone or an Android phone. If Foursquare can expand its end-user relevance (why do I want to use it in the first place), then it may survive long enough to flex its muscles and show its true value. Otherwise, it?s yet another social network.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
