<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: renewable energy | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/renewable-energy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-08T22:37:30-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Check Out the NREL Renewable Energy Applications]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/16/check-out-the-nrel-renewable-energy-applications/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/16/check-out-the-nrel-renewable-energy-applications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Among the items in the category of "<a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/03/sharpening-the-saw/" target="_blank">what I care about</a>" are renewable energy and open-source geospatial tools. So I was happy to rediscover the <a href="http://maps.nrel.gov/" target="_blank">various online tools</a> by the <a href="http://www.nrel.gov/" target="_blank">National Renewable Energy Laboratory</a> in Golden, Colorado. Many of the tools have been available for some time but the <a href="http://www.nrel.gov/news/press/2012/1681.html">recent announcement</a> of the <a href="http://maps.nrel.gov/re_atlas" target="_blank">RE Atlas</a> application brought me back to them. <!--more--></p>

<p>RE Atlas is described as:</p>

<blockquote>The Renewable Energy Atlas is an interactive mapping tool to allow users to explore base level renewable energy resource datasets. The intention is to provide a broad overview of available data and provide appropriate links to allow users to explore the data in greater detail.</blockquote>


<p>I have also been browsing around the <a href="http://maps.nrel.gov/prospector">Solar Energy Prospector</a>, described as:</p>

<blockquote>The Prospector is a mapping tool developed for the Solar Power industry. This tool is designed to help developers site large-scale solar plants by providing easy access to solar resource datasets and other data relevant to utility-scale solar power projects.</blockquote>


<p>The front ends of these tools are built using open-source tools (<a href="http://openlayers.org/">OpenLayers</a>, <a href="http://drupal.org/">Drupal</a>, others). The interfaces provide a lot of capability, including query and download of underlying data. I like that the tools focus on making renewable energy data available to industry and private citizens for decision-making since uptake and investment by the private sector will be needed for renewable energy to gain lasting traction. These tools provide a good example of the potential for collaboration between government and industry to tackle challenging problems.</p>

<p>So, if you're looking for data related to renewable energy, these tools might be a good place to start.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
