<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: microsoft | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/microsoft/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-13T10:32:54-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SilverLight and ArcGIS Server 9.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/08/14/silverlight-and-arcgis-server-9-3/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/08/14/silverlight-and-arcgis-server-9-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://alpascual.com/blog/al/archive/2008/08/14/esri-silverlight-control-up-on-the-code-gallery.aspx">Al Pascual has posted</a> about a sample app <del datetime="00">he</del> Richie developed using <a href="http://silverlight.net/">SilverLight 2.0</a>. For those who have been wondering about this (like me), I highly encourage checking this out. The SilverLight <a href="http://labs.live.com/Silverlight+2+Deep+Zoom.aspx">Deep Zoom</a> technology is pretty impressive and it works well in IE, FireFox and Safari (on Windows anyway). See below.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/08/silverlight_ie_win.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-277" height="77" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/08/silverlight_ie_win.png?w=128" width="128" /></a> <a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/08/silverlight_firefox_win.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-277" height="77" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/08/silverlight_firefox_win.png?w=128" width="128" /></a> <a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/08/silverlight_safari_win.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-279" height="77" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/08/silverlight_safari_win.png?w=128" width="128" /></a></p>

<p>Links to the demos are on Al's blog. Source code is available from the code gallery. Good work <del datetime="00">Al</del> Richie!</p>

<p>Update! The first version of this post was incorrect. This application was written by <a href="http://mrrichie.spaces.live.com/blog/cns!DD16C3F34F4D913E!1841.entry">Richie Carmichael</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Microsoft Certifying Open-Source]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/04/04/microsoft-certifying-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/04/04/microsoft-certifying-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I got a link to <a href="http://seekingalpha.com/article/71145-microsoft-s-savvy-open-source-move">this article</a> on SlashDot. It discusses Microsoft's effort to begin actively certifying open-source applications for Windows Server 2008.</p>

<p>I see this as a positive move. I use a lot of open-source apps on Windows myself. Many of my customers are still downright suspicious of open-source (I know) and achieving Windows certification will make it a lot easier to introduce them into some of the environments I support.</p>

<p>Of course, those same environments are just now upgrading to Windows Server 2003 so maybe 2008 certification isn't such a big deal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MSDN Article on Mapping with WPF]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/18/msdn-article-on-mapping-with-wpf/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/18/msdn-article-on-mapping-with-wpf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/07/12/Maps/default.aspx">this article</a> today about using <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/express/vb/default.aspx">VB9</a> and <a href="http://windowsclient.net/Default.aspx">WPF</a> to draw thematic maps. It's a good walk-through of how to do it. The article admits that the coordinate transformation used is not terribly accurate but that can be rectified. This article is a good example of how to build a mapping application without any third-party components. The author converts Census boundary files to XML for this app. It shouldn't be a stretch to use <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/sql/2008/technologies/spatial.mspx">SQL 2008</a>, <a href="http://postgis.refractions.net">PostGIS</a> or some other database that can emit GML and has an OLEDB provider as a data source.</p>

<p>I've been using WPF with <a href="http://codeplex.com/SharpMap">SharpMap</a> on a project <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2007/08/14/sharpmap-and-wpf/">for a while</a> but my mapping code is about 5% of the overall project and I haven't had a chance to extract what I've done into something digestable to provide an example. I had to fit into the rendering paradigm of a previously developed GUI so it deviates from how it's shaping up in SharpMap 2.0.</p>

<p>So, if you're looking for an example of how to render spatial data in WPF, this is a good one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spatial References in SQL Server 2008, Part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/08/spatial-references-in-sql-server-2008-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/12/08/spatial-references-in-sql-server-2008-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little clarification is in order:</p>

<p>SQL Server 2008 Books Online makes the following statement about SRIDs:</p>

<blockquote>
"A SQL Server-supported SRID for geography instances must be used when performing calculations or using methods with geography spatial data. The SRID must match one of the SRIDs displayed in the sys.spatial_reference_systems catalog view."
</blockquote>


<p>As previously noted, SQL 2008 supports two spatial data types: geometry and geography. As can be seen, the above statement only applies to the geography data type. If you are using geometry, the SRID can be set to anything (I have done so). It would probably be a best practice to stick to <a href="http://www.epsg.org/">EPSG</a>-defined SRIDs but this does open up the possibility of user-defined spatial references similar to <a href="http://postgis.refractions.net">PostGIS</a>. <a href="http://forums.microsoft.com/MSDN/ShowPost.aspx?PostID=2505683&amp;SiteID=1">In a discussion with Isaac on the MSDN forum</a>, he clarified that they plan to leave such things to the discretion of the database designers/users for implementation. As can be seen in the discussion, it seems they may also write up some best practices but it seems many things such as constraints to limit SRIDs and geometry types will be left to users/developers/DBAs to implement.</p>

<p>So, as a result of the discussion, I think I have a better understanding of <a href="http://www.microsoft.com">MSFT</a>'s intent and how to proceed with SQL 2008. It will be interesting to adjust my way of thinking from what I have come to expect from other products.</p>

<p>Also, other discussions on the forum seem to indicate that this release will not have any coordinate transformation functions so those of us planning to use and develop with SQL 2008 should probably get comfortable with something like <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/ProjNET">Proj.Net</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes It's the Simple Stuff...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/04/15/sometimes-its-the-simple-stuff/"/>
    <updated>2007-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/04/15/sometimes-its-the-simple-stuff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've become very enamoured of the new VE-based map display at weather.com. For example, <a href="http://www.weather.com/outlook/homeandgarden/home/map/interactive/20622?from=36hour_map_large&amp;zoom=7&amp;interactiveMapLayer=radar">here's my location</a>. My wife had to drive out to Ohio yesterday and, with the big storm moving across the country, I've been spending more time at weather.com than usual.</p>

<p>Anyway, one of the most useful features of the display, from an interactive mapping standpoint, is one that seems rather innocuous. It's the little crosshair in the center of the map. This is the point that you'll zoom in to as you use the slider bar. You'll notice it here:</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/04/ve_crosshair.png" title="I guess vacation is over?"><img alt="I guess vacation is over?" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/04/ve_crosshair.thumbnail.png" /></a></p>

<p>My issue with the "slider bar" approach to zooming has always been how you have to eyeball your location to the center and then readjust as you zoom in. This one little feature has virtually eliminated the need to for me to do that. So that's the simple little detail that's making me happy today.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
