<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: javascript | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-08T23:31:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple Tile Viewer]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/04/25/simple-tile-viewer/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T14:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/04/25/simple-tile-viewer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We do a lot of tiles for various customers at <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a>. Tiling is as much art as science and sometimes things go wrong so we have a range of utilities that we use to perform various kids of QA. Because the caches can be large, we usually want to perform a visual QA on the static tiles before pushing them up to wherever they are going to live full-time.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/cacheviewer2.png" /></p>

<p>In order to facilitate that, I wrote a very simple tile viewer using <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> and <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</a>. It uses a config file to get everything it needs to operate so we just make our changes there. This application currently only works with Web Mercator tiles but I'm working on adding support for WGS84. It also doesn't work with 'compact' tiles from ArcGIS Server. It obviously requires Node, and it also requires an <a href="https://npmjs.org/">NPM</a> install of the 'open' module to facilitate opening the browser.</p>

<p>Anything else you need to know is in the readme. I hope you find it useful. It can be <a href="https://github.com/geobabbler/cacheview">downloaded here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[js.geo Day One]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/14/js-dot-geo-day-one/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-14T18:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/14/js-dot-geo-day-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I attended the <a href="http://geojs.eventbrite.com/">JS.geo</a> conference at the Colorado University Denver campus. It looked like about 100 or so came out for the event. I was able to catch up with <a href="http://twitter.com/cwhelm">Chris Helm</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/briantimoney">Brian Timoney</a> the night before and they told me the event took off faster than they had originally expected. I think this speaks to two things: 1) the level of interest in Javascript as a solution for geospatial applications and 2) the fast pace of innovation in the Javascript community that has a lot of people looking for ways to stay abreast of the latest developments.</p>

<p>What follows is an overview based on some of the notes I took. I wasn't always writing as I sometimes just stopped to listen and I'll probably follow up with more details later.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/jsgeo13.png" /></div>


<p>Data reduction was strong current running under the day. With the rise of newer libraries that enable more sophisticated capabilities in the browser, there is increased recognition of the need to reduce the amount of data passing over the wire. For geometry, <a href="https://github.com/mbostock/topojson">TopoJSON</a> is getting a lot of attention here. It delivers topologically correct data which reduces data by removing redundant geometry such coincident arcs between polygons and such. The output reminds me of an old <a href="http://www.gdal.org/ogr/drv_avcbin.html">ARC/INFO coverage</a> and is providing stunning results in reducing the size of geometries when compared to <a href="http://geojson.org">GeoJSON</a> or Esri JSON. <a href="http://twitter.com/andrewxhill">Andrew Hill</a> of <a href="http://vizzuality.com">Vizzuality</a> mentioned that <a href="http://cartodb.com">CartoDB</a> currently has support for TopoJSON in staging. He also discussed strategies they use to reduce the size of feature and attribute data. This "data cubing" strategy turns out to similar to approaches that are commonplace in the financial industry. This serves as a reminder to look around and see what others are doing to solve similar problems.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>One a related note, the reduction of application code being delivered to the browser is also a focus. This was probably best illustrated by <a href="http://twitter.com/mattpriour">Matt Priour's</a> talk on <a href="http://openlayers.org">OpenLayers</a>. The fact that there are now three builds (full, mobile, light) as well as a focus on being more modular in version 3. <a href="http://twitter.com/pmbatty">Peter Batty</a>, in his demo of <a href="http://www.ubisense.net/en/">Ubisense</a>, made a good case for intelligent balance between server-side and client-side processing to achieve good performance.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.khronos.org/webgl/">WebGL</a> got a lot of attention from a number of speakers, with <a href="http://twitter.com/brendankenny">Brendan Kenny</a> of Google showing work he has done, including a Javascript port of GLUTessellation. Jeremy Bartley of Esri gave a lightning talk about <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/cityengine">CityEngine</a>, which is based on WebGL. WebGL is widely seen as the open solution to graphics performance that may finally kill the need for plug-ins. In side discussions, Jeremy talked about how WebGL will figure more into the previously discussed data reduction problem. The reality is that both servers and clients are getting much better at handling large data sets but the same can't necessarily be said for the wires that connect them.</p>

<p>GeoJSON continues to get a lot of love. It continues to be, in my opinion, the motor oil for the engine that is web mapping. It will be interesting see how the separation of concerns between GeoJSON and TopoJSON evolves, but I think GeoJSON will continue to be an important syntax.</p>

<p>While the majority of the discussion focused on browsers, <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> got significant attention. <a href="http://twitter.com/willwhitedc">Will White</a> of <a href="http://mapbox.com">MapBox</a> gave a good talk about the evolution of Node and the advantages of its non-blocking I/O model. One statistic he gave was surprising: he said 6 of the top 12 contributors on GitHub are Node contributors. That speaks loudly to the rapid evolution of Node as well as the interest in Javascript. Will put out a call to the geospatial community to build out the geospatial capabilities of Node. Later in the day, we saw a good lightning talk that showed Node processing real-time data and feeding a number of D3 visualizations.</p>

<p>While Matt Priour and <a href="https://twitter.com/atogle">Aaron Ogle</a> opened with great talks on OpenLayers and <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</a>, respectively, the clear star of the client-side show was <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3</a> (although Aaron's walkshed analysis in Leaflet was cool). There were lots of great visualizations (as well as nods to TopoJSON). While the D3's support for projections is getting a lot of attention from geospatial developers, I am more interested in its holistic approach to data visualization. In D3, geo is one way to look at data, but not the central way. Because of this, D3 provides an integrated capability to have multiple data visualizations in an application without overloading with a ton of libraries.</p>

<p>I am already well past tl;dr on this post and I have to catch a plane. Many of the URL talks were great but I'll follow up with some more details. All-in-all, I think the event was quite a success and I'm glad I came.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Ready for JS.geo]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/08/getting-ready-for-js-dot-geo/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T15:50:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/08/getting-ready-for-js-dot-geo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm looking forward to next week's <a href="http://geojs.eventbrite.com/">JS.geo</a> event in Denver. It is a small event, spearheaded by <a href="http://twitter.com/cwhelm">Chris Helm</a> of <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a>, that focuses on the use of Javascript in geospatial applications. Although I have been more vocal in my <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/python/">recent explorations with Python</a>, I've probably done as much, if not more, work with Javascript over the past 18 months.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://mapbrief.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/no_plugin.jpg" /></div>


<p>The pace of innovation with Javascript in the geospatial area has been staggering. It seems like only a short time ago that the options for working with geospatial applications were <a href="http://openlayers.org/">OpenLayers</a> and the <a href="http://help.arcgis.com/en/webapi/javascript/arcgis/">Esri Javascript API</a>. The rapid advent of tools such as <a href="http://www.geoext.org/">GeoExt</a>, <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</a>, and many others has really lead to a explosion of capability. Of course, the recent buzz has been about <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3</a>, which tackles a wide range of data visualization problems, including geo. D3 is of particular interest because it is tackling the issue of projection in the browser, freeing applications from the dominance of Web Mercator.</p>

<p>Of course, it's not been all about the browser, either as <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> has made abundantly clear. One of the most effective desktop applications for cartographic design, <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/">TileMill</a>, is built with Node, among other tools.</p>

<p>The maturity of Javascript as a tool for geospatial development is such that I am at the point that, if it weren't for government customers that are <a href="http://mapbrief.com/2011/10/13/web-mapping-continues-to-pay-for-the-sins-of-internet-explorer/">still standardized on Internet Explorer 8</a> or older, a plug-in-based environment would not be my first choice for a new application.</p>

<p>As for the JS.geo event itself, I am intrigued by its small, focused nature. It doesn't seem to be as informal as an unconference but may be easier to digest than the typical geo event. It will also be great to catch up with the Front Range crowd.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
