<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ESRI | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/esri/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-10T09:17:36-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcWhat? I Just Want My Map.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/30/arcwhat-i-just-want-my-map/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T15:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/30/arcwhat-i-just-want-my-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>TL;DR:</h3>

<p>What follows is probably my last post related to the Esri User Conference and is highly Esri-centric. Open-source readers may want to jump off here, or exercise a willing suspension of disbelief.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/16/the-esri-uc-so-far/">A couple of posts ago</a>, I did something that I generally try to avoid. I took <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> to task for its confusing product names without really offering any thoughts on how to make things better. I don't really like it when people do that to me so I'll try to correct that here. It bears noting that I was not the only person feeling this way at the UC. I was happy to see <a href="http://www.directionsmag.com/articles/making-sense-of-the-2014-esri-international-user-conference/410201">Adena's post over at Directions</a> touch on this and it also came up in a number of conversations I had while I was in San Diego.</p>

<p>Here are some things that I think may help. They represent most of the stumbling blocks I typically encounter when doing consulting/integration with Esri-centric users, especially new ones.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/93/Spaghetti.jpg" /> <br/>
 <sub>"<a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Spaghetti.jpg#mediaviewer/File:Spaghetti.jpg">Spaghetti</a>". Licensed under <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" title="Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0<p></p>">CC BY-SA 3.0</a> via <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/">Wikimedia Commons</a>.<sub></p>

<!--more-->


<ol>
<li><p>Retire the "Arc" prefix - It's confusing to have a relatively meaningless and seemingly random (to new users) prefix attached to everying. If you are moving to a platform concept, shouldn't that platform just bear your name? The company is Esri, the platform should be "Esri GIS" or something. Don't hide from your own product line. "Arc" is a verbal stumbling block. Try telling a user how to publish a map online and see how many times you say "Arc." Is it any wonder they get confused? It's like the old dog food commercial, except all they hear is "Blah blah Arc blah Arc blah blah Arc."</p></li>
<li><p>Acknowledge four environments for the platform - Mobile, Desktop, Server, Online. Period. "Esri GIS Desktop" or "Esri GIS Server" for example. Clean up spurious products that just clutter the menu. The current Explorer? Esri GIS Mobile (resist the urge to tack on "for iOS"). The current Portal? Esri GIS Online (Online can offer a hosted or on-premise version). What's the distinction between Esri GIS Server and an on-premise instance of Esri GIS Online? I don't know. Those are your waters to unmuddy.</p></li>
<li><p>One Desktop - Basic? Standard? Advanced? How about just Desktop? After 15 or so years of selling the three tiers, you should have enough data on the sales mix to set one normalized price for a fully-functional desktop product and be done with it. I suspect that price would hover somewhere between the current prices of Basic and Standard, perhaps closer to Standard. Everybody pays one price, everybody gets the current Advanced product. If nothing else, that code base should have long since paid for itself. Then you'll be better positioned for the inevitable transition to Esri GIS Pro (which could really just be the next Esri GIS Desktop) that everyone sees coming. Need more? Buy extensions.</p></li>
<li><p>Speaking of Extensions - You can have too much of a good thing. Roll some of them into core products (like Spatial Analyst). Doing so will assure users that a common set of tools will be available as they move between the environments (see item number 2). Furthermore, stop calling everything an "extension," which exacerbates the need for cumbersome qualifiers like "for Desktop" and "for Server." Choose a standard nomenclature for each environment and stick with it. Desktop can have "extensions" and server can have "adapters," for example. Then I know that a discussion about the Network Analyst Adapter is focused on Server.</p></li>
<li><p>Stop changing product names - Take any of the suggestions above, or do something else entirely. But, whatever you do, leave it alone once you're done. At least for a couple of dot releases, anyway.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Initial Thoughts On the DC DevSummit]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/13/initial-thoughts-on-the-dc-devsummit/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T17:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/13/initial-thoughts-on-the-dc-devsummit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, I attended the first-ever <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/devsummit-dc">DC DevSummit</a> which followed the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/federal">Federal GIS Conference</a> (please switch it back to "FedUC"). This event, intended and a smaller, Federally-focused, companion to the annual Palm Springs DevSummit, came together quickly but was very well-attended with about 300 attendees.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/devsummit.jpg" /></p>

<p>It was interesting to note that the most well-attended sessions of the day had to do with Javascript (every Javascript session had over 100 participants). As more and more organizations update their IT infrastructures, the acceleration away from plug-ins seems to be picking up pace. The most common refrain amongst attendees in that regard is that continued standardization on IE8 remains the biggest impediment to sunsetting things like Flex and Silverlight, but the logjam seems to be starting to break loose.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Despite the photo I posted, <a href="http://twitter.com/ajturner">Andrew Turner's</a> open-source session was fairly well-attended. It was good to see tools like <a href="https://github.com/Esri/koop">Koop</a> in action. It is clear that there is real effort going on within Esri to produce open-source tools and that the people working on them are genuinely committed to them. That said, it is obviously still early days and such efforts are clearly swimming upstream against the preponderance of corporate culture. This is an effort that will best be judged over the long haul.</p>

<p>I also have to give a shout out to <a href="http://twitter.com/agup">Andy Gup</a>, whom I finally met at this conference. By chance, I sat through three of his sessions. He is one of the best technical presenters I have ever seen and Esri should require junior staff to sit through his sessions to see how it should be done.</p>

<p>I found the DevSummit generally worthwhile and I was impressed with how well it came together given the short timeframe. Since I was encouraged to blog suggestions, here are a few:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Make a DevSummit a permanent fixture as a follow-on to the Federal User Conference each year. The format of this year's Federal conference can be tweaked but stay mainly focused on user-centric use cases and some intro-level discussions of technologies. A DevSummit would mark a shift in to much more technical content with advanced discussions of APIs, security, techniques and best practices.</p></li>
<li><p>Pull out the stops. As I indicated in item 1, ramp up the technical content, in comparison to that of the Federal conference, significantly. This year's event started down that path. I would keep the technical content of the Federal conference on the bunny slopes and shift to the black diamonds for the DevSummit.</p></li>
<li><p>Expand to two days. It was a quick day and there were definitely sessions I would have liked to have gotten to. Additionally, it would be good to see some user content, maybe some lightning talks on the evening between the days. One of the biggest challenges working in the Federal space is the compartmentalization between and within agencies. With the DevSummit drawing interested people to one location, it would be good to get more opportunities to interact with other developers and exchange information.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.gsa.gov/portal/category/102371?utm_source=OCM&amp;utm_medium=print-radio&amp;utm_term=HP_13_SpecialTopics_fedramp&amp;utm_campaign=shortcuts">FedRAMP</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Information_Security_Management_Act_of_2002">FISMA</a> were non-existent this year. Jim Barry explained to me that these were areas where content simply wasn't ready to go in the short time given to prepare for the DevSummit. That's fair, and I certainly respect the decision to not provide content that could not be done well. These are, however, core issues for anyone doing development for the Federal Government. Next year's DC DevSummit really needs to have content for developers attempting to deploy to FedRAMP and achieve FISMA compliance with Esri tools.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Those my quick hits. I'll probably have more after I have time to digest what I saw and dig out from the backlog resulting from two days out of the office. Kudos to <a href="http://twitter.com/jimbarry">Jim Barry</a> for his work pulling the DC DevSummit together.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meanwhile, Over at Zekiah...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/06/meanwhile/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T11:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/06/meanwhile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't usually cross-pollinate between this, my personal blog, and the company blog over at <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a>. One of the great things about working at a place like Zekiah, however, is the opportunity to work with smart people and see what they are doing. At times, my colleagues will share components of their work on the company blog. We encourage this, and the experimentation that leads to the posts, as a way to keep our technical capabilities fresh and to also showcase what we do in a way that goes beyond the typical capabilities statements that exist on every site. My colleagues have been pretty busy but have managed to take some time to write a few posts about their work:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/02/04/esri-cityengine-unity-40-and-oculus-rift">Esri CityEngine, Unity 4.0 and the Oculus Rift</a> - My colleague, <a href="http://twitter.com/DanEntzian">Dan Entzian</a>, is an avid gamer, a great developer, and a smart GIS guy. This post combines those interests by showing how to bring cities created in Esri's <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/cityengine/">CityEngine</a> into gaming environments like <a href="http://unity3d.com/">Unity</a> and integrate them with the <a href="http://www.oculusvr.com/">Oculus Rift</a> virtual reality display. It's a quick, but detailed, read that shows the interactions possible between geospatial tools and games.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/unity_ide.png" /></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/01/23/using-awk-ease-your-csv-manipulation">Using AWK to ease your CSV manipulation</a> - <a href="http://twitter.com/hugoestr">Hugo Estrada</a> shows how to use an old, but still effective, tool, <a href="http://www.grymoire.com/Unix/Awk.html">AWK</a>, to process GPS data for use in GIS software. This post is a great reminder that the best tool for the job may already be sitting there at our command prompt waiting for us.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2013/12/18/exporting-esri-silverlight-graphic-layer-google-earth-part-2">Exporting ESRI Silverlight Graphic Layer to Google Earth, Part 2</a> - While Silverlight is, politely speaking, passe, we have a few customers that are still attached to it. Generally, the systems that are using it are accredited systems of record so a rip-and-replace of Silverlight (or any other component) is simply not feasible without a significant paperwork drill. So we try to help our customers keep those systems as useful for their end users as possible. This post, also by Dan Entzian, illustrates how we did that in one case. A follow up to <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2011/10/11/exporting-esri-silverlight-graphic-layer-google-earth">an older post</a>, this post was done in response to an e-mail inquiry from a reader of the previous post.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2013/12/17/overview-clojure">An Overview of Clojure</a> - In this post, Hugo Estrada takes a look a <a href="http://clojure.org/">Clojure</a>, a variant of the Lisp programming language, and reports on his experience at Clojure Con. I found this particularly interesting since, as a lifelong programmer, I am always interested in new languages (even if it is getting harder to find the time to tinker with them myself).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/01/02/generating-physical-schemas-pim">Generating Physical Schemas From a PIM</a> - Okay, this one was written by me, but the work is pretty interesting and involved the efforts of a few co-workers, including Barry Schimpf and Dan Entzian. This post describes a tool that we developed as part of our overall approach to geospatial data model management. This script generator produces SQL scripts for either <a href="http://postgis.net/">PostGIS</a> or <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/">SpatiaLite</a> that enable a user to create spatial databases that are compliant with a data model. The information for the data model (which is always user-defined, not proscribed by us) is stored in what we call the platform independent model, or <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim">PIM</a>. We've used the PIM, its encapsulating API, and tools to good effect for a couple of customers now. This post attempts to provide a concrete picture of what can be an abstract concept.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Since Zekiah is a services company, rather than a platform company, we get to work with a broad range of technologies in support of our customers, in addition to our own internal research. This makes each day pretty interesting and can also make for lively conversation at company events. As the posts above showcase, my colleagues are working on some interesting things and it's a pleasure to work them each day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[File Geodatabase Schema Compare Tool]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/01/08/file-geodatabase-compare-tool/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T20:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/01/08/file-geodatabase-compare-tool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my work supporting various aspects of geospatial data modeling, I've spent a lot of time delving into concepts around configuration management of such data models. We've been able to apply a core tool set to perform various functions such as version managment, profiling, version-to-version migration, and validation in conjunction with a system we call the platform independent model (PIM). I gave quick overview of the PIM <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2014/01/02/generating-physical-schemas-pim">in this post over on the Zekiah blog</a> and the complete series on it <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim">can be found here</a>.</p>

<p>I've recently spent a bit of time consolidating code after a recent data delivery and decided to post a utility that was an outgrowth of that effort: <a href="https://github.com/Zekiah/ArcGISCompare">a tool to compare schemas of two Esri file geodatabases and report differences</a>. This lent itself to general use because it does not require any connection to a PIM.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="https://github.com/Zekiah/ArcGISCompare/raw/master/screenshot.png" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>The PIM deals mainly at the logical level with data models, but a full configuration management workflow must occasionally touch physical data sets. One use case we had to support, for which this tool was built, was the case where users in the field must compare separate data sets for eventual integration. Although these workflows start with a template data set, it is not unusal for changes to be made during collection, resulting in very similar but not identical schemas. This tool helps users identify such differences in order to make configuration management decisions based upon the actual state of the collected data.</p>

<p>The tool is fairly straightforward: choose a template data set, choose an implementation data set, run the compare, and examine the results. It contains ArcObjects dependencies although we may migrate it to the file geodatabase API in order to eliminate those.</p>

<p>We are also in the process of building a similar tool to work with SQLite/SpatiaLite data sets, which is the other format we commonly see used and will post that tool when it is complete. In the meantime, I hope you find this application useful.</p>

<p>An installer (10.1) <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6749645/PIM/setup_ArcGISCompare.zip">can be found here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DC DevSummit In Works for 2014 Esri Federal GIS Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/12/27/dc-devsummit-in-works-for-2014-esri-federal-gis-conference/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T13:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/12/27/dc-devsummit-in-works-for-2014-esri-federal-gis-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I got word today that <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> is planning a one-day [Developer Summit] in conjunction with the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/federal/">2014 Federal GIS Conference</a>. It appears that the DevSummit will happen on the Wednesday immediately following the Fed Conference (which runs on the Monday and Tuesday) and will be focused on the issues and challenges that are unique to developing applications with Esri technologies for the Federal Government. I spoke with <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/jdbarry">Jim Barry</a>, who told me the DevSummit has come together rather quickly and Esri hasn't had time to do its usual data gathering to prepare for such an event. As a result, they are canvassing the developer community for input on topics they should cover. Here are some things I suggested:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li><p>Developing for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Information_Security_Management_Act_of_2002">FISMA</a> compliance - FISMA compliance has to be baked into an application from the beginning. It would be great to see some content on best practices and resources available to support this when developing with Esri tools and APIs. Esri's regional office in Vienna, Virginia has been doing a lot of work in this area but I'm not sure the information is widespread.</p></li>
<li><p>Desktop development - I still see <em>a lot</em> of ArcGIS desktop development in the Federal arena. This ranges from traditional ArcObjects extensions to add-ins to work with the File Geodatabase API. I think content related to how to do continued desktop development and support in light of the current realities of highly constrained desktop environments would be invaluable. For example, how to construct and deploy applications that don't necessarily need to touch the registry and can be deployed without administrative rights. Also, some content on the future of Esri desktop products (like <a href="http://video.esri.com/watch/2533/unveiling-the-new-arcgis-professional-application-with-jim-mckinney-and-jack-dangermond">ArcGIS Professional</a>) and what it means for application developers would be useful.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/code.png" style="float:left;margin: 5px 25px 5px 0px;" /></p>

<ul>
<li><p>.Net - There's still a lot of .Net development going on in Federal spaces. Most of my Federal customers are still primarily using .Net and you can peruse Federal geospatial RFPs on any given day and see that it is widespread. I'm fairly comfortable with .Net, as are most of the government and contractor developers I work with but it would be good to have some .Net-focused content alongside the newer, sexier platforms.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.arcgis.com/features/">ArcGIS Online for Organizations</a> - Whatever messaging Esri thinks they are doing is not working very well. I encounter a great many Federal users who simply don't understand what it can do for them, why they would consider it, how to budget for it, or whether they can really use it. My understanding is the main Federal GIS Conference will be talking about these issues a lot so I think the DevSummit should focus on the <a href="https://developers.arcgis.com/en/">tools and APIs</a> that are available so that developers can begin to address the ideas the main conference attendees will come back with.</p></li>
<li><p>Data interoperability - I have spent a lot of time over the past year developing tools to support data modeling and configuration management efforts for some Federal users. Part of this work has involved developing tools to produce physical implementations of approved geospatial data models in a number of formats, though the formats that have been of primary interest with my customers have been the Esri File Geodatabase and <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/">SpatiaLite</a>. The general workflows I have seen involve users working with Esri geodatabase formats in the office, while ingesting field-collected data in SpatiaLite format. All of this data needs to remain compliant with approved data models throughout the life cycle, regardless of format. <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim">We've been tackling that</a> at <a href="http://www.esri.com">Zekiah</a> with good success. Given the support of SQLite/SpatiaLite in ArcGIS 10.2, I'd like to see some discussion of data conversion/interoperability approaches that developers can automate with Esri tools.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Those are some topics I suggested to Jim off the top of my head. I'll probably think of more. Jim and his team at Esri are actively seeking this sort of input since time is short so I'd suggest <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/jdbarry">contacting him</a> with your thoughts. Given the short timeframe, I'd expect official information from Esri very soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
