<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Esri | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/esri/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-25T13:52:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Esri UC So Far #EsriUC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/16/the-esri-uc-so-far/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T12:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/16/the-esri-uc-so-far</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I'm halfway through the largest geospatial event of the year, attending it for the first time in four years, and I haven't blogged yet. As always, it's a busy week. Because this event draws people from all over the country (and world), my dance card fills up pretty quickly. And, by the way, there's a conference going on.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/plenary_stage.jpg" /></p>

<p>This is the first I've ever attended the Esri User Conference as just an attendee. If it were a video game, I'd be playing it on the easy level. I sat through the entire plenary for the first time in years. It was nice table setting for the rest of the week. As the father of a dancer, I have developed an eye for choreography and there is plenty of it up on the plenary stage. If I were to level one piece of constructive criticism toward the UC, it's that I'd let speakers be themselves a little bit more. That said, the content was delivered smoothly, which is really the larger point.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The plenary features a lot of demos that are rehearsed to within an inch of their lives. Knowing that, I still found ArcGIS Pro to be interesting. The UI is well-designed to get out the user's way and it's native 64-bit architecture finally allows it to take advantage of system resources in a way that ArcMap never could. The UI is more modern, featuring the ribbon toolbar. Esri seems to have learned a lesson from Microsoft by not re-engineering the UI of a familiar product, but releasing a new product that users can transition to. That was smart. In Microsoft Office terms, the UI upates from the Office 97 feel of ArcMap to more of an Office 2012 feel. Tasks in ArcGIS simplify geoprocessing even more but also run the risk of hiding complexity too much. I hope we're not training another generation of button-clickers.</p>

<p>One of the more subtle announcements in the plenary was that ArcGIS Portal will be included with ArcGIS Server at 10.3. I suspect that's the beginning of a gentle nudge of Server into ArcIMS-like oblivion but that's just my speculation.</p>

<p>The newly-released (not beta) ArcGIS Open Data extension (product?) was shown by <a href="http://twitter.com/ajturner">Andrew Turner</a>. It does a very nice job of putting an almost-GeoCommons-easy interface in front of ArcGIS Online to enable organizations to easily share their data. Andrew showed the implementations for the DC government and the State of Maryland. Maryland, in particular, is exceedingly happy with how quickly it has helped them start sharing data. By chance, I had dinner with some of the development team the night before and it's a motivated team with a diverse skill set not rooted in traditional Esri thinking which, in my opinion, bodes well for what they are doing.</p>

<p>Yesterday, I sat through a couple of sessions on the GeoEvent Processor (GEP), which has already been rebranded as the GeoEvent Extension for Server (or something like that). Those who have tracked my blog over the years know that I've done a lot of work with situational awareness systems. Within that field, I've concentrated a lot on feeds (streaming data sources) and track management so it's something of a geeky passion for me. Esri's previous, long-standing, and wholly awful product in this space was Tracking Server. I would gleefully dance around Tracking Server's funeral pyre.</p>

<p>GEP seems to be a better attempt at solving this problem. In its current incarnation, it simply doesn't have the throughput my customers will need (it currently supports about 800 - 1000 messages per second). To the product team's credit, they know this and are focusing on it. At 10.3, GEP will support "clustering" to increase throughtput. Clustering, however, was not explained during the session and could mean anything so I'll wait and see. The management interfaces and APIs behind GEP are top-notch and enable some of the use cases I've supported in the past. Once the throughput challenges are solved, this could be a product to watch.</p>

<p>You may have noticed a few parenthetical comments above when referring to product names. The reason for that is that Esri's product naming has fallen off the cliff to become just confusing, unwieldy, and random. Couple that with the fact that product names change constantly, or are recycled endlessly (Explorer?), and it's a complete mess. It's always been difficult walking new users through the maze of Esri products and the current naming "convention" doesn't help at all. Esri really needs to circle the wagons on this and simplify things.</p>

<p>That sums up my week so far. I'll try to check in again before I go.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gearing Up For the Esri UC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/09/gearing-up-for-the-esri-uc/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-09T16:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/09/gearing-up-for-the-esri-uc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With a house move behind us and a lot of unpacking and other tasks ahead, I am nonetheless getting ready to head out to the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/user-conference">Esri International User Conference</a> next week. This will be my first time attending since 2010 and is the first UC since then that has aligned with my schedule in a way that I can make it. Of course, the price is right this year as well ($0.00).</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/office_view.png" /></p>

<p>The "big" UC has steadily dropped in significance for me over years as it has become much easier to get Esri-related information through various other channels; primarily through social media and local/regional events such as the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/federal">FedUC</a> and local dev meetups. The last few trips to San Diego left me feeling that the content presented there is getting increasingly superficial compared to the other events. This year, however, I have been in the midst of building a house and moving so I have not had the time to attend the smaller events. As a result the UC makes sense. I am hoping the recent trend reverses itself.</p>

<p>I still do some Esri-based consulting so it's important to stay current however I can. My government customers are starting to at least ask about ArcGIS Online, so I want to finally get my mind around it as best I can. The messaging around that platform has been so muddled that it's still difficult for me to articulate what productivity advantages, if any, it actually offers. My own experimentation with it has left me wanting. The fact that it has been <a href="http://www.executivegov.com/2014/06/agriculture-dept-grants-fisma-certification-to-esri-cloud-mapping-tech/">certified as FISMA compliant</a> will certainly raise its profile with some of my Federal customers, though that's typically only the first step in a very long process. I'm also curious about ArcGIS Pro.</p>

<p>Unlike previous years, I won't be manning a booth (we sold ours a few years ago) or directly representing a customer so I'll actually have the luxury to attend sessions and meet up with people. There are some people who, unfortunately, I really only see face-to-face at such large magnet events so I'm looking forward to catching up with them, as well as meeting new people. I will, however, be popping into the paper session of one of my co-workers. (It would be awesome if the online agenda provided permalinks to individual sessions.)</p>

<p>So, if you're going to be in at the UC next week and would like to meet up, feel free to ping me on Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/billdollins">@billdollins</a>), via e-mail (bill [at] geomusings [dot] com), or drop a comment below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Esri Federal GIS Conference Features Immersion Summits]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/05/esri-federal-gis-conference-features-immersion-summits/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-05T20:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/02/05/esri-federal-gis-conference-features-immersion-summits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The 2014 installment of the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/federal">Esri Federal GIS Conference</a> (formerly known as the Federal User Conference) happens next week. I have attended the event off and on since its inception. While I originally was drawn by the presence of a large geo-related event in my local area, that gap has been filled by numerous, smaller events from various sources in the past few years. The FedUC has traditionally had something of an identity crisis, with the content often feeling a bit diffuse and somewhat rushed over its quick, two-day schedule.</p>

<p>To Esri's credit, and probably in recognition of the changing economics regarding travel for Federal employees, they have continued to fine-tune the event when they could have easily walked away from it. The main problem with the FedUC is the fact that the Federal Government performs a wide array of functions that are difficult to cover well over two days in a conventional format. Esri has tackled that problem this year with the introduction of <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/federal/agenda/immersion-summits">"immersion summits,"</a> which are three-and-a-half hour sessions dedicated to specific domain areas.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>For example, check out the Natural Resources Immersion Summit led by my friend <a href="http://twitter.com/jsteffenson">John Steffenson</a>. The agenda features speakers from USDA, USGS, the US Forest Service, the EPA, the Fish and Wildlife Service, and Department of Interior, representing over 100 years of higher education dedicated to natural resources management. The session also has slots for several demos of systems deployed in natual resources domain.</p>

<p>The session's content seems to be designed take a holistic view, including fiscal, logistical, technical, and demographic challenges among others. This type of deep focus is an intriguing change to event's focus. While nautral resources is not my usual domain, I do like to drop into other sessions as I find that uses cases from other domains can give me ideas to bring back to my work. I think this new format could maximize the use of the compact schedule of the Federal GIS Conference and begin to give the event its own identity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite and ArcGIS 10.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/08/07/spatialite-and-arcgis-10-dot-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T12:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/08/07/spatialite-and-arcgis-10-dot-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the release of ArcGIS 10.2, <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> quietly added support for <a href="https://sqlite.org/">SQLite</a> as a geodatabase container. This is big news as the community has been looking for such support for some time. An open-source RDBMS originally designed for embedded systems, SQLite has a very small footprint and is <a href="https://www.sqlite.org/mostdeployed.html">arguably the most widely deployed RDBMS</a> in the world. (Thanks, in part, to the fact that it is embedded into Adobe Reader and other commonly used software.) Over the years numerous strategies for storing spatial data in SQLite have been developed, ranging from simply storing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Well-known_text">WKT or WKB</a> geometries in a column up to full extensions like <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/">SpatiaLite</a>, which adds OGC-compliant data types and methods. SQLite is also the engine that drives the popular <a href="http://www.mapbox.com/developers/mbtiles/">MBTiles</a> implementation used by <a href="http://www.mapbox.com/tilemill/">TileMill</a> and <a href="http://www.mapbox.com">MapBox</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://resources.arcgis.com/en/help/main/10.2/index.html#//019v0000001w000000">According to the documentation</a>, ArcGIS supports the use of either Esri's ST_GEOMETRY or SpatiaLite data types for geometry storage. This is consistent with Esri's approach on other RDBMS platforms such as <a href="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</a> and <a href="http://www.oracle.com">Oracle</a>. While SpatiaLite has been supported by platforms such as <a href="http://qgis.org/">QGIS</a>, I can't say I've seen a huge demand for data in SpatiaLite format. I have been using it for a while in some of <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">my company's</a> data modeling work as we have a Federal customer that has a documented requirement for generation of physical models in SpatiaLite, among other platforms. We have also taken the step of supporting SQLite as a container for our <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim">platform independent model (PIM) approach</a> for configuration management of logical geospatial data models.</p>

<p>Esri's new support of SpatiaLite, combined with my existing customer requirements, obviously sparked my interest so I was curious to kick the tires. Unfortunately, I also had the situation that my development environment for the PIM tools, due to current customer constraints, must remain at ArcGIS 10.1 for both the desktop software and the underlying ArcObjects libraries. I have not been able to carve out the time to build a 10.2 VM.</p>

<p>Luckily, others were also interested in the new SpatiaLite support so <a href="http://twitter.com/brymcbride">Bryan McBride</a>, "<a href="http://twitter.com/fathersandman">Father Sandman</a>," and I were able to crowdsource some very cursory compatibility tests via Twitter. The full tweet stream can be accessed by clicking the date in the tweet below.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/billdollins">@billdollins</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/FatherSandman">@FatherSandman</a> Score! Looks like we&#39;ve confirmed ArcGIS 10.2, QGIS 1.9.0, and SpatiaLite-GUI 1.7.1 are compatible.</p>&mdash; Bryan McBride (@brymcbride) <a href="https://twitter.com/brymcbride/statuses/365103999671738369">August 7, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>So, using Father Sandman's existing 10.2 install, we were able to verify the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>A SpatiaLite database created in ArcGIS 10.2 can be accessed and viewed in QGIS 1.9.0 and SpatiaLite GUI 1.7.1</li>
<li>A SpatiaLite database created in QGIS 1.9.0 can be accessed in ArcGIS 10.2</li>
</ol>


<p>Obviously, some more rigorous tests need to be performed but the initial results are promising. I'm curious to explore the boundaries, in ArcGIS terms, between a SQLite geodatabase and a file geodatabase. It remains to be seen whether this will put a dent in the use of file geodatabases. If it happens at all, I think it will take time since SQLite is not on the radar of the vast majority of ArcGIS users. I would hope, at a minimum, it puts a final stake through the heart of the personal geodatabase. It could also drive explicit accreditation of SQLite/SpatiaLite tools on government systems, which would be nice.</p>

<p>I'm happy, and somewhat pleasantly surprised, to see Esri take this step and provide another open option for data exchange.</p>

<p>Now, about GeoJSON...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
