<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ESRI | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/esri/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-28T07:05:56-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc2Earth: Choose Your 'Cloud']]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/02/28/arc2earth-choose-your-cloud/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-28T06:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/02/28/arc2earth-choose-your-cloud</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For various reasons, I can't attend today's inaugural <a href="http://fedgeoday.com/">FedGeoDay</a> at the Woolly Mammoth Theatre in Washington, DC, though I'll be watching the hashtag with great interest. Jack Flood of <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/">Arc2Earth</a>, however, has already posted his slides to SlideShare:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/16811994" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jflood3/fedgeodays-022013" title="Fedgeodays 022013" target="_blank">Fedgeodays 022013</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jflood3" target="_blank">Jack Flood</a></strong> </div></p>

<!--more-->


<p>While neither <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcMap</a> nor Arc2Earth are open-source themselves, Jack points out that Arc2Earth acts as a bridge between ArcMap and several geospatial hosting platforms that are built on open-source technology but, also just as important, are successful at making data more openly available. These platforms include <a href="http://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> and <a href="http://mapbox.com/">MapBox</a>, among many others.</p>

<p>Many people use, and prefer, ArcMap has their desktop cartography and analysis tool. I view Arc2Earth as an enabling technology that allows users to continue to be productive with ArcMap while also allowing them to retain control of how they direct their GIS investments in terms of publishing and hosting their maps and data.</p>

<p>Disclaimer: <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">My company</a> is an Arc2Earth reseller.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GeoIQ & Esri]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/10/geoiq-esri/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/10/geoiq-esri</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, everybody calm the hell down. Anyone who thinks that the <a href="http://blog.geoiq.com/2012/07/10/building-from-the-inside/" target="_blank">Esri acquisition of GeoIQ</a> is strange hasn't been paying attention to two things: 1) the direction that Esri says they want to go and 2) what the GeoIQ platform really is. I would be very surprised if GeoIQ becomes the 2012 version of <a href="http://www.thefreelibrary.com/ESRI+Acquires+Atlas+GIS+and+Atlas+SDK+--+Claritas+and+ESRI+Announce...-a018336428" target="_blank">Atlas GIS</a>. This acquisition/merger makes more sense than may be initially apparent.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/_eyFiClAzq8?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>It's no secret that I've worked with <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> tools for a long time and my recent work with the <a href="http://www.geoiq.com" target="_blank">GeoIQ</a> platform has been well-documented on this blog, including work integrating the two platforms at the API level. Based on what I've seen from both companies, here are thoughts on why I think this move makes a lot of sense:  <!--more--></p>

<p><strong>First, why it makes sense for Esri...</strong></p>

<p>GeoIQ/<a href="http://www.geocommons.com" target="_blank">GeoCommons</a> is, and has been for a long time, what <a href="http://www.arcgis.com/home/" target="_blank">ArcGIS Online</a> (AGOL) should be and still isn't. It was built from the beginning as a hosted platform without any encumbrances of an existing technology/code base. It is stable, staying online throughout many recent incidents, in a way that AGOL can't claim. The back-end data storage architecture, developed on a "NoSQL" platform and designed by GeoIQ, is already much more scalable than anything coming from a geodatabase legacy.</p>

<p>Esri made their mark in client/server (there's an oldie) GIS and have not been able to successfully move past it to this day. You can move ArcGIS to Amazon if you want but it's still client/server. If you pull back and think about it, the least logical thing you can do when trying to build a SaaS is to try and port an architecture that was designed for desktops and servers. GeoIQ, on the other hand, never designed for those platforms. Their SaaS was built to be a hosted system, accessible via an API. That approach has enabled them to expand from data storage to cartographics/visualization to analytics smoothly and consistently.</p>

<p>The API is key here. The GeoIQ platform is exposed via a "RESTish" <a href="http://developer.geoiq.com/api/rest-api/" target="_blank">HTTP+JSON API</a>. If you examine the API documentation with an eye toward bridging to the Esri <a href="http://www.esri.com/news/releases/10_3qtr/geoservices-rest.html" target="_blank">GeoServices REST Specification</a> (which I have), it doesn't take long to get from GeoIQ's overlays, maps and analytics to Esri's map services, feature services and server extensions. Resource hierarchies are a little different and, of course, JSON syntax is different but none of those are insurmountable hurdles. In fact, it would be no more difficult to make GeoIQ emit Esri JSON than it would be to make the Esri REST API emit <a href="http://www.geojson.org" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>.</p>

<p>Based on my previous analyses, I don't think putting a GeoServices REST implementation on top of GeoIQ would be the most technically challenging thing in the world. And given the existence of the <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/projects/groups/gservrestswg" target="_blank">OGC GeoService REST SWG</a>, doing so may eventually get you in line for standards compliance. (I'll leave the rest of you to debate the value of that.) But, aside from potential standards compliance, the biggest reason to do so would be to enable all of the existing Esri client tools that already know how to interact with the Esri REST API to be able to talk to the GeoIQ platform.</p>

<p>So let's summarize: In a hosted world, the back-end implementation doesn't really matter much because client tools talk through an API. If I'm using HTTP to communicate, I don't care if it's COM or Java or Ruby or whatever on the back end. That's why APIs are valuable and those built to use standards like HTTP are even more so. GeoIQ has an in-place, highly-scalable, spatial storage/visualization/analytics platform that's exposed through an HTTP interface. Bolt on another interface, and you have ArcGIS Online. There's some work involved but not nearly as much as building the platform from scratch.</p>

<p>So, if Esri is smart, the GeoIQ platform becomes ArcGIS Online. They'd need to work on improving the tools to pass data between the hosted platform and the client/server platform, and maybe tighter integration with the desktop tools to ease publishing. It would probably be good to beef up symbology in GeoIQ as this is one thing that Esri currently does better, more easily, than GeoIQ. Also the analytical tools in place with GeoIQ are already win over AGOL.</p>

<p><strong>Why it makes sense for GeoIQ...</strong></p>

<p>So I've done a good bit of work with the GeoIQ platform and APIs. Probably not enough to call myself an expert but enough to feel comfortable. I've worked on a couple of successful implementations, including the <a href="http://blog.geoiq.com/2012/04/27/visualizing-our-changing-climate-with-climascope/" target="_blank">ClimaScope portal recently mentioned on the GeoIQ blog</a> and am currently in the middle of another one. I have found the platform to be impressive, with the potential for a great amount of productivity.</p>

<p>A couple of years ago, I had the good fortune to attend the FortiusOne holiday party (they weren't yet called GeoIQ). One thing that struck me about that evening was the dedication and passion that every single employee seemed to have for what they were doing. Everyone was committed to building the best tools they possibly could. I got the sense that if someone were tasked with building a CSV exporter, they would make sure it was the best CSV exporter anyone had ever seen. I came away from that experience a believer.</p>

<p>Over the ensuing time working with the GeoIQ platform, I have noticed small anomalies here and there: documentation that's not quite up to date, small bugs, longer response times, etc. These types of issues are not uncommon but are somewhat out of character for an organization with a high level of dedication and enthusiasm.</p>

<p>That said, my role as a business owner has given me an interest in things such as acquisition drivers. What I have come to realize is that the small issues I was observing are not uncommon for a small company that has achieved a certain level of growth but has plateaued. In other words, growing pains. The reasons small companies plateau are varied but getting past a plateau can be difficult and may require additional resources that are difficult to muster internally. This can lead small companies to seek acquisition.</p>

<p>GeoIQ has always been very dedicated to how their technology is applied. They have a noticeable footprint in the DoD world and have had high-profile implementations such as the World Bank, World Wildlife Fund and others on the NGO side of things. Not coincidentally, these are areas in which Esri is active. In short, there has probably always been more in common between Esri and GeoIQ than met the eye. GeoIQ now has access to the resources of a larger company than help mitigate their growing pains and help them more effectively focus on the application areas they care about.</p>

<p>In my opinion, this acquisition not only makes sense, it is somewhat classic. In hindsight, it could even be called obvious. I could go on about this but I won't.</p>

<p>Many in our industry, myself included, took a vicarious enjoyment in the David-versus-Goliath interplay between GeoIQ and Esri but now it's time for us to get back to work. I think all of the principals involved in this transaction deserve credit for keeping open minds and being able to look past all of that to recognize the potential common benefits of joining forces. I sincerely hope GeoIQ doesn't become the next Atlas GIS and I suspect it won't.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AGIO Puts the Data First]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/24/agio-puts-the-data-first/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/24/agio-puts-the-data-first</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I read <a href="http://www.gisuser.com/content/view/23022/222/">Learon Dalby's latest GISuser.com expert column</a> (disclosure: I am a contributor there also) with great interest since it addresses an issue with which I have worked closely over the years: availability of GIS data in a time of crisis. Over the years, the proliferation of "operating pictures" (you're not in style unless you have your own <a href="http://www.mitre.org/work/tech_papers/tech_papers_07/07_0093/">UDOP</a>) and other systems has obscured the fact that the data is really what matters. Certain segments of the community, especially those more focused on man-made disasters rather than the natural variety, have gotten very good at putting multiple layers of technology, services, security, policy, etc. between GIS data and the people who need it. <!--more--></p>

<p>The problem with with all of this is that these systems tend to be very fragile under stress (exactly the kinds of stress that one can expect during an actual crisis). To mitigate that, we add scalability, complexity and cost to build out large, highly-available systems to serve out a small amount of data.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="" height="278" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/buffet.png" title="Is it this easy to get to your GIS data?" width="416" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Is it this easy to get to your GIS data?<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>As Learon and Arkansas demonstrate, there is another approach and it is simply making GIS data as open and <em>directly</em> available as possible. This isn't always sexy (Shapefiles via FTP?!?!) but can be effective. Additionally, it touches upon <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/09/16/be-the-crowd/">an issue I raised last year</a>. Some of the best GIS data in existence is that which is created and maintained at the local government level (one might even call it "authoritative"), but that data is not always available. Arkansas is very realistic when they say that people most likely won't look to their GIS servers first and so they try to push that data to the places people will go to look (<a href="http://maps.google.com">Google</a>, <a href="http://www.bing.com/maps/">Bing</a>, <a href="http://geocommons.com/search?model=&amp;query=AGIO">GeoCommons</a>, <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a>, <a href="http://www.mapquest.com/">MapQuest</a>) in formats that are the most universally accessible (shapefiles, KML, ATOM).</p>

<p>This is a low-level, and somewhat low-tech, form of data sharing and interoperability but, in a time of extended economic stress, Arkansas' GIS data is available and up-to-date. They have made the hurdles to get that data as low as possible and, in so doing, have raised the bar higher when judging data openness and availability.</p>

<p>Put that in your COP and view it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ten-Second Tidy]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/12/10/ten-second-tidy/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/12/10/ten-second-tidy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things have been a bit hectic the last few weeks and that's left little time for blogging. Quite a bit has happened so I thought I'd do a little round-up (if for no other reason than to clear my own head).</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/cJa7P6dfmco?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>In no particular order:</p>

<p><strong>Steve Coast to Microsoft</strong> (I told you it had been a while) - Firstly, congratulations to Steve (#sincerity).  Secondly, this clearly is the final proof that crowd-sourced data in general, and OpenStreetMaps (sic) in particular, <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/09/16/be-the-crowd/">has no real value when compared to "authoritative" data sources</a> (#sarcasm).</p>

<p><strong>Google Fusion Tables</strong> - The only real problem at this point is the size limitation but, otherwise, this will be a game-changer for storing and sharing data. In its current form, it's already fairly easy to push your data up and expose it through Google's APIs. It'll be interesting to see if it gets easier. Support for spatial queries hints at some analytical capability, too. Speaking of which...</p>

<p><strong>Analytics in GeoCommons</strong> - This is one to watch. They are debuting a new function each day <a href="http://blog.fortiusone.com/2010/12/06/the-12-analytics-of-christmas/">on their blog</a>. FortiusOne builds their platform API-first, UI-second so everything they are showing should be exposed through their APIs. This will be a huge step in moving cloud-based geospatial technology from the "bit-bucket" stage to having a more complete workflow on the cloud infrastructure.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Arc2Earth Data Services and Arc2Cloud</strong> - Continuing the theme of building a complete workflow, <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> is working on exposing a <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/services/data-services/">complete range of Google geospatial services</a> to ArcGIS Desktop users. It's no secret that I'm a fan of Arc2Earth (and <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">my company</a> is a reseller), but this represents a big expansion of capability. Google's cloud infrastructure works differently that Amazon's and I think what <a href="http://beta.arc2cloud.com/">Arc2Earth is doing</a> is important because it will open up another channel for users and enable them to <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/clouds/">make choices based on their needs and requirements</a>.</p>

<p><strong>WeoGeo</strong> - <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">These guys</a> never sit still either. They've got some changes coming up that will greatly increase flexibility for managing spatial data on a cloud infrastructure. Taken together with the previous two entries on GeoCommons and Arc2Earth, I see a lot of innovation in cloud-based GIS really being driven by small, focused companies. This is not simply "push your server to an AMI and keep working." (Although that approach can have some utility.) Each of these companies is trying to figure out how to leverage the unique capabilities of cloud infrastructures to build new workflows and expand capability for users. And, it's important to note, they are making headway.</p>

<p><strong>WhereCampDC</strong> - Obviously, judging from the <a href="http://wherecampdc.org/">web site</a>, it's still in the early planning stages but I'm excited by the idea. This is exactly the kind of independent event that this area needs. I have always been baffled by the lack of such events in this area, especially given the level of geospatial activity around here.</p>

<p><strong>Google Earth 6</strong> - The <a href="http://www.google.com/earth/index.html">latest release</a> confirms that StreetView has yet to drive my street. For that I am happy.</p>

<p><strong>FOSS4G</strong> - The conference doesn't happen until next September and already the buzz is building. I have had people that I know have yet to touch an open-source GIS tool ask me what I know about "that <a href="http://foss4g.org/static/index.html">conference</a> I'm hearing about in Denver."</p>

<p><strong>Silverlight</strong> - I can't think of a technology in recent years that has given me more of a feeling of ambivalence. It has great capability and the Esri Silverlight API team has done good work building on it (this piece addresses Silverlight, not the Esri API). I think it'll continue to be a fine technology for intranet development but I'll leave it there. I don't expect my work with it to wind down anytime soon so I'll keep blogging it as I think it's perfectly possible to be productive with Silverlight within certain parameters. <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/10/30/rip-silverlight-on-the-web/">The whole episode regarding its future</a> (which was something of a tempest in a teapot, in reality) simply highlights the risks involved in relying on closed, proprietary technologies. This time, it was Silverlight, but make no mistake, the same risks are there with Flex/Flash (it just runs on more browser/OS combinations). Of course, there are risks with <em>any</em> technology choice but it's nice when those risks do not include "whim."</p>

<p>So that's it for my odds and ends. It's good to get them stuffed back into the couch. 2010 has been an interesting year. It almost feels like a year in which groundwork is being laid. It may just be me, but I have a feeling of anticipation similar to what I feel right before the first daffodils appear in Spring. It just feels like there's a good bit of pent-up energy and that a lot of new things are about to spring forth. It could be loads of fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
