<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Vizzulaity | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/vizzulaity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:36:14-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FOSS4G Quick Hits]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/09/19/FOSS4G-Quick-Hits/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/09/19/FOSS4G-Quick-Hits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had the distinct pleasure of attending my first <a href="http://2011.foss4g.org">FOSS4G conference in Denver</a> last week. Having not attended one previously, I can only rely on the opinions of others that this has been the best FOSS4G yet. For me, this was best geospatial conference I have attended. I'll probably blog in more detail about some of the things I saw but here are my high-level observations:</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="" height="266" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/09/rotary_sign3.jpg" title="rotary_sign3" width="300" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">It&#039;s time to refresh your thinking about open-source geospatial tools.<br/><br/></div></div>




<!--more-->


<ol>
<li><p><a href="http://www.qgis.org/">QGIS</a> - I didn't attend many QGIS sessions but I didn't need to. It had everyone talking in hallways during breaks. Remember a few years ago when the desktop was the weak link with open-source GIS? Forget about that.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.vizzuality.com/">Vizzuality</a> is doing great things to deploy usable mapping applications on the web with open-source tools. Every session   they led was standing-room only, with good reason.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://vizzuality.com/cartoset">CartoSet</a> and <a href="https://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> - from the aforementioned Vizzuality. These open-source tools are designed to help speed the front-end and back-end development of a web application respectively. These are at the top of my list of things to check out.</p></li>
<li><p>One of the key characteristics of most of the open-source tools discussed in sessions I attended is that they originally grew out of the need to solve a problem. They were not just built on spec, hoping someone would find them useful. As a result, these tools tend to already be proven within the problem set for which they were built.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://postgis.refractions.net/">PostGIS</a> - If open-source geospatial is a flowering field, then PostGIS is the water that hydrates it. The amount of tools that support it is staggering (including CartoDB). The importance of a robust, open-source, spatial data store cannot be overstated and the role PostGIS plays as a foundation technology is pivotal. As for PostGIS 2.0, Michael Weisman sums it up best here:</p></li>
</ol>


<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>My second takeaway from <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23foss4g">#foss4g</a>: PostGIS 2's tagline should be "You no longer have an excuse to use anything else."</p>&mdash; Michael Weisman (@mweisman) <a href="https://twitter.com/mweisman/status/115163092207403010" data-datetime="2011-09-17T20:39:55+00:00">September 17, 2011</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<ol>
<li>Javascript mapping libraries - <a href="http://openlayers.org/">there</a> are <a href="http://leaflet.cloudmade.com/">now</a> more <a href="http://2011.foss4g.org/sessions/geomap-%E2%80%93-new-open-source-javascript-mapping-api">ways</a> to <a href="http://polymaps.org/">get</a> an <a href="http://mapstraction.com/">interactive</a> map <a href="http://www.tile5.org/">into</a> a browser than I can keep track of. Those based on Javascript and/or HTML5 are proliferating like wildfire. The "I" in "RIA" now stands for "intranet".</li>
</ol>


<p>I'm still organizing my notes and thoughts about what I saw at FOSS4G. It's impossible to describe the richness of the information that was available. The only real downtime I had was that which I sought for myself. I'll follow up these quick observations in the near future as I begin to dig into the new tools I was exposed to.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
