<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: IFTTT | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/ifttt/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-29T10:24:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Put Planet Geospatial to Work for You]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm happy to see that <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2012/11/24/planet-geospatial-the-way-forward/" target="_blank">James has decided keep Planet Geospatial going</a>. It's been one of the more consistently valuable resources in the community since its inception and it's good that it will continue.</p>

<p>While I'm looking forward to seeing how <a href="http://twitter.com/cageyjames" target="_blank">James</a> evolves <a href="http://planetgs.com" target="_blank">Planet Geospatial</a>, there are ways to more efficiently extract value out of its current state right now. At its core, Planet Geospatial is an RSS feed. RSS can safely be called "venerable" nowadays, but it still does what it does very well.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3002" height="400" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/postgis_evernote1.png" title="PostGIS items from Planet Geospatial in Evernote" width="640" /></p>

<p>Two of my favorite tools for culling down the firehose that is Planet Geospatial are <a href="http://ifttt.com" target="_blank">IFTTT</a> (the title of this post is a riff on the IFTTT motto) and <a href="http://evernote.com/" target="_blank">Evernote</a>. If you're not familiar with IFTTT, you should be. It reminds me of a more-intuitive Yahoo Pipes and it allows you to mix channels, triggers, and actions to automate processes of your choosing. It's become by preferred method of synchronizing my blog with social media and for filtering data sources. It also drives the <a href="http://twitter.com/QGISInfo" target="_blank">Unofficial QGIS Info</a> Twitter account. <!--more--></p>

<p>Evernote is becoming a key tool for me to store and access notes and other kinds of information. The fact that it runs on every device I own in addition to browsers makes it very useful for me as I move between customer locations.</p>

<p>When James first posted that he was wondering what to do with Planet Geospatial, I shared with him an IFTTT recipe that inserts posts from Planet Geospatial about <a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> into an Evernote notebook. He kindly tweeted it.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Try this IFTTT Recipe: Log PostGIS Items from Planet Geospatial to Evernote. <a href="https://t.co/z5hOxPqH" title="https://ifttt.com/recipes/67215">ifttt.com/recipes/67215</a></p>&mdash; James Fee (@cageyjames) <a href="https://twitter.com/cageyjames/status/272025049526050816" data-datetime="2012-11-23T17:13:20+00:00">November 23, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>I usually have three to four such filters running, depending upon topics that I'm watching. Currently, I'm grabbing posts about PostGIS, <a href="http://geojson.org" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>, and <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/" target="_blank">CartoCSS</a>. These filters allow me to peruse the posts at my leisure without worrying about missing them. I can delete them from my notebook or save them as I see fit. For me, it's like having a DVR for Planet Geospatial.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Planet Geospatial is an information source. It just happens to be an information source that's based on a mature, open, well-documented, and widely adopted standard. As such, there's no need to wait for James to evolve it into something else. We can take it and transform it to meet our needs and then share it back. It's been a great community resource for a long time; it will be fun to see what the community can do with it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Favorite QGIS Resources of the Moment]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/27/favorite-qgis-resources-of-the-moment/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/27/favorite-qgis-resources-of-the-moment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been dabbling more with Quantum GIS (<a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a>) lately. I'm not doing anything particularly sophisticated but it's a great viewer for some data types (<a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a>, <a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>) that aren't supported by my commercial desktop GIS so it's helping me validate outputs of some applications I'm writing.</p>

<p><img alt="" src="http://fossies.org/unix/misc/qgis-1.8.0.tar.gz:a/qgis-1.8.0/images/splash/splash.png" /></p>

<p>While I'll never be a real cartographer, I am interested in doing a little more. Here are the resources that have been helping me the most lately...</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I'll start with three blogs:</p>

<p><a href="http://underdark.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">Anita Graser</a> (<a href="http://twitter.com/underdarkgis" target="_blank">@underdarkgis</a>)</p>

<p><a href="http://woostuff.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">Nathan Woodrow</a> (<a href="http://twitter.com/madmanwoo" target="_blank">@madmanwoo</a>)</p>

<p><a href="http://mapbox.com/blog/" target="_blank">The MapBox Blog</a> (<a href="http://twitter.com/mapbox" target="_blank">@mapbox</a>)</p>

<p>The MapBox blog takes some explaining. It is primarily about how to be productive with MapBox, but some posts deal with using QGIS in your workflows. Those posts have some good information. All of these blogs have been helpful to me over the last couple of months.</p>

<p>Outside of that, I set up a Google Alert for QGIS which feeds me all kinds of things: posts from other blogs, mailing entries, StackExchange questions, and so on. To make that easy, I ran the feed from that alert through <a href="http://ifttt.com/" target="_blank">ifttt.com</a> and have it posting to a Twitter account: (<a href="http://twitter.com/QGISInfo" target="_blank">@QGISInfo</a>). Feel free to check it out. Keep in mind that it's based on a Google search so odd results may creep in from time to time. I've been running the alert for a few weeks and it's been pretty clean. The Twitter feed is new and will be sparse until a few refresh cycles happen. Think of it as a poor man's "Planet QGIS." I hope you find it useful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
