<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: awesome flag | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/awesome-flag/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-18T19:31:01-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Maryland GIS Data Resources]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/09/26/free-maryland-gis-data-resources/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/09/26/free-maryland-gis-data-resources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It was with great interest that I read <a href="http://greatergreaterwashington.org/post/12041/regional-map-data-is-expensive/">this post last week about the cost of GIS data in the Washington, DC region</a>. Not only is the post itself informative but the comment discussion is also a worthy read.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.netstate.com/states/symb/flags/md_flag.htm"><img alt="" class="aligncenter" height="256" src="http://www.netstate.com/states/symb/flags/images/md_fi.gif" title="Maryland state flag" width="384" /></a></p>

<p>This did get me curious, however, as to which counties in my home state of Maryland make GIS data freely available. The approach I took to this was simple: I did what any average county resident would probably do and went to each county's web site looking for a link to a data download. If I didn't find something in a few clicks, I went to Google (search term: {county name} md gis). If there was nothing there, I moved on. With that, here are the counties I found which provide free, downloadable GIS data:</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://ccgovernment.carr.org/ccg/mapserver4/gis/webpage/MapCatalogPage.html">Carroll County</a> (2000 Orthos only)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ccgov.org/dept_planning/gis/avdata.cfm">Cecil County</a></p>

<p><a href="https://ww3.frederickcountymd.gov/gisdatazip/">Frederick County</a>  (requires registration)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.harfordcountymd.gov/GIS/Index.cfm">Harford County</a></p>

<p><a href="http://gis.howardcountymd.gov/mainsite/GeneralDataDownload.html">Howard County</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.stmarysmd.com/gis/">St. Mary's County</a></p>

<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> Additionally, data is available from the <a href="http://www.marylandgis.net/SHAdata/list.asp">Maryland State Highway Administration</a> (ESRI personal geodatabase)</p>

<p>I'm sure Maryland is not unique in the varying ways in which GIS data is distributed and the myriad ways local jurisdictions attempt cost recovery. These are difficult issues in the best of times and the current economic climate doesn't make them any easier.</p>

<p>I only surveyed data that was available from the counties (and Baltimore City) directly. I did not delve into the many municipalities. Basically, the list above should not be interpreted as comprehensive but I hope it is useful to some.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
