<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: arcgis engine | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/arcgis-engine/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-18T22:16:30-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Thoughts on ArcGIS 10.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/01/13/First-Thoughts-on-ArcGIS-100/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/01/13/First-Thoughts-on-ArcGIS-100</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.esri.com/news/podcasts/audio/speaker/dangermond_arcgis10.mp3">announcement</a> that ArcGIS 9.4 is being re-christened as 10.0 leaves me feeling somewhat bemused. I have seen the new version of Desktop and it is nice and will finally update the current Office-97-feeling UI. The <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/whats-new/whats-coming.html">list of changes coming in 10.0</a> (published so far) is impressive but I haven?t seen any discussion of the changes coming to the ArcGIS architecture, which is of greater interest to me as a developer and integrator. Given the past history of ArcGIS, calling this release 10.0, in my mind, implies a significant architectural shift. ArcGIS 8 was a clear departure from the previous releases of ARC/INFO. Indeed, it not only came with a new version but introduced the name ?ArcGIS.?<!--more--></p>

<p>ArcGIS 9 represented a less-radical, but significant architectural update. By restructuring the underlying ArcObjects components of ArcGIS, ESRI enabled the introduction of ArcGIS Server and ArcGIS Engine and began to unify their desktop, web and mobile offerings. ArcGIS 8 would not have been able to support this.</p>

<p>Quite frankly, I think the current ArcGIS architecture has just about run its course. I think it is time to recognize that desktop, web and mobile applications are each different and need to be built differently. The current reliance on a common pool of ArcObjects, while not necessarily a bad thing for the desktop platform, is a hindrance for ArcGIS Server. To be specific, I am talking about COM here.</p>

<p>ArcGIS Server would benefit greatly from breaking its dependency on COM. I would not complain if I never had to do <a href="http://blog.davebouwman.com/index.php/2009/12/zen-and-the-art-of-serverobjectextensions/">this kind of stuff</a> anymore. This would, of course, mean replacing the capability for extending ArcGIS Server using ArcObjects with a similar capability. It would also mean choosing what to replace it with: .Net?...Java?...ROR?...something else? I think recent efforts with the REST API and its client technologies (JSAPI, Flex API, Silverlight API) speak to a way ahead. I can now pick a native approach and build ArcGIS solutions with less COM than ever before and ArcGIS Server itself is abstracted from the client code enough that replacing the technology that drives it can be relatively transparent. My hope is that these APIs continue to evolve and become more robust and are, perhaps, augmented by a server-side API to enable the development of advanced custom tools without the use of COM.</p>

<p>While ArcGIS Server is far from perfect, it does provide one of the better (quasi)REST APIs available and a consistent way to expose geo-processing and analysis in web applications. I think an official realization that Server is different and a commitment to re-engineer it top to bottom will benefit it in the long run. So the announcement of 10.0 now begs the question ?What is the roadmap for the 10.x series?? I haven?t seen anything yet that indicates 10.0 will introduce such changes but, perhaps, it could be setting the stage for them. ArcGIS 9.0 was released in May 2004. By the time of the scheduled release of 10.0, we will have been working with 9.x for six years. The 8.x series lasted about three and a half years. Given that we could be looking at a few years of 10.x, I?d be interested in knowing more about the underpinnings of 10.x and plans for the future. Could make the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/devsummit/index.html">DevSummit</a> and <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/feduc/index.html">FedUC</a> interesting this year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patch to ArcGIS 9.3 Service Pack 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/11/25/Patch-to-ArcGIS-9.3-Service-Pack-1/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/11/25/Patch-to-ArcGIS-9.3-Service-Pack-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you've recently installed ArcGIS 9.3 Service Pack 1, be aware that there is a patch out that fixes an issue with topology validation. You can read more about it here:</p>

<p><a href="http://support.esri.com/index.cfm?fa=knowledgebase.techarticles.articleShow&amp;d=35833">http://support.esri.com/index.cfm?fa=knowledgebase.techarticles.articleShow&amp;d=35833</a></p>

<p>This patch seems to apply to Desktop, Engine and Server so you may want to check it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS 9.4 Holistic Testing Schedule Posted]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/08/01/ArcGIS-9.4-Holistic-Testing-Schedule-Posted/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/08/01/ArcGIS-9.4-Holistic-Testing-Schedule-Posted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you missed it, ESRI as posted the <a href="http://blogs.esri.com/Dev/blogs/holistictesting/">ArcGIS 9.4 holistic testing schedule</a>. The schedule currently runs through the end of April 2009 but doesn't give any hints of a release date.</p>

<p>So, just in time for the UC next week, you can begin to think about 9.4. If you want to get involved with it, now's your chance.</p>

<p>Hopefully, I'll see a lot of you next week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS 9.3 is Shipping]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/06/25/ArcGIS-9.3-is-Shipping/"/>
    <updated>2008-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/06/25/ArcGIS-9.3-is-Shipping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to this <a href="http://www.gisuser.com/content/view/14986/">press release</a>, ArcGIS 9.3 started shipping today. ESRI has pretty much stuck to the aggressive schedule that they announced at the Dev Summit.</p>

<p>My experiences thus far with the beta and the release candidate have been pretty positive so it'll be good to get the final product.</p>

<p>Who's starting the pool on the when the first service pack will be out?  ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DDJ on "The Return of the Desktop"]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/08/15/DDJ-on-The-Return-of-the-Desktop/"/>
    <updated>2007-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/08/15/DDJ-on-The-Return-of-the-Desktop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, I swear I'm not on the DDJ payroll, but <a href="http://www.ddj.com/web-development/201202675">this article</a> caught my eye immediately. <a href="http://www.swaine.com/">Michael Swaine</a> has been on a roll lately but I think this one just drips with significance for the GIS community.</p>

<p>Over the past 10 years, as everyone has run screaming from the desktop, I've been a little mystified as to why it was considered a good thing to reduce a <a href="http://www.computerpoweruser.com/Editorial/article.asp?article=articles/archive/c0612/28c12/28c12.asp&amp;guid=">CPU more powerful than everything NASA had in 1969</a> to a mere vehicle for a browser. The browser-based model reduced our computers to really cool-looking equivalents of a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VT220">VT220</a> so it's nice to see that the market is starting to gain back a little sanity.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I will readily admit that the browser model has its advantages. Application deployment is a snap compared to what it takes to ensuring desktops are in synch. Anyone who's had to deal with <a href="http://www.nmciinfo.usmc.mil/nmci2/nmci.nsf/HomePage?openform">NMCI</a> will vouch for that. In addition, there's the matter of targeting the desktop OS. That can be a pain for a desktop app (Windows/UNIX/Linux?, Flavor of Linux?, 32bit or 64bit?, ugh). That hasn't changed much over the years. I remember running ArcView under <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Win32s">Win32s</a> on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_3.1x">Windows 3.11</a> also testing <a href="http://www.macrovision.com/products/installation/installshield.htm">Installshield</a> builds against WinNT 4, Win2K and Win9x for <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/mapobjects/index.html">MapObjects</a> apps. So, yeah, the web app model is definitely attractive. However, the trend has also led to the need for really big bandwidth, multi-socket/multi-core servers and a loss of control at the desktop for the user. If the developer of the server app/service didn't think of it and the sysadmin of the server doesn't want you to have it, you're kind of outta luck. Also, Moore's Law has been giving us faster, better CPUs but we've been asking them to do less and less.</p>

<p>The article gives a few examples of products that are making use of local resources instead merely relying on the server for everything. In the article, things like <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/">Dojo</a>, <a href="http://gears.google.com/">Gears</a> and <a href="http://silverlight.net/">Silverlight</a> are discussed. We're already seeing some of this trend in our market with the advent of the various virtual globes (<a href="http://earth.google.com/">Google Earth</a>, <a href="http://worldwind.arc.nasa.gov/">NASA World Wind</a>, <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/explorer/index.html">ArcGIS Explorer</a>, etc.). These apps tap into very data-rich servers or services but use local resources for tasks such as tile caching. I think GIS is an ideal place to push the boundaries of this model due to the resource-intensive nature of some geospatial processes.</p>

<p>This is an area where, with a little work, the <a href="http://www.esri.com">ESRI</a> product line could shine. With <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/about/desktop_gis.html">ArcGIS Desktop</a>, <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgisengine/index.html">Engine</a> and <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgisserver/">Server</a>, the same objects can potentially reside on the server as well as the desktop. It would be interesting to see these objects be able to communicate together in such a way as distribute processing load between themselves. Of course, any of the technologies mentioned in the article could serve as a basis to do a similar thing with non-ESRI technologies or for users with only a browser. Not that such an approach would be easy or trivial, but it would certainly be worthwhile.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
