<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: arcims | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/arcims/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-17T21:45:06-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS 10 Service Pack 2 Is Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/05/20/arcgis-10-service-pack-2-is-available/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/05/20/arcgis-10-service-pack-2-is-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Esri announced late today that Service Pack 2 for ArcGIS 10 is available. It looks like <a href="http://downloads2.esri.com/support/downloads/other_/ArcGIS-10sp2-issues.htm">a fairly sizable list of issues</a> was addressed with this service pack.</p>

<p>Who knows, we could be witnessing history as this could potentially be the last service pack to address ArcIMS. (Well, I can dream, can't I?)</p>

<p>Anyway, if you're among those who like to wait until the second service pack before doing an Esri upgrade, you can now start putting 9.3 out to pasture. Live it up!</p>

<p><img alt="Out to pasture" src="http://www.ia.nrcs.usda.gov/news/images/Pics/pasture.gif" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcGIS 10.0 and 10.1 Deprecation Plan Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/19/arcgis-100-and-101-deprecation-plan-released/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/19/arcgis-100-and-101-deprecation-plan-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/mikehogan">Mike Hogan</a> tweeted that the Esri deprecation plan for ArcGIS 10.0 and 10.1 is now available. It can be found <a href="http://downloads2.esri.com/support/TechArticles/ArcGIS_10_and__101_Deprecation_Plan.pdf">here</a>. Much of what it contains is not new as Esri has been pretty good about getting information related to 10.x out. Some of the more interesting things (to me) include (comments in parens are mine):</p>

<blockquote>

ArcGIS Server 10.0 is the last release with support for 32-bit operating systems. The next release of ArcGIS Server (10.1) will run natively as a 64-bit application, requiring 64-bit operating systems. (I heard about the native 64-bit move at the Esri UC but I didn't know that included dropping 32-bit. It's not a big deal for me but I can imagine it'll be an impact for many.)

ArcGIS Server 10.0 is the last release supporting publishing non-optimized map documents (MXD files). The next major release will only support publishing optimized maps (MSDs) as that is the best practice for map publishing. (There you have it, no more serving from MXDs after 10.0.)

ArcGIS Server 10.1 will be the last planned release for the ArcGIS Server Web ADFs (Application Developer Framework) for both Microsoft .NET and Java. (We had a small "wake" in San Diego for the ADFs. I won't shed a tear when it's "official.")

ArcGIS Server 10.1 will no longer support local connections (DCOM connections) from Web ADF applications. ArcGIS Server 10.1 will be a web services (REST and SOAP) server only. (This is actually pretty major and the document details the impacts. <strong>If you have any ADF code doing editing and such, read this!</strong>)
</blockquote>


<p>There's a lot of good information in the document, especially pertaining to ArcGIS Server so it's definitely worth a read.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crazy Times - Coming Up For Air]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/06/26/crazy-times-coming-up-for-air/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/06/26/crazy-times-coming-up-for-air</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been an extremely busy few months, as evidenced by the pace (or lack thereof) of blogging. I have been hopping between customer sites, mainly helping with ArcGIS Server implementations. We're also re-hosting an ArcIMS site for someone. I expect that to eventually transition as well but we have to get it moved first. I'm also working a pro-bono implementation of PostGIS/GeoServer/OpenLayers for the town of Green Mountain Falls, Colorado. That's been fun. It's great to see how a small town can marshall it resources (Boys Scouts with GPS collected trails as an Eagle Scout project) to get things done. The initial implementation will be simple as they are more interested in getting their data out there but then we'll circle back around to address public-service-type applications after that.</p>

<p>Significant changes are coming for <a href="http://pub.obtusesoft.com">zigGIS</a>. Abe, Paolo and I have been laying out a roadmap for its way ahead. Look for an announcement soon via <a href="http://twitter.com/zigGIS">zigGIS on Twitter</a>.</p>

<p>I have been having a lot of fun with the REST-based APIs from ESRI (Javascript, Flex, Silverlight/WPF). In particular, I've been happy with how extensible they are in terms of being able to support new data sources.
<a href="http://openlayers.org/pipermail/users/2009-June/012414.html">OpenLayers 2.8</a> and <a href="http://blog.opengeo.org/2009/06/17/geoexplorer-preview/">GeoExplorer</a> are also on my radar but that radar screen is getting pretty crowded.</p>

<p>All of this with less than a week to go before vacation. Whew!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Little Bit of Java]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/07/01/a-little-bit-of-java/"/>
    <updated>2008-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/07/01/a-little-bit-of-java</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just wrapped up the second phase of the first significant Java project I've done in a long time. In general, I try to be technology-agnostic but, due mainly to customer demand, I find myself working predominantly in .Net. As a result, I find myself treading water a little bit when I have to work with Java.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-203" height="300" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/07/java.png?w=295" width="295" /></p>

<p>I did this last project in NetBeans 6.1 and was generally pleased with it. I was originally an Eclipse fan but have been less and less happy with it with each release. But my real problem is that I need to get more comfortable with the workflow when working with Java and Java tools. This last round of coding was a little more "cowboy" than I am typcially comfortable with.</p>

<p>This time around, I was working with ArcIMS (ugh), JSP and a couple of custom servlets. I found NetBeans integration of Tomcat to be pretty seamless, yielding a test/debug experience similar to that you get when developing ASP.NET in VS2005 and VS2008. I see hooks to integrate with SCC systems such as CVS and SVN. We're currently using VSS (again, mostly .Net work) but I've been meaning to set up an SVN server. This may give me the little extra push I needed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
