<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: WeoGeo | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/weogeo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-26T15:36:36-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using BruTile and MapsUI to Enable WeoGeo Previews]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/21/using-brutile-and-mapsui-to-enable-weogeo-previews/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/21/using-brutile-and-mapsui-to-enable-weogeo-previews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/">my company announced the availability</a> of the first beta version of <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=weogeo">WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS</a>. Unlike the previous version, which opened a separate browser window, this new release allows a user to order a data set from <a href="http://market.weogeo.com">WeoGeo Market</a> or a library from inside ArcMap.</p>

<p>One of the challenges was enabling data set previews. If you browse data sets using the <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">WeoGeo</a> online tool, you can get an idea of what the data set contains by using the data set preview images supplied by the data set provider.</p>

<p>When we developed the first version of WeoGeo Tools for WeoGeo, they used kamap to create preview tiles for data sets. This was accomplished by used either one of two desktop tools: the weoapp (command line) or gWeoApp (GUI). The first version of WeoGeo Tools used the weoapp in the background to create tiles when uploading data. <!--more--></p>

<p>In between the two versions, WeoGeo switched to a ZYX tile structure similar to Google Maps or <a href="http://wiki.osgeo.org/wiki/Tile_Map_Service_Specification">TMS</a> (although not always using spherical mercator). This change made the idea of integrating ordering much easier.</p>

<p>Part of the challenge was implementing support for preview tiles in a manner that provided a smooth user experience inside ArcMap. Luckily, my experience with <a href="http://sharpmap.codeplex.com/">SharpMap</a> pointed the way. It's been a while since I've blogged SharpMap but, in the intervening time, the project added support for map tiles by way of another .Net-based open-source project called <a href="http://brutile.codeplex.com/">BruTile</a>. It was through SharpMap that I was first exposed to BruTile and the two projects have developed something of a symbiotic relationship.</p>

<p>A while back, BruTile branched, with its UI aspects being spun off into another project called <a href="http://mapsui.codeplex.com/">MapsUI</a>. Between these two projects, I had what I needed to added support for WeoGeo previews. I've been building the UI elements of WeoGeo tools using Windows Presentation Foundation (WPF) from the beginning. MapsUI provided exactly what I needed in a simple WPF map control to embed tile support into my application.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/orderwindow.png"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-1574" height="491" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/orderwindow.png" title="Order window showing preview tiles for Maryland census tracts" width="590" /></a><div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px">Order window showing preview tiles for Maryland census tracts<br/></div></div>


<p>Because WeoGeo chose well-known tiling schemes for their previews, most of what I needed was already there. For data sets with preview tiles in spherical mercator, there was already a BruTile schema defined for working with Google Maps that I could leverage. For tiles in WGS84, there was also a schema defined based on the work <a href="http://www.maptiler.org/google-maps-coordinates-tile-bounds-projection/">documented at the MapTiler site</a> (which is the same schema WeoGeo uses for WGS84 tiles).</p>

<p>The primary customization that was required was to create custom request classes that formatted tile request URLs for WeoGeo. To get a tile from WeoGeo, you need to know two pieces of information in addition to the Z, Y and X positions of the tile: you also need to know the data set (identified by a GUID) for which you want tiles and the file format (JPG or PNG) of those tiles. So you end up with a URL that looks like this:</p>

<p><em>http://weodata.weogeo.com/dataset_tiles/{dataset_token}/xyz/{Z}/{Y}/{X}.{format}</em></p>

<p>Beyond the request, you can fine-tune the tile schema by using information from the data set metadata to set the tile extent and remove unused scale levels. For spherical mercator tiles, for example, I defined custom tile source, tile schema and request classes that defined these additional pieces of information. The result was the ability to very easily create a TileLayer for use by the MapsUI control:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}
//_dataSet is deserialized from JSON and contains the data set metadata</p>

<p>//Create schema based on data set format, min and max scaled and tile extent</p>

<pre><code>        var weoSchema = new WeoGeoSchema(_dataSet.TileFileFormat, _dataSet.Scales[0], _dataSet.Scales[_ds.Scales.Count - 1], new BruTile.Extent(_dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.West, _dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.South, _dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.East, _dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.North));
        var weosource = new WeoGeoTileSource(new WeoGeoRequest("http://weodata.weogeo.com", _dataSet.Token, _dataSet.Scales[0], _dataSet.Scales[_dataSet.Scales.Count - 1], _dataSet.TileFileFormat), weoSchema);
        var tl = new TileLayer(weosource); //the layer to be added to the map control
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Using BruTile, this aspect of adding support for ordering went very quickly and smoothly. I like that they have native WPF UI components as I generally avoid using WinForms anymore when doing Windows desktop development. There's a lot of good work between BruTile and MapsUI and I'll be using these tools more in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I generally try to keep my blog separate from my daily work life in that I usually don't directly blog about the projects on which I am working. I'm going to deviate from that today to make a couple of announcements.</p>

<p>It's been a while now, but you may recall that, about a year ago, <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">WeoGeo</a> <a href="http://blog.weogeo.com/2010/02/16/introducing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/">announced the availability</a> of WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS. It was an <a href="http://www.esri.com/products/index.html#desktop_gis">ArcGIS Desktop</a> extension that integrated the ability browse data sets on WeoGeo Market or hosted libraries as well as providing the ability to upload your data directly from ArcMap.</p>

<p>My first bit of news is that my company, <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah Technologies</a>, produced that extension for WeoGeo. We did not announce it at the time because the original plan was for WeoGeo to support it after it was released. That arrangement has continued to the present.  <!--more--></p>

<p>Shortly before the <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> International User Conference last year, I delivered a preliminary build of an updated version with a better user interface. This was shown in the WeoGeo booth but never officially released, primarily because WeoGeo had a few major changes to their systems and APIs in the offing which would have had a large impact on the extension's code. So we decided to hold off on implementing a new version until after those changes were complete. That leads me to my second announcement.</p>

<p>Zekiah is happy to announce the availability of the first beta release of the new version of WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS. This release improves an existing capability (browsing Market and libraries), adds a new one (the ability customize and create a data order) and temporarily removes a previous capability (uploading data). But don't worry, uploading will be back very soon! WeoGeo introduced a new set of APIs to support uploading (the previous version used their command-line tool behind the scenes) and also implemented a new tiling scheme for preview images so the upload capability requires a complete re-write but will be better. (We also intend to leverage new the ability of <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> to generate WeoGeo tile packs so you may want to check that out.)</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/02/weotools10.png"><img alt="" height="314" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/02/weotools10.png" title="Browsing WeoGeo Market in ArcGIS Desktop 10" width="590" /></a><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Browsing WeoGeo Market in ArcGIS Desktop 10<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>This release is an open beta. There are versions for ArcGIS Desktop 9.3 and 10.0 which currently have the same capabilities; but this will change. You can find information about WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS (and download it) here: <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=weogeo">http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=weogeo</a>. From there, you can download the extension and also view the development roadmap. The user manual is draft and will be fleshed out with more detail with each release. When you view the roadmap, you will see that the capabilities between 9.3 and 10.0 will quickly diverge. We plan to integrate the new upload capability with 10.0 but limit 9.3 to browse and download. The final release (scheduled for mid-June) will be the only one that supports 9.3. From that point forward, we will focus solely on 10.0 and beyond. Please feel free to download the version for your platform. We have also established a <a href="http://zekiah.uservoice.com">feedback site</a> for comments.</p>

<p>One of the best parts is that we plan to keep WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS free-of-charge. Of course there are fees associated with ordering data from WeoGeo Market or from having a library subscription but users will be able to install and use the extension throughout their organization without needing to purchase a license.</p>

<p>We are excited about this release for a number of reasons. First, this is the first product that will have a Zekiah "nameplate" so it breaks new ground for us. Second, it strengthens our relationship with WeoGeo, who have been great to work with throughout this process. And, third, this release will put the power of WeoGeo's hosted data infrastructure at the fingertips of analysts working in ArcMap. This release helps streamline the WeoGeo workflow for ArcMap users, allowing them to access their hosted geospatial content without leaving their environment.</p>

<p>I won't be using my blog for announcements in the long term. We are finalizing a new company site and announcements will ultimately come from there. You can also track us on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Zekiah-Technologies-Inc/134576235629?ref=ts">Facebook</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/zekiah">Twitter</a>, and <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/company/109709">LinkedIn</a> for news related to WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS and Zekiah in general.</p>

<p>Between project work which almost kept me from attending NCGIS and this, there have been a few long nights so I am happy to pass this milestone. There's quite a bit left to be done but it's nice to get this far.</p>

<p>In the coming weeks, I do plan to blog some aspects of building the extension. I've gotten pretty comfortable with some nice technologies like <a href="http://brutile.codeplex.com/">BruTile</a> and am excited to explore them more. Stay tuned...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started With a Python Wrapper For the WeoGeo API]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/26/getting-started-with-a-python-wrapper-for-the-weogeo-api/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/26/getting-started-with-a-python-wrapper-for-the-weogeo-api</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2011/01/03/turning-it-up-to-11/">goals for 2011</a> was to sharpen my Python skills. As if on cue, <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">WeoGeo</a> puts out a Python wrapper for their RESTful API. It can be found <a href="http://code.google.com/p/weogeo-public-code/">here</a>. The good news is that I now have a familiar problem set to sink my teeth into. The bad news (for me) is that it's so easy to use it's probably not going to do much for my Python skills.</p>

<p>The wrapper addresses the full WeoGeo API (Datasets, Jobs, Events, etc.) so it exposes pretty much everything you can through through the WeoGeo SaaS. For example, here is a very simple browse operation:</p>

<!--more-->


<p>{% codeblock lang:python %}
import WeoGeoAPI</p>

<h1>do a simple browse of WeoGeo Market</h1>

<p>session = WeoGeoAPI.weoSession('market.weogeo.com', '', '')
session.connectToMarket()</p>

<h1>send some parameters to look for vector data sets covering Washington, DC.</h1>

<p>datasets = session.getDatasets('JSON', '&amp;data_type=VECTOR&amp;per_page=2&amp;page=1&amp;north=39.043&amp;south=38.767&amp;west=-77.2&amp;east=-77.906')</p>

<h1>prints the raw JSON response</h1>

<p>print datasets
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>The output, cleaned up with <a href="http://jsonlint.com/">JSONLint</a> is at the end of this post. The WeoGeo JSON output for a dataset is large so I used the 'per_page" parameter to limit the response to two datasets.</p>

<p>Since I started playing with the wrapper, WeoGeo has posted a test script which shows how to use it. I'll start playing with creating jobs next. A word of caution about jobs: I highly recommend creating your own individual WeoGeo library (free) and loading a couple of datasets to play with. Most of the datasets on WeoGeo Market are for sale commercially so that's probably not the best place to test an API.</p>

<p>In all, the wrapper seems pretty straightforward. I'm looking forward to working with it in more detail.</p>

<p>The JSON response to the browse executed above:
{% codeblock lang:js %}
{</p>

<pre><code>'per_page': 2,
'total_entries': 34,
'current_page': 1,
'total_pages': 17,
'items': [
    {
        'rating': 0.0,
        'projection': 'geo',
        'provider_margin': 1995.0,
        'uncompressed_misc_files_size': 7683891,
        'spatial_resolution': 0,
        'children_count': 0,
        'datum': 'WGS84',
        'library': {
            'name': 'Pitney Bowes - Business Insight',
            'id': 112
        },
        'kml_file_size': 0,
        'hosted': True,
        'market': 'Complete',
        'center_lat': 38.8051135,
        'layers': [
            'all'
        ],
        'east': -74.986282,
        'votes': 0,
        'content_license': {
            'url': 'http: //licenses.weogeo.com/licenses/8/original.PDF?1273263090',
            'name': 'PBBI Software and Data End User License v. April 2008'
        },
        'data_type': 'VECTOR',
        'royalty_model': 'CREDITED',
        'west': -79.487651,
        'scales': '6;7;8;9;10;11;12',
        'provider_discount_expires_at': None,
        'boundaries': {
            'geo': {
                'proj4': '+proj=latlong +datum=wgs84',
                'north': '39.723622',
                'west': '-79.487651',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'projection_datum': 'geo-wgs84',
                'east': '-74.986282',
                'south': '37.886605'
            },
            'tiles': {
                'number_of_lines': '316',
                'number_of_samples': '316',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'line_pixel_size': '-830.510836842',
                'sample_pixel_size': '1585.72818023',
                'proj4': '+proj=merc +a=6378137 +b=6378137 +lat_ts=0.0 +lon_0=0.0 +x_0=0.0 +y_0=0 +k=1.0 +units=m +nadgrids=@null +no_defs',
                'projection_datum': 'spherical_mercator',
                'west': '-8848524.83367',
                'north': '4825860.68838',
                'east': '-8347434.72872',
                'south': '4563419.26394'
            },
            'native': {
                'number_of_lines': '316',
                'number_of_samples': '316',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'line_pixel_size': '-830.510836842',
                'sample_pixel_size': '1585.72818023',
                'proj4': '+proj=merc +a=6378137 +b=6378137 +lat_ts=0.0 +lon_0=0.0 +x_0=0.0 +y_0=0 +k=1.0 +units=m +nadgrids=@null +no_defs',
                'projection_datum': 'spherical_mercator',
                'west': '-8848524.83367',
                'north': '4825860.68838',
                'east': '-8347434.72872',
                'south': '4563419.26394'
            },
            'data': {
                'proj4': '',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'projection_datum': 'geo-WGS84'
            },
            'baseimage': {
                'number_of_lines': 0,
                'number_of_samples': 0,
                'west': '-8848524.833673440000000',
                'line_pixel_size': 0,
                'sample_pixel_size': 0,
                'proj4': 'spherical_mercator',
                'projection_datum': 'spherical_mercator',
                'north': '4945185.028635530000000',
                'east': '-8347434.728720820000000',
                'south': '4444094.923682910000000'
            }
        },
        'tile_layer_type': 'xyz',
        'provider_discount_rate': 100,
        'provider_discount_expire_option': True,
        'x_conv': 1,
        'parents_count': 0,
        'status': 'Approved',
        'north': 39.723622,
        'description': '&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;StreetPro USA&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;\nVersion 2009.12&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt; \nStreetPro offers users a premier street-level data product featuring accuracy and street display quality unparalleled in the industry. It reflects real world geographic conditions with the most current street data available.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;With StreetPro,
        perform the most comprehensive,
        efficient and effective street-based analysis possible.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;StreetPro U.S.: &amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Provides the most complete,
        current and comprehensive streets on the market.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Integrates easily with Pitney Bowes Business Insight software.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Includes exclusive tools for use with Pitney Bowes Business Insight software.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Ships with display templates to get up and running quickly and easily with great looking maps.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Created from Tele Atlas streets,
        this highly accurate street data is gathered from over 35,
        000 sources including E911 agencies,
        the U.S. Postal Service,
        city planning commissions,
        state departments of transportation and other local government sources. ',
        'spatial_resolution_in_meters': 0.0,
        'provider_min_margin': 477.67,
        'from_appliance?': False,
        'center_long': -77.2369665,
        'user': {
            'username': 'pbbidata',
            'rating': 5.0,
            'votes': 1
        },
        'data_created_on': '2009/12/15',
        'provider_max_discount': 304.32,
        'permalink': 'pbbidata_streetpro_maryland',
        'uploaded_at': '2010/05/06 15: 42: 51 -0400',
        'name': u'StreetPro\xae Maryland',
        'price_type': 'VARIABLE',
        'tile_file_format': 'png',
        'number_of_layers': 1,
        'file_format': 'mapinfo_tab',
        'token': '64ac8785-eab9-4856-b04b-1f33d872f511',
        'uncompressed_data_files_size': 127090387,
        'y_conv': 1,
        'max_price': 1995.0,
        'south': 37.886605
    },
    {
        'rating': 0.0,
        'projection': 'geo',
        'provider_margin': 1995.0,
        'uncompressed_misc_files_size': 7683891,
        'spatial_resolution': 0,
        'children_count': 0,
        'datum': 'WGS84',
        'library': {
            'name': 'Pitney Bowes - Business Insight',
            'id': 112
        },
        'kml_file_size': 0,
        'hosted': True,
        'market': 'Complete',
        'center_lat': 38.003375,
        'layers': [
            'all'
        ],
        'east': -75.166435,
        'votes': 0,
        'content_license': {
            'url': 'http: //licenses.weogeo.com/licenses/8/original.PDF?1273263090',
            'name': 'PBBI Software and Data End User License v. April 2008'
        },
        'data_type': 'VECTOR',
        'royalty_model': 'CREDITED',
        'west': -83.675415,
        'scales': '5;6;7;8;9;10;11;12',
        'provider_discount_expires_at': None,
        'boundaries': {
            'geo': {
                'proj4': '+proj=latlong +datum=wgs84',
                'north': '39.466012',
                'west': '-83.675415',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'projection_datum': 'geo-wgs84',
                'east': '-75.166435',
                'south': '36.540738'
            },
            'tiles': {
                'number_of_lines': '316',
                'number_of_samples': '316',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'line_pixel_size': '-1308.10717344',
                'sample_pixel_size': '2997.51683788',
                'proj4': '+proj=merc +a=6378137 +b=6378137 +lat_ts=0.0 +lon_0=0.0 +x_0=0.0 +y_0=0 +k=1.0 +units=m +nadgrids=@null +no_defs',
                'projection_datum': 'spherical_mercator',
                'west': '-9314704.58972',
                'north': '4788645.33132',
                'east': '-8367489.26895',
                'south': '4375283.46452'
            },
            'native': {
                'number_of_lines': '316',
                'number_of_samples': '316',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'line_pixel_size': '-1308.10717344',
                'sample_pixel_size': '2997.51683788',
                'proj4': '+proj=merc +a=6378137 +b=6378137 +lat_ts=0.0 +lon_0=0.0 +x_0=0.0 +y_0=0 +k=1.0 +units=m +nadgrids=@null +no_defs',
                'projection_datum': 'spherical_mercator',
                'west': '-9314704.58972',
                'north': '4788645.33132',
                'east': '-8367489.26895',
                'south': '4375283.46452'
            },
            'data': {
                'proj4': '',
                'datum': 'WGS84',
                'projection_datum': 'geo-WGS84'
            },
            'baseimage': {
                'number_of_lines': 0,
                'number_of_samples': 0,
                'west': '-9314704.589715850000000',
                'line_pixel_size': 0,
                'sample_pixel_size': 0,
                'proj4': 'spherical_mercator',
                'projection_datum': 'spherical_mercator',
                'north': '5055572.058304870000000',
                'east': '-8367489.268945700000000',
                'south': '4108356.737534730000000'
            }
        },
        'tile_layer_type': 'xyz',
        'provider_discount_rate': 100,
        'provider_discount_expire_option': True,
        'x_conv': 1,
        'parents_count': 0,
        'status': 'Approved',
        'north': 39.466012,
        'description': '&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;StreetPro USA&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;\nVersion 2009.12&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt; \nStreetPro offers users a premier street-level data product featuring accuracy and street display quality unparalleled in the industry. It reflects real world geographic conditions with the most current street data available.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;With StreetPro,
        perform the most comprehensive,
        efficient and effective street-based analysis possible.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;StreetPro U.S.: &amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Provides the most complete,
        current and comprehensive streets on the market.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Integrates easily with Pitney Bowes Business Insight software.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Includes exclusive tools for use with Pitney Bowes Business Insight software.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt; * Ships with display templates to get up and running quickly and easily with great looking maps.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Created from Tele Atlas streets,
        this highly accurate street data is gathered from over 35,
        000 sources including E911 agencies,
        the U.S. Postal Service,
        city planning commissions,
        state departments of transportation and other local government sources. ',
        'spatial_resolution_in_meters': 0.0,
        'provider_min_margin': 477.71,
        'from_appliance?': False,
        'center_long': -79.420925,
        'user': {
            'username': 'pbbidata',
            'rating': 5.0,
            'votes': 1
        },
        'data_created_on': '2009/12/15',
        'provider_max_discount': 304.37,
        'permalink': 'pbbidata_streetpro_virginia',
        'uploaded_at': '2010/05/06 14: 35: 58 -0400',
        'name': u'StreetPro\xae Virginia',
        'price_type': 'VARIABLE',
        'tile_file_format': 'png',
        'number_of_layers': 1,
        'file_format': 'mapinfo_tab',
        'token': '06ce3537-deb2-cc51-a081-2360eff828f7',
        'uncompressed_data_files_size': 234980712,
        'y_conv': 1,
        'max_price': 1995.0,
        'south': 36.540738
    }
]
</code></pre>

<p>}
{% endcodeblock %}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ten-Second Tidy]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/12/10/ten-second-tidy/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/12/10/ten-second-tidy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things have been a bit hectic the last few weeks and that's left little time for blogging. Quite a bit has happened so I thought I'd do a little round-up (if for no other reason than to clear my own head).</p>

<p>{% youtube cJa7P6dfmco %}</p>

<p>In no particular order:</p>

<p><strong>Steve Coast to Microsoft</strong> (I told you it had been a while) - Firstly, congratulations to Steve (#sincerity).  Secondly, this clearly is the final proof that crowd-sourced data in general, and OpenStreetMaps (sic) in particular, <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/09/16/be-the-crowd/">has no real value when compared to "authoritative" data sources</a> (#sarcasm).</p>

<p><strong>Google Fusion Tables</strong> - The only real problem at this point is the size limitation but, otherwise, this will be a game-changer for storing and sharing data. In its current form, it's already fairly easy to push your data up and expose it through Google's APIs. It'll be interesting to see if it gets easier. Support for spatial queries hints at some analytical capability, too. Speaking of which...</p>

<p><strong>Analytics in GeoCommons</strong> - This is one to watch. They are debuting a new function each day <a href="http://blog.fortiusone.com/2010/12/06/the-12-analytics-of-christmas/">on their blog</a>. FortiusOne builds their platform API-first, UI-second so everything they are showing should be exposed through their APIs. This will be a huge step in moving cloud-based geospatial technology from the "bit-bucket" stage to having a more complete workflow on the cloud infrastructure.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Arc2Earth Data Services and Arc2Cloud</strong> - Continuing the theme of building a complete workflow, <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> is working on exposing a <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/services/data-services/">complete range of Google geospatial services</a> to ArcGIS Desktop users. It's no secret that I'm a fan of Arc2Earth (and <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">my company</a> is a reseller), but this represents a big expansion of capability. Google's cloud infrastructure works differently that Amazon's and I think what <a href="http://beta.arc2cloud.com/">Arc2Earth is doing</a> is important because it will open up another channel for users and enable them to <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/clouds/">make choices based on their needs and requirements</a>.</p>

<p><strong>WeoGeo</strong> - <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">These guys</a> never sit still either. They've got some changes coming up that will greatly increase flexibility for managing spatial data on a cloud infrastructure. Taken together with the previous two entries on GeoCommons and Arc2Earth, I see a lot of innovation in cloud-based GIS really being driven by small, focused companies. This is not simply "push your server to an AMI and keep working." (Although that approach can have some utility.) Each of these companies is trying to figure out how to leverage the unique capabilities of cloud infrastructures to build new workflows and expand capability for users. And, it's important to note, they are making headway.</p>

<p><strong>WhereCampDC</strong> - Obviously, judging from the <a href="http://wherecampdc.org/">web site</a>, it's still in the early planning stages but I'm excited by the idea. This is exactly the kind of independent event that this area needs. I have always been baffled by the lack of such events in this area, especially given the level of geospatial activity around here.</p>

<p><strong>Google Earth 6</strong> - The <a href="http://www.google.com/earth/index.html">latest release</a> confirms that StreetView has yet to drive my street. For that I am happy.</p>

<p><strong>FOSS4G</strong> - The conference doesn't happen until next September and already the buzz is building. I have had people that I know have yet to touch an open-source GIS tool ask me what I know about "that <a href="http://foss4g.org/static/index.html">conference</a> I'm hearing about in Denver."</p>

<p><strong>Silverlight</strong> - I can't think of a technology in recent years that has given me more of a feeling of ambivalence. It has great capability and the Esri Silverlight API team has done good work building on it (this piece addresses Silverlight, not the Esri API). I think it'll continue to be a fine technology for intranet development but I'll leave it there. I don't expect my work with it to wind down anytime soon so I'll keep blogging it as I think it's perfectly possible to be productive with Silverlight within certain parameters. <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/10/30/rip-silverlight-on-the-web/">The whole episode regarding its future</a> (which was something of a tempest in a teapot, in reality) simply highlights the risks involved in relying on closed, proprietary technologies. This time, it was Silverlight, but make no mistake, the same risks are there with Flex/Flash (it just runs on more browser/OS combinations). Of course, there are risks with <em>any</em> technology choice but it's nice when those risks do not include "whim."</p>

<p>So that's it for my odds and ends. It's good to get them stuffed back into the couch. 2010 has been an interesting year. It almost feels like a year in which groundwork is being laid. It may just be me, but I have a feeling of anticipation similar to what I feel right before the first daffodils appear in Spring. It just feels like there's a good bit of pent-up energy and that a lot of new things are about to spring forth. It could be loads of fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clouds]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/07/26/clouds/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/07/26/clouds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent the vast majority of my time at the 2010 ESRI User Conference working the <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a>/<a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth </a>booth. That was fun as I got meet/reconnect with a lot of people but I didn't see much of the conference itself. As a result, I haven't really blogged it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.esri.com">ESRI</a> continued with the "cloud ready" theme that was rolled out at the Federal User Conference but with more details about how they are moving to "the cloud." This generated a lot of buzz amongst many of the attendees from what I could tell. One of the big new features of Arc2Earth v3 (disclaimer: my company is an Arc2Earth reseller) is Cloud Services. As a result, we had a banner in our booth that had the word "cloud" on it, prompting lots of people to stop.<!--more--></p>

<p>Probably the biggest question I heard related to the cloud was "tell me how it works." Generally, people were not asking us about how Arc2Earth uses the cloud (although there was a lot of interest there but that is not the focus of this post) but rather to explain "the cloud" in conceptual terms. What I concluded was that, while ESRI's focus on the cloud raised the consciousness of cloud computing for many attendees, it did not necessarily raise their understanding of it. I don't particularly consider this a failing on the part of ESRI. I think they did a good job of continuing to flesh out their approach, which is what I would expect at their conference.</p>

<p>{% youtube oAB9Y2CVqZU %}</p>

<p>My problem with the term "the cloud" has always been that it conveys the impression of one monolithic entity that's "out there" to be used. In reality, there are multiple "clouds." Each of them is a massive computing infrastructure that is being exposed for users to rent for their computing needs. This is not unlike the more traditional hard infrastructures such as the power grid or telephone networks. One major difference is that they are not boxed into "natural monopolies" like physical networks can be. With internet access, you can freely pick and choose.</p>

<p>The major infrastructures right now are owned by <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/">Amazon</a>, <a href="http://code.google.com/appengine/">Google</a> and <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windowsazure/">Microsoft</a>. There are others but these three seem to be generating the most interest at the moment. Each has a different model for how it exposes its infrastructure for use. Layered onto them are companies that have built service offerings on top of these infrastructures, not unlike how there are different kinds of transportation companies (car rental, taxis, courier services, overnight shipping, trucking companies, etc.) that use the transportation infrastructure. In the geospatial market, the ones that I have the most experience with are <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">WeoGeo</a>, <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a>, <a href="http://www.fortiusone.com">GeoCommons/GeoIQ</a> and <a href="http://www.esri.com">ESRI</a>. Like the cloud providers, each has a different approach for exposing geospatial data and tools via the cloud infrastructure.</p>

<p>The choice of cloud infrastructure and service provider can greatly affect workflow and also have widely varying costs so it's important to really dig in and understand the various permutations available and make the best choice for your organization. If you are considering moving your geospatial operations to "the cloud", it is worth taking time to understand the various cloud infrastructures, how they operate, and what the various service providers offer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
