<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ESRI International User Conference | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/esri-international-user-conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-24T13:25:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[See You at the UC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/16/see-you-at-the-uc/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/16/see-you-at-the-uc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have finalized my travel plans for San Diego to attend the ESRI User Conference this year. I will be spending most of my time on the exhibit floor working a booth. My company, <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah Technologies</a>, became a <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/gsa">GSA reseller</a> for <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> this year so Zekiah will have a joint booth with Arc2Earth.</p>

<p>I'll be there with Brian and Jack Flood and we'll have the newly-released Arc2Earth v3 on display. Come by booth 632 to see A2E Cloud Services (using Google's Cloud) in action as well as integration with <a href="http://www.arcgis.com/home/">ArcGIS.com</a> and a number of other features, including the new ability to export ArcGIS layer styles to <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/sld">SLD</a> (more on that in a future post). Don't forget the free A2E Community Edition. If you won't be at the UC, that's a great way to check out what it can do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[San Diego in August]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/05/26/san-diego-in-august/"/>
    <updated>2008-05-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/05/26/san-diego-in-august</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Beats the heck out of Washington in August.</p>

<p>I'll be doing booth duty most of the week at the <a href="http://esri.com/events/uc/">ESRI UC</a> this year. I'll be in booth 612 doing the old soft-shoe for <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a>. Feel free to stop by and say hello. I'm hoping there will be some good off-site meetups.</p>

<p>This trip will complete my 2008 ESRI conference trifecta (quad-fecta if you count the BP Conference/Dev Summit as two distinct events). I wear a lot of hats in my business and this conference is good for the business side. It'll be <em>really</em> hard to top the technical content of the Dev Summit (and I'm not expecting it) but, based on the Where 2.0 <a href="http://twitter.com">Twitter</a> buzz (and, yes, there was Where 2.0 Twitter buzz), I think there'll even more good stuff about 9.3. I'll probably blog in more detail in the near future but I think 9.3 may be the most significant ArcGIS release since 8.0.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
