<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Esri | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/esri/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-08T23:10:54-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Thoughts On the AppGeo Announcement]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/09/11/personal-thoughts-on-the-appgeo-announcement/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T20:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/09/11/personal-thoughts-on-the-appgeo-announcement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I read with great interest <a href="http://www.appgeo.com/blog/breaking-up-is-hard-to-do/">today's announcement that AppGeo is no longer an Esri Business Partner</a>. I find the announcement significant for a number of reasons, which I will explore shortly. I have always respected <a href="http://www.appgeo.com/">AppGeo's</a> work. As a small business that does geospatial consulting, they have foregone the "grow at all costs" approach that is seen all too often in the consulting world. They generally stuck to what they do well and branched out conservatively in ways that tie logically back to their core business.</p>

<p>I first met the President of AppGeo, Rich Grady, at an early <a href="https://www.hifldwg.org/">HIFLD</a> meeting many years ago. (It may have even been before the group was called "HIFLD.") The work they were doing then was very relevant to critical infrastructure protection efforts and, had some of their concepts for sharing data between state, local, and Federal agencies been adopted, we'd probably be better off today. I have always considered Rich one of the good guys in the geospatial industry and the company he has built reflects his integrity.</p>

<p>Over the years, our companies haven't quite found the right vehicle to work together and we sometimes even compete against each other. That's the nature of the consulting business. You will often compete against friends and still be able to have dinner together later.</p>

<p>So I was happy for Rich and AppGeo when I read their announcement. As I said above, I found it significant in a few ways...</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Professionalism</h2>

<p>The announcement was a textbook example of the professionalism with which such matters should be handled. AppGeo did not burn down the house in announcing they were no longer a business partner. There were no declarations that "Esri sucks" or any other such unnecessary hyperbole. They discussed real, significant differences that had evolved over time with Esri that lead to an agreement that their business interests had diverged to the point that a Business Partner status no longer made sense. While Esri initiated the final break, AppGeo handled it well, stated their case professionally, and gave no ground. Well done. This announcement should be required reading for the various factions and camps in our industry.</p>

<h2>A Sign of Maturity</h2>

<p>I found the announcement significant because I see it as evidence that AppGeo, as a geospatial business, has evolved to a point of maturity that most businesses never reach. They have built a diverse portfolio and realize they can go it alone without the safety net of Redlands under them. I will note that my company is an Esri Business Partner so I guess we haven't gotten there yet. I have worked as a consultant for my entire career and I believe to my bones that my primary job is to recommend the most appropriate solution to my customers. That is quite often an Esri solution for a lot of valid reasons, but not always. Right now, I am working on a project for a Federal agency based entirely on open-source geospatial tools. Often, a hybrid solution is really the best fit. The point is that, as a consultant, my job is to first gather data, analyze it, and determine the best solution. My job is not to walk in with a pre-conceived notion. If you call yourself a consultant and never look outside the Esri stable of tools (or whomever your preferred vendor may be), then you are not a consultant but a salesman. Just own it.</p>

<p>AppGeo recognizes this and has built a consulting practice that can proceed forward with less influence from large vendors. I commend them for that.</p>

<h2>Maturity of Open-Source Geospatial</h2>

<p>This next observation is statistically spurious as it is based only on this particular case, but I see this announcement as a sign of the increased maturity of the open-source geospatial segment. AppGeo is still a fairly small business, and many small consulting shops tend to be very conservative in their business moves. The fact that they are willing to decouple themselves from Esri indicates that they are not only confident in their capabilities with a diverse tool set, but that they are also confident in the stability and reliability of the tools in terms of being able to stake their business on them. Those of us who work with open-source geospatial tools are not surprised by this but it is important to note that AppGeo is as deeply proficient with the Esri tool suite as any company I've seen. I am not privy to their internal decision-making process but, at some point, a comparison must have yielded the conclusion that open-source tools (and Google) were sufficient to stand on equal footing in their capability portfolio. When a once-marquee partner like AppGeo reaches that conclusion, I find it significant.</p>

<p>Those represent some of my thoughts after reading the announcement. I recognized a lot in it but I can't say I've had all of the experiences they describe. I can't say that I've ever received any poor treatment from Esri as a Business Partner. I have heard enough stories from others that I don't doubt that it happens but I have never personally experienced it. Esri has always been exceedingly professional with me and my company. I don't feel like I've ever felt undue pressure to push their products to the front of the line but I recognize that my experience may be atypical.</p>

<p>In many ways, I expect all vendors to be partisan about their products, be it Esri or Microsoft or Oracle or Boundless or whomever. I would be suspicious if they weren't. Perhaps, because of that expectation, I've developed a bit of a filter for it but it doesn't bother me. My job as a consultant is to stand between my customers and the vendors and use my experience to sort through the market blather, find the real data, help my customers make an informed decision, and then help them implement. I have always felt that proficiency with a broad set of technologies makes me a better consultant, even for my strictly-Esri customers. AppGeo clearly understands this better than most and I commend them on reaching this significant and positive milestone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcWhat? I Just Want My Map.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/30/arcwhat-i-just-want-my-map/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T15:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/30/arcwhat-i-just-want-my-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>TL;DR:</h3>

<p>What follows is probably my last post related to the Esri User Conference and is highly Esri-centric. Open-source readers may want to jump off here, or exercise a willing suspension of disbelief.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/16/the-esri-uc-so-far/">A couple of posts ago</a>, I did something that I generally try to avoid. I took <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> to task for its confusing product names without really offering any thoughts on how to make things better. I don't really like it when people do that to me so I'll try to correct that here. It bears noting that I was not the only person feeling this way at the UC. I was happy to see <a href="http://www.directionsmag.com/articles/making-sense-of-the-2014-esri-international-user-conference/410201">Adena's post over at Directions</a> touch on this and it also came up in a number of conversations I had while I was in San Diego.</p>

<p>Here are some things that I think may help. They represent most of the stumbling blocks I typically encounter when doing consulting/integration with Esri-centric users, especially new ones.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/93/Spaghetti.jpg" /> <br/>
 <sub>"<a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Spaghetti.jpg#mediaviewer/File:Spaghetti.jpg">Spaghetti</a>". Licensed under <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" title="Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0<p></p>">CC BY-SA 3.0</a> via <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/">Wikimedia Commons</a>.<sub></p>

<!--more-->


<ol>
<li><p>Retire the "Arc" prefix - It's confusing to have a relatively meaningless and seemingly random (to new users) prefix attached to everying. If you are moving to a platform concept, shouldn't that platform just bear your name? The company is Esri, the platform should be "Esri GIS" or something. Don't hide from your own product line. "Arc" is a verbal stumbling block. Try telling a user how to publish a map online and see how many times you say "Arc." Is it any wonder they get confused? It's like the old dog food commercial, except all they hear is "Blah blah Arc blah Arc blah blah Arc."</p></li>
<li><p>Acknowledge four environments for the platform - Mobile, Desktop, Server, Online. Period. "Esri GIS Desktop" or "Esri GIS Server" for example. Clean up spurious products that just clutter the menu. The current Explorer? Esri GIS Mobile (resist the urge to tack on "for iOS"). The current Portal? Esri GIS Online (Online can offer a hosted or on-premise version). What's the distinction between Esri GIS Server and an on-premise instance of Esri GIS Online? I don't know. Those are your waters to unmuddy.</p></li>
<li><p>One Desktop - Basic? Standard? Advanced? How about just Desktop? After 15 or so years of selling the three tiers, you should have enough data on the sales mix to set one normalized price for a fully-functional desktop product and be done with it. I suspect that price would hover somewhere between the current prices of Basic and Standard, perhaps closer to Standard. Everybody pays one price, everybody gets the current Advanced product. If nothing else, that code base should have long since paid for itself. Then you'll be better positioned for the inevitable transition to Esri GIS Pro (which could really just be the next Esri GIS Desktop) that everyone sees coming. Need more? Buy extensions.</p></li>
<li><p>Speaking of Extensions - You can have too much of a good thing. Roll some of them into core products (like Spatial Analyst). Doing so will assure users that a common set of tools will be available as they move between the environments (see item number 2). Furthermore, stop calling everything an "extension," which exacerbates the need for cumbersome qualifiers like "for Desktop" and "for Server." Choose a standard nomenclature for each environment and stick with it. Desktop can have "extensions" and server can have "adapters," for example. Then I know that a discussion about the Network Analyst Adapter is focused on Server.</p></li>
<li><p>Stop changing product names - Take any of the suggestions above, or do something else entirely. But, whatever you do, leave it alone once you're done. At least for a couple of dot releases, anyway.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Slow Food]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/29/slow-food/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T09:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/29/slow-food</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 1985, I was a junior in high school and I got my first job at a local chain steakhouse. I ended up staying there for a few years and did everything, including management. This particular location happened to be the busiest store in the chain, which had a couple hundred locations at the time. Basically, we just unlocked the doors and people came in. We often had a line and managers from all over the country came to see how we did business.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://s3-media3.fl.yelpcdn.com/bphoto/NhIU66uSYbsi9LPzBpSgwA/l.jpg" /></p>

<p>Eventually, I transferred to another store that happened to be much slower. I expected this to be a something of a cakewalk compared to the store I had just left. Sometime during my first day, the long-time manager made a point to remind me to close the back dining room after lunch and turn the lights out. The dark room looked uninviting to me so I asked if we could leave the lights on. He replied that doing so would raise the electric bill and affect the store's profits. Over the next few weeks, I learned so many new techniques for managing food inventory, staffing levels, and equipment that I realized my initial impression was wrong. So I told the manager this. He was not surprised.</p>

<p>He said to me: "It takes more skill to run a slow store than a busy one."</p>

<!--more-->


<p>He was absolutely right. At the first location, we would simply order enough food to fill the walk-ins and did enough prep every day to fill the racks. We quickly ramped our staffing up to max levels every day and just waited for the customers to roll in. There was a myriad of issues we simply never had to worry about because sales volume masked them.</p>

<p>It's been many years since I've had to work in a restaurant but I have found this observation applicable throughout my career, during which I have worked primarily in the defense industry, designing and building various forms of geospatial tools and systems. Two weeks ago, I attended the Esri International User Conference. The Esri UC is full of opportunities to see more of these types of applications, from the Defense Showcase to the National Security Summit to many defense/intel/homeland security related paper sessions.</p>

<p>I attended almost none of them.</p>

<p>Over the past few years, I have developed the habit of attending sessions related to local governments, non-profits and other small organizations. These organizations tend to have budgets that are essentially rounding error in the defense world and I have become much more intrigued by the solutions they build to meet their missions with so few resources.</p>

<p>Of course, I was at an Esri conference, so everyone I saw was an Esri user. It's no secret that Esri tools tend to be expensive and every dollar counts for small governments, so I am intrigued how these organizations arrive at the choice of Esri tools in light of so many other capable options. Too often, there is a misconception that these small governments simply choose Esri-based solutions out of a lack of understanding of alternatives. What I have discovered is, like the manager of the slow restaurant, some of the best business understanding and most cogent and well-reasoned justifications come from these small users.</p>

<p>They seem to take a much more holistic approach to evaluating their solutions; including the availability of support from the technology provider as well as the existence of a robust third-party community that enables them to effectively compete for value-added services, customizations, and consulting. What I found interesting has been the most consistent attraction of local governments and small organizations to Esri-based solutions: the seamless integration of the entire ArcGIS platform. From mobile to desktop to web, they find that Esri tools make it easier to move through the product lifecycle. This exposes a very business-centric way of thinking that is larger than any individual technology or its licensing cost.</p>

<p>As I indicated above, an Esri conference places a huge filter on the users whom you meet. As I attend less vendor-centric events in the months ahead, I'd like to continue this line of inquiry. While landing the giant white whales of large Federal agencies might be more satisfying for the short-term bottom line, it is important to remember that all levels of government are facing downward budget pressure. Learning the thought processes of organizations that have always had to tightly manage limited resources may be more valuable in the long run.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Esri UC So Far #EsriUC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/16/the-esri-uc-so-far/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T12:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/16/the-esri-uc-so-far</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I'm halfway through the largest geospatial event of the year, attending it for the first time in four years, and I haven't blogged yet. As always, it's a busy week. Because this event draws people from all over the country (and world), my dance card fills up pretty quickly. And, by the way, there's a conference going on.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/plenary_stage.jpg" /></p>

<p>This is the first I've ever attended the Esri User Conference as just an attendee. If it were a video game, I'd be playing it on the easy level. I sat through the entire plenary for the first time in years. It was nice table setting for the rest of the week. As the father of a dancer, I have developed an eye for choreography and there is plenty of it up on the plenary stage. If I were to level one piece of constructive criticism toward the UC, it's that I'd let speakers be themselves a little bit more. That said, the content was delivered smoothly, which is really the larger point.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The plenary features a lot of demos that are rehearsed to within an inch of their lives. Knowing that, I still found ArcGIS Pro to be interesting. The UI is well-designed to get out the user's way and it's native 64-bit architecture finally allows it to take advantage of system resources in a way that ArcMap never could. The UI is more modern, featuring the ribbon toolbar. Esri seems to have learned a lesson from Microsoft by not re-engineering the UI of a familiar product, but releasing a new product that users can transition to. That was smart. In Microsoft Office terms, the UI upates from the Office 97 feel of ArcMap to more of an Office 2012 feel. Tasks in ArcGIS simplify geoprocessing even more but also run the risk of hiding complexity too much. I hope we're not training another generation of button-clickers.</p>

<p>One of the more subtle announcements in the plenary was that ArcGIS Portal will be included with ArcGIS Server at 10.3. I suspect that's the beginning of a gentle nudge of Server into ArcIMS-like oblivion but that's just my speculation.</p>

<p>The newly-released (not beta) ArcGIS Open Data extension (product?) was shown by <a href="http://twitter.com/ajturner">Andrew Turner</a>. It does a very nice job of putting an almost-GeoCommons-easy interface in front of ArcGIS Online to enable organizations to easily share their data. Andrew showed the implementations for the DC government and the State of Maryland. Maryland, in particular, is exceedingly happy with how quickly it has helped them start sharing data. By chance, I had dinner with some of the development team the night before and it's a motivated team with a diverse skill set not rooted in traditional Esri thinking which, in my opinion, bodes well for what they are doing.</p>

<p>Yesterday, I sat through a couple of sessions on the GeoEvent Processor (GEP), which has already been rebranded as the GeoEvent Extension for Server (or something like that). Those who have tracked my blog over the years know that I've done a lot of work with situational awareness systems. Within that field, I've concentrated a lot on feeds (streaming data sources) and track management so it's something of a geeky passion for me. Esri's previous, long-standing, and wholly awful product in this space was Tracking Server. I would gleefully dance around Tracking Server's funeral pyre.</p>

<p>GEP seems to be a better attempt at solving this problem. In its current incarnation, it simply doesn't have the throughput my customers will need (it currently supports about 800 - 1000 messages per second). To the product team's credit, they know this and are focusing on it. At 10.3, GEP will support "clustering" to increase throughtput. Clustering, however, was not explained during the session and could mean anything so I'll wait and see. The management interfaces and APIs behind GEP are top-notch and enable some of the use cases I've supported in the past. Once the throughput challenges are solved, this could be a product to watch.</p>

<p>You may have noticed a few parenthetical comments above when referring to product names. The reason for that is that Esri's product naming has fallen off the cliff to become just confusing, unwieldy, and random. Couple that with the fact that product names change constantly, or are recycled endlessly (Explorer?), and it's a complete mess. It's always been difficult walking new users through the maze of Esri products and the current naming "convention" doesn't help at all. Esri really needs to circle the wagons on this and simplify things.</p>

<p>That sums up my week so far. I'll try to check in again before I go.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gearing Up For the Esri UC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/09/gearing-up-for-the-esri-uc/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-09T16:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/09/gearing-up-for-the-esri-uc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With a house move behind us and a lot of unpacking and other tasks ahead, I am nonetheless getting ready to head out to the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/user-conference">Esri International User Conference</a> next week. This will be my first time attending since 2010 and is the first UC since then that has aligned with my schedule in a way that I can make it. Of course, the price is right this year as well ($0.00).</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/office_view.png" /></p>

<p>The "big" UC has steadily dropped in significance for me over years as it has become much easier to get Esri-related information through various other channels; primarily through social media and local/regional events such as the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/federal">FedUC</a> and local dev meetups. The last few trips to San Diego left me feeling that the content presented there is getting increasingly superficial compared to the other events. This year, however, I have been in the midst of building a house and moving so I have not had the time to attend the smaller events. As a result the UC makes sense. I am hoping the recent trend reverses itself.</p>

<p>I still do some Esri-based consulting so it's important to stay current however I can. My government customers are starting to at least ask about ArcGIS Online, so I want to finally get my mind around it as best I can. The messaging around that platform has been so muddled that it's still difficult for me to articulate what productivity advantages, if any, it actually offers. My own experimentation with it has left me wanting. The fact that it has been <a href="http://www.executivegov.com/2014/06/agriculture-dept-grants-fisma-certification-to-esri-cloud-mapping-tech/">certified as FISMA compliant</a> will certainly raise its profile with some of my Federal customers, though that's typically only the first step in a very long process. I'm also curious about ArcGIS Pro.</p>

<p>Unlike previous years, I won't be manning a booth (we sold ours a few years ago) or directly representing a customer so I'll actually have the luxury to attend sessions and meet up with people. There are some people who, unfortunately, I really only see face-to-face at such large magnet events so I'm looking forward to catching up with them, as well as meeting new people. I will, however, be popping into the paper session of one of my co-workers. (It would be awesome if the online agenda provided permalinks to individual sessions.)</p>

<p>So, if you're going to be in at the UC next week and would like to meet up, feel free to ping me on Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/billdollins">@billdollins</a>), via e-mail (bill [at] geomusings [dot] com), or drop a comment below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
