<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: local | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/local/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-28T08:22:22-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Try Some Local Fare]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/28/try-some-local-fare/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/28/try-some-local-fare</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, Randal Hale <a href="http://www.northrivergeographic.com/archives/1259">posted an announcement</a> about the upcoming Southern Appalachian Conference on GIS to be held at East Tennessee State University. I have never attended that conference and probably won't this year but, if you live and work in that area, you may want to check it out. <!--more--></p>

<p>Why? Well, I don't know yet because they are still accepting abstracts for papers so it's hard to know what the content will be. But I'm coming to the close of a 12 month period in which I only attended one "big" conference (the Esri FedUC). All other such outings were either regional conferences (<a href="http://www.gisintherockies.org/GISITR2011/Home/Default.aspx">GIS in the Rockies</a>, <a href="http://www.ncgicc.com/CurrentActivities/NCGISConference/tabid/158/Default.aspx">North Carolina GIS</a>) or our local unconference, <a href="http://www.wherecampdc.org/">WhereCampDC</a>.</p>

<p>These conferences, along with my recent work with the <a href="http://www.gis.arkansas.gov/">Arkansas GIO</a> office, have given me a greater appreciation of the innovation that goes on at a local level. Admittedly, my years of working at the Federal level may have hopelessly skewed my perception but I am finding that the conflicting conditions of reduced resources and increased requirements create a powerful crucible in which unique solutions to real-world problems can emerge. There's not a lot of pie-in-the-sky <a href="http://www.mitre.org/work/tech_papers/tech_papers_07/07_0093/">UDOP</a> (re)development happening there.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/06/steamed_crabs_small.png"><img alt="Maryland Steamed Crabs" height="288" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/06/steamed_crabs_small.png" title="Maryland Steamed Crabs" width="512" /></a><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Much like food, the best GIS is local.<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>I saw more innovation in one day in Charlotte than I did in five days in San Diego. Perhaps the same will be true in Johnson City. It's hard to say. So I'll leave it at this: get off the beaten path. Whether it's Johnson City or <a href="http://www.rocketcitygeospatial.com/site/overview/">Huntsville</a> or Loveland or someplace else, there's probably a regional event happening within a day's drive of wherever you are. Go to it. See what's happening, what challenges people are facing, and how they are applying/integrating GIS (or whatever it's called these days) to address them.</p>

<p>You might just be happy you did.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
