<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cool flag | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/cool-flag/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-17T14:50:22-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off to TUGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/18/off-to-tugis/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T12:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/18/off-to-tugis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow, I'll be heading up to the <a href="http://www.towson.edu/tugis/">Towson University GIS (TUGIS) conference</a> with 500 or so of my closest Maryland geo-friends. It has been restructured into a one-day event and the program seems to be very content-rich as a result. I am particularly happy to see more open-source content this year. There's an intro session featuring <a href="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</a>, <a href="http://www.postgis.org">PostGIS</a>, <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a>, and <a href="http://geoserver.org">GeoServer</a> presented by <a href="http://www.salisbury.edu/">Salisbury State University</a>. Salisbury was once known as a bastion of <a href="http://www.manifold.net/">Manifold</a> so they've got a long history of thinking outside the Arc. Additionally, there is a session (by Towson University) discussing the use of <a href="http://www.gdal.org">GDAL</a>, <a href="http://www.gdal.org/ogr/">OGR</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/sgillies/shapely">Shapely</a> in the development of a spatial service.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/mdflag.png" alt="Brian Timoney's favorite state flag" title="Brian Timoney's favorite state flag" /></p>

<p>One thing I like about regional GIS conferences like this is that they tend to focus more on solutions to real-world problems instead of the latest technological bells and whistles. I spend so much of my time with my head in Federal requirements that it's nice do a reset and get different perspectives on how geospatial technologies are used. I am particularly interested to hear the keynote from <a href="http://twitter.com/learondalby">Learon Dalby</a> of <a href="http://www.sanborn.com/">Sanborn</a> and formerly of the <a href="http://www.gis.state.ar.us/">Arkansas GIO office</a>. I had the pleasure of working with Learon and the AGIO team on a project a couple of years ago and am impressed with what they accomplished.</p>

<p>I appreciate the new format of TUGIS as a one-day event is much easier to fit into the schedule. I'm looking forward to it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
