<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: where did that come from? | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/where-did-that-come-from-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-19T14:49:16-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mowers and Maps]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/18/mowers-and-maps/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/18/mowers-and-maps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was mowing the lawn today and trimming with the push mower pictured below. If it looks old, that's because it is. I first acquired it in 1978 when it was given to me by neighbors that were moving to an apartment near the city, meaning they no longer needed it. It still starts on the third pull and I've used it every summer since it was given to me.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2823" height="360" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/mower.jpeg" title="They don&#039;t make them like this anymore" width="640" /></p>

<p>As I was mowing, I thought about how old the mower is and how it came to be in my possession. This led me to think about the origin of my fascination with maps. What does one have to do with the other? Allow me to explain.</p>

<p>As you can imagine, I was fairly young when the lawn mower was given to me. I had gotten to know the neighbors up the street by playing with their son. One day, I noticed a large shelf of identical, leather-bound books taking up the entire back wall of a room. I asked what they were and they invited me to browse them. It turned out that my neighbor was the son of a long-time chair of the National Geographic Society. These books were actually bound collections, by year, of every issue of National Geographic from the first issue on.</p>

<p>Over time, I would spend hours poring through these volumes, fascinated by the world as it was documented by National Geographic from 1888 forward. I did not get to read every issue but I was especially drawn to the maps when they were present. I realize now that my identity as a "map nerd" took root there.</p>

<p>Coincidentally, 1978 was the year I first started programming. Those two experiences turned out to be major influences on who I became.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ten-Second Tidy]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/12/10/ten-second-tidy/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/12/10/ten-second-tidy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things have been a bit hectic the last few weeks and that's left little time for blogging. Quite a bit has happened so I thought I'd do a little round-up (if for no other reason than to clear my own head).</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/cJa7P6dfmco?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>In no particular order:</p>

<p><strong>Steve Coast to Microsoft</strong> (I told you it had been a while) - Firstly, congratulations to Steve (#sincerity).  Secondly, this clearly is the final proof that crowd-sourced data in general, and OpenStreetMaps (sic) in particular, <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/09/16/be-the-crowd/">has no real value when compared to "authoritative" data sources</a> (#sarcasm).</p>

<p><strong>Google Fusion Tables</strong> - The only real problem at this point is the size limitation but, otherwise, this will be a game-changer for storing and sharing data. In its current form, it's already fairly easy to push your data up and expose it through Google's APIs. It'll be interesting to see if it gets easier. Support for spatial queries hints at some analytical capability, too. Speaking of which...</p>

<p><strong>Analytics in GeoCommons</strong> - This is one to watch. They are debuting a new function each day <a href="http://blog.fortiusone.com/2010/12/06/the-12-analytics-of-christmas/">on their blog</a>. FortiusOne builds their platform API-first, UI-second so everything they are showing should be exposed through their APIs. This will be a huge step in moving cloud-based geospatial technology from the "bit-bucket" stage to having a more complete workflow on the cloud infrastructure.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Arc2Earth Data Services and Arc2Cloud</strong> - Continuing the theme of building a complete workflow, <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> is working on exposing a <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/services/data-services/">complete range of Google geospatial services</a> to ArcGIS Desktop users. It's no secret that I'm a fan of Arc2Earth (and <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">my company</a> is a reseller), but this represents a big expansion of capability. Google's cloud infrastructure works differently that Amazon's and I think what <a href="http://beta.arc2cloud.com/">Arc2Earth is doing</a> is important because it will open up another channel for users and enable them to <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/clouds/">make choices based on their needs and requirements</a>.</p>

<p><strong>WeoGeo</strong> - <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">These guys</a> never sit still either. They've got some changes coming up that will greatly increase flexibility for managing spatial data on a cloud infrastructure. Taken together with the previous two entries on GeoCommons and Arc2Earth, I see a lot of innovation in cloud-based GIS really being driven by small, focused companies. This is not simply "push your server to an AMI and keep working." (Although that approach can have some utility.) Each of these companies is trying to figure out how to leverage the unique capabilities of cloud infrastructures to build new workflows and expand capability for users. And, it's important to note, they are making headway.</p>

<p><strong>WhereCampDC</strong> - Obviously, judging from the <a href="http://wherecampdc.org/">web site</a>, it's still in the early planning stages but I'm excited by the idea. This is exactly the kind of independent event that this area needs. I have always been baffled by the lack of such events in this area, especially given the level of geospatial activity around here.</p>

<p><strong>Google Earth 6</strong> - The <a href="http://www.google.com/earth/index.html">latest release</a> confirms that StreetView has yet to drive my street. For that I am happy.</p>

<p><strong>FOSS4G</strong> - The conference doesn't happen until next September and already the buzz is building. I have had people that I know have yet to touch an open-source GIS tool ask me what I know about "that <a href="http://foss4g.org/static/index.html">conference</a> I'm hearing about in Denver."</p>

<p><strong>Silverlight</strong> - I can't think of a technology in recent years that has given me more of a feeling of ambivalence. It has great capability and the Esri Silverlight API team has done good work building on it (this piece addresses Silverlight, not the Esri API). I think it'll continue to be a fine technology for intranet development but I'll leave it there. I don't expect my work with it to wind down anytime soon so I'll keep blogging it as I think it's perfectly possible to be productive with Silverlight within certain parameters. <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/10/30/rip-silverlight-on-the-web/">The whole episode regarding its future</a> (which was something of a tempest in a teapot, in reality) simply highlights the risks involved in relying on closed, proprietary technologies. This time, it was Silverlight, but make no mistake, the same risks are there with Flex/Flash (it just runs on more browser/OS combinations). Of course, there are risks with <em>any</em> technology choice but it's nice when those risks do not include "whim."</p>

<p>So that's it for my odds and ends. It's good to get them stuffed back into the couch. 2010 has been an interesting year. It almost feels like a year in which groundwork is being laid. It may just be me, but I have a feeling of anticipation similar to what I feel right before the first daffodils appear in Spring. It just feels like there's a good bit of pent-up energy and that a lot of new things are about to spring forth. It could be loads of fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quilted Map of Monongahela National Forest]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/05/18/quilted-map-of-monongahela-national-forest/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/05/18/quilted-map-of-monongahela-national-forest</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found this map on display at the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cranberry_Glades">Cranberry Glades</a> <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=38.203056,+-80.266389&amp;sll=37.0625,-95.677068&amp;sspn=38.41771,79.013672&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=38.202576,-80.266113&amp;spn=0.596777,1.234589&amp;z=10">visitor center</a> in West Virginia (click any of the pictures to enlarge them):</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/img_2429.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-903" height="225" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/img_2429.jpg?w=300" title="Map of Monongahela National Forest" width="300" /></a></p>

<p>One of the rangers working there told me it is to scale (although the quilt itself lacks any indication of scale).</p>

<p>The next two pictures are close-ups showing the north arrow and the use of buttons as place markers. The kids we are traveling with were fascinated by this map. You will notice a red box over a portion of the forest. That was the area covered by a relief map on a table elsewhere in the visitor center.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/img_2430.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-904" height="225" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/img_2430.jpg?w=300" title="Buttons as place markers" width="300" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/img_2431.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-905" height="225" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/img_2431.jpg?w=300" title="Quilted north arrow" width="300" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy GIS Day 2009]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/17/happy-gis-day-2009/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/17/happy-gis-day-2009</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-740" height="265" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2009/11/great_map.png" title="It's the Great Map" width="257" /></p>

<p>GIS Day is when the Great Map renders from its cache and slips around the world giving GPS units to all the good geographers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does Vendor Lock-In Increase Health-Care Costs?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/14/does-vendor-lock-in-increase-health-care-costs/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/11/14/does-vendor-lock-in-increase-health-care-costs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is World Diabetes Day. I am a parent of a child with Type 1 diabetes (also known as juvenile diabetes). As such, my child is dependent upon insulin and will be until a cure is found. I am using my blog today to discuss the issue of interoperability (or lack thereof) of medical devices.<!--more--></p>

<p>My child is primarily dependent upon two medical devices for diabetes management. The first is a blood glucose meter which is used to check blood sugar. The second is an insulin pump which maintains a suitable basal rate of insulin and also helps cover carbohydrate intake at meals. Both devices produce a fair amount of data  that allows us to see what is happening with blood glucose levels and help us make adjustments to keep things going smoothly.</p>

<p>We have a fairly typical setup in which neither of these devices talks to each other so we download data from them into software on our computer. Over the past decade, interoperability has been a leading issue in the geospatial industry. As such, it has made me sensitive to it in other areas, most notably in diabetes management. What I have come to realize is that there is very little in the way of true interoperability in this area and I think it is potentially very relevant to the current discussions of reducing health-care costs. Our case serves as an example:</p>

<p>Each of the devices we use comes with its own software. The software for the glucose monitor allows us to hook the devices up to a USB port and download all of the blood glucose information they contain (we use more than one, all from the same vendor). The insulin pump has a different piece of software that allow us to download information to examine basal rates and boluses in conjunction with blood glucose. It also downloads the meal-time glucose numbers. In order to properly cover for a meal, you must tell the pump what your current glucose is so that information is available for download. The complexity begins here.</p>

<p>Good management of diabetes requires glucose checks throughout the day, not just at mealtime. In order to get a complete picture of what is going on, you must download from the glucose monitor to see all of the information. Our insulin pump software provides the ability to hook up our monitor and download information directly. This gives us that complete picture. The glucose meter software does not allow download from any insulin pumps. It must be entered manually (ugh) or imported from a CSV file. It expects the CSV to be formatted in a way that is not supported by our insulin pump software.</p>

<p>The insulin pump software does not support two of the type of meters that we use, so we cannot download that information into it. What this implies is that, although all of our glucose monitors are from the same vendor, their firmware is sufficiently different to indicate that nothing resembling a standard interface is used. If I use the software for the glucose monitor, I can install a driver update to support new devices from the vendor. These driver updates are not recognized by the insulin pump software.</p>

<p>Why do we use both pieces of software? The glucose monitor software is the only way to get a full picture of the glucose readings. The insulin pump software provides better statistical analysis tools. I need them both and that is my problem. I should be able to simply plug in each device and upload to either piece of software (or some other if I wish). This is a quite solvable problem but the vendors lack any incentive because you become dependent upon their tools.</p>

<p>Over time, devices from different vendors leapfrog each other in capability. A new glucose monitor requires less blood, a new pump gives you more ways to tune basal rates, etc. As you do what is best for your child and get the best devices available, you are faced with the problem of importing and exporting your historical diabetes data between different pieces of software. The importance of this data is such that it can cause people to stick with a single vendor regardless of the cost or effectiveness of the devices.</p>

<p>The interoperability issue concerns me more as closed-loop systems begin to hit the market. These are systems in which the monitor and the pump do talk to each other (usually via signalling) and work together. Some systems feature new continuous glucose monitoring devices (CGM) that constantly sample blood glucose and message the pump to make adjustments. Many of these systems are still waiting for approval. CGMs are new and have issues but we can expect the technology to mature. The leap-frogging process will continue. The problem with closed-loop systems is that I have only seen them discussed in terms of single-vendor solutions. Vendor A's CGM will work in concert with Vendor A's pump but I have seen no evidence that, if Vendor B produces a better CGM, it will be able to work in the closed-loop system. I see this as having the potential to reduce patient choice, suppress demand, reduce negotiating power with vendors and keep costs artificially high.</p>

<p>In the community in which I work my "day job", we think about these issues a lot. I think I was somewhat surprised to see how little these issues seem to be considered in the health industry. Because we deal with diabetes every day, I tend to look at it through that lens but I can imagine that it is pervasive elsewhere. I think this is an area that can and should be looked at as something that has the potential to reduce costs independent of health insurance and the more hotly contested topics in the current debate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
