<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: where did that come from? | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/where-did-that-come-from-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-18T12:13:04-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[April Fool - Ancient GIS Discovered]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/04/01/April-Fool-Ancient-GIS-Discovered/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/04/01/April-Fool-Ancient-GIS-Discovered</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Researchers working at the base of Mount Ararat in Eastern Turkey have discovered the remnants of what appears to an ancient map-based navigation system that is being called the "world's first GIS." The presence of the artifact, which has been dubbed "ArkMap", at the base of mountain is seen as further evidence that Ararat was indeed the resting place of Noah's Biblical ark.<!--more--></p>

<p>The mechanical device seems to have been supported by what appears to be the ancient equivalent of a database that includes such items a comprehensive collection of depth soundings and well as information on the habitats of various animal species that were common at the time. It is interesting to note that the database appears to contain no information about landmarks.</p>

<p>The data has survived due to the fact that it was encoded onto to bronze plates in a manner that seems to indicate that a strong electrical current was used. "Given the technology of the time, it is a mystery how this was accomplished." said Dr. Una Balatro, leader of the research team. "It's hard to imagine anything short of lightning being able to do this."</p>

<p>The data was uniquely encoded in a complex series of two-by-two matrices. The researchers have not fully uncovered how the matrices were linked to each other but as Dr. Balatro put it: "two-by-two seemed to be a big thing for them."</p>

<p>Also found at the site were fragments of what appears to be a stone tablet with a map engraved on it. It is the first evidence that ancient navigators may have used tablets for mapping and charting. "It appears that they used information from the database to mark up the basemap on the tablet with some form of ink, which could be easily removed as needed." said Dr. Balatro.</p>

<p>More information on the discovery can be found <a href="http://is.gd/3BW">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nearest Book]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/11/17/Nearest-Book/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/11/17/Nearest-Book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This meme is percolating across the internets and it's kinda fun.</p>

<blockquote>By definition then, the terrorists and their followers become excluded from civil society of the mainstream, while the sympathetic public remains included.</blockquote>


<p><em>The Geographical Dimensions of Terrorism</em>, edited by Susan L. Cutter, Douglas B. Richardson and Thomas J. Wilbanks.</p>

<p><strong>The instructions</strong>: Grab the nearest book. Open it to page 56. Find the fifth sentence. Post the text of the sentence in your journal along with these instructions. Don?t dig for your favorite book, the cool book, or the intellectual one: pick the CLOSEST.</p>

<p>If I hadn't cleaned my desk on Friday, it would've most likely been something about Test-Driven Development but I did so this one was closest today which is interesting since it's been ages since I read it. This particular excerpt comes from a passage describing the two primary audiences of terrorists and the social/physical separation of those audiences. It is taken from the section titled "Geographies of Inclusion/Exclusion" by Colin Flint.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lyrical Revisionism]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/04/09/Lyrical-Revisionism/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/04/09/Lyrical-Revisionism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"Buy the sky and
Sell the sky and
Lift your arms up to the sky
And ask the sky
And ask the sky
Don't fall on me"</p>

<p>Did REM predict carbon trading in 1986?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First ArcGIS 9.4 Screenshot]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/03/31/First-ArcGIS-94-Screenshot/"/>
    <updated>2008-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/03/31/First-ArcGIS-94-Screenshot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You saw it here first...</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img alt="ArcGIS 9.4 circa 1 April 2008" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2008/03/arcgis94.png" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quote of the Day...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/03/28/Quote-of-the-Day/"/>
    <updated>2008-03-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/03/28/Quote-of-the-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Abe Gillespie had the quote of the day in his latest <a href="http://abegillespie.blogspot.com/2008/03/ziggis-update.html">post</a> about <a href="http://code.google.com/p/ziggis">zigGIS</a>.</p>

<p>In describing the development approach (disclaimer: I have been known to dabble in the zigGIS code from time to time although it's been the Abe show recently), Abe described it as "software 2.0" which, in his words, "doesn't mean much, but mostly we're not responsible to deadlines."</p>

<p>That alone was worth firing up the aggregator today. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
