<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mapobjects | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/mapobjects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-20T12:01:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SharpMap and WPF]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/08/14/sharpmap-and-wpf/"/>
    <updated>2007-08-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/08/14/sharpmap-and-wpf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I blogged about the <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2007/07/09/mo-no-mo/">end of the line for MapObjects</a>. I waxed nostalgic about how fun it was to develop with MO and how, although I haven't used it in a while, I'll still be sad to see it go.</p>

<p>Well, I'm glad I'm over that! I been working with <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/SharpMap">SharpMap</a> for the last few weeks and I'm feeling that old MO vibe again. It started a few weeks ago with developing a data provider for SQLite (<a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2007/07/31/extending-sharpmap-with-sqlite/">read here</a>) but I've continued to look under the hood.</p>

<p>Lately, I've been working a project where we need to feed some spatial data into native <a href="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/netframework/aa663326.aspx">WPF</a> display. WPF offers high performance and great graphics quality. In addition, there are numerous other types of data involved that also need to be displayed. We didn't want dedicated display components for each type of data so we decided to bring the spatial data into WPF.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I started looking at SharpMap because it gives us quite a few data options, has a robust geometry model and also includes a decent set of spatial operations. In addition, it's open source and free. The open source nature of SharpMap was a huge plus and I'm having fun doing things that I always wanted to do in MO. One thing is extend it support a new data source (ala SQLite). Another thing is to redirect layer rendering elsewhere.</p>

<p>SharpMap includes ASP.NET 2.0 and Winforms 2.0 controls. It features rendering objects that are distinct from the UI on which they are rendering. It's a model that allows for great flexibility.</p>

<p>In my current project, I am collaborating with a group outstanding developers working different pieces who already had a strong application framework in place. There already existed rendering and display components so I just had to extend those to understand geometry objects coming out of SharpMap. Being open source, it was really easy to dig under the hood to see what the objects were doing so I could integrate better.</p>

<p>So I read from the database, create the geometry objects and then feed them into a renderer that transforms them to screen space and converts them to WPF geometries for rendering. Pretty straightforward and, at a high level, exactly what you would do in COM and WinForms but still kinda neat given that I don't need an AxMapControl or some such other thing to pull off a free-standing app.</p>

<p>This is where I would normally post some code but I just got it working and my code is a) still ugly and b) still intertwined with a lot of other people's code. Once I get it cleaned up some, I can post some samples. But here's a little map...</p>

<p><img alt="WPF Canvas" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/08/wpf_sharpmap.png" /></p>

<p>This depicts one layer loaded into a WPF canvas control. It's still a little skewed and need some other work but I was excited to see it on the screen. It's been a while since I've had to deal with the nitty gritty of device rendering. <a href="http://www.esri.com">ESRI</a> always handled that for me :D</p>

<p>It's been quite fun coming up to speed on two APIs with which I'm not terribly familiar (SharpMap and WPF). Again, the SharpMap source code was a lifesaver. It didn't have anything to help with WPF <em>per se</em> but it was great reference as I was trying figure out behaviors. If you browse the <a href="http://sharpmapv2.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/">SVN trunk for SharpMap 2.0</a>, you'll see that they're planning to handle WPF but there's no code there yet. I can't wait see what they com up with. Anyway, here's one for the SharpMap team...</p>

<p><img alt="The beer you?ve been practicing for." src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/08/guinness.jpg" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MO No Mo']]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/07/09/mo-no-mo/"/>
    <updated>2007-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/07/09/mo-no-mo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, there's nothing terribly surprising about ESRI's announcement regarding <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/mapobjects/index.html">MapObjects</a> in this <a href="http://support.esri.com/index.cfm?fa=knowledgebase.techarticles.articleShow&amp;d=31074">technical article</a>. I would have been more surprised if they had announced that it <em>would</em> be supported or that there would be another version or something like that. In truth, I haven't touched MapObjects in years. It was dead to me even if it was still on life support at ESRI. But there was something about seeing it in print:</p>

<blockquote>MapObjects Windows 2.4 and MapObjects-Java 2.2 and 2.3 are not supported on the Windows Vista. ESRI is not certifying any new environments for MapObjects-Windows and there are no plans to support Vista with MapObjects-Java.</blockquote>


<p>It brought back a lot of memories. I began programming when I was 10. I wrote a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_and_dragons">D&amp;D</a> character generator in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BASIC_programming_language">BASIC</a> on a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commodore_64">Commodore 64</a>. I guess that makes me an old geek. D&amp;D and computers might even be a double-down. ;-)? I've pretty much been doing some form of BASIC ever since (not so much VB.Net anymore, though, as I do most of my .Net in C#) along with a lot of other languages. I got interested in maps a few years later and discovered I could fuse maps and computers as I headed into the workforce.</p>

<p>Early on, I was able to do some <a href="http://extranet.mapinfo.com/products/Overview.cfm?productid=1063">MapBasic</a> stuff but that didn't get too far. So I suffered through AML and Avenue for a while in order to feed the GIS development jones. Then along came MO.</p>

<p>With MO, I was able to introduce an old friend (BASIC in the form of VB5 and later VB6) to a new friend (GIS, although it wasn't new to me by then). I was able to write real apps that fused mapping with databases and other cool tools. For one customer, I built a COM system that featured a core UI and provided a pluggable architecture and an API so others could write plug-ins. Then we converted a lot of stand-alone apps to work in the system. Sounds familiar huh?</p>

<p>From a GIS standpoint, MO wasn't the most powerful game in town but it was <em>fun</em>! And, if you needed an algorithm or something that MO didn't support, you could just implement it yourself in the language of your choice. There are operations that I originally implemented in MO/VB6 that I have migrated and still use in C#/ArcObjects/Others. In case I didn't get the point across earlier, it was just plain fun.</p>

<p>That was a while ago. GIS is still fun but I just don't use MO anymore (maybe that's the problem). ESRI's announcement is sort of like when you read that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_Centre">the arena where you went to all of your concerts in your youth got dynamited to make room for a shopping plaza</a>. So, much like I did that day, I'll pop a cold one, raise a glass and say "Thanks for the memories."</p>

<p><img alt="The better part of my hearing was left here." src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/07/cap_centre.png" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
