<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: FedUC | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/feduc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-21T07:51:53-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ESRI Federal GIS Conference Wrap-up]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/25/ESRI-Federal-GIS-Conference-Wrap-up/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/25/ESRI-Federal-GIS-Conference-Wrap-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After arriving a little late on Day 2 due to needing to push updates to an application we're building for an NGO, I was able to catch most of the session about deploying ArcGIS Server in the cloud. James was sitting in the front and has <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2012/02/23/the-business-case-for-arcgis-in-da-cloud/" target="_blank">already blogged that session</a> so I won't go into detail about it here. One thing that did jump out at me came during the Q&amp;A, when someone asked about certification and accreditation (C&amp;A) of AWS deployments.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="alignnone" height="419" src="http://www.visitingdc.com/images/washington-dc-convention-center.jpg" title="Washington Convention Center" width="620" /></p>

<p>If you work in the Federal space, you know that C&amp;A is a huge issue for the deployment of any information system, regardless of platform, for the Federal Government. Since hosted deployments essentially mean outsourcing your physical infrastructure, information security types have understandably proceeded with caution here. <!--more--></p>

<p>To be quite frank, C&amp;A is an issue that ESRI has historically treated superficially at best. It has been viewed as something for integrators to work out despite the fact that there are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Information_Security_Management_Act_of_2002" target="_blank">FISMA</a> implications at the platform level as well. I am happy to say that seems to have changed. As I mentioned toward the end of my <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/23/esrifedcon-day-one-users-will-be-happy/">previous post</a>, ESRI seems to possess a much more mature and holistic understanding of the issues that drive Federal IT acquisition. This was on display here as the ESRI staff running the session provided intelligent answers regarding levels of FISMA compliance as well as the existence/creation of baseline C&amp;A packages that can help jump start <a href="http://iase.disa.mil/diacap/" target="_blank">DIACAP</a> accreditation. Due to time constraints, they didn't get into a lot of detail but it was clear there is now a deeper understanding of C&amp;A issues within ESRI.</p>

<p>I also attended the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/fedcon/agenda/dev-geo.html">DevGeo</a> segment on ArcGIS Runtime. This technology, which is different than I had expected in many ways, seems to finally plug a gap that has existed in the ESRI platform since the sunsetting of MapObjects. There is once again an easily deployable way to embed ESRI mapping capability into an application. The reality is that there's still a huge demand for desktop applications out there. Over the last two years, I have personally seen increased demand for various desktop tools as the majority of the development community has moved to the web. The ArcGIS Runtime demo I saw during the session already demonstrates that it can plug a serious performance issue that one of my customers is currently having with an in-vehicle application.</p>

<p>The quick hits that jumped out at me: easy deployment model, lack of COM dependencies, native 64-bit support on Linux and Windows while also retaining 32-bit support on Windows, Linux support, and the ability to safely deploy Runtime applications side-by-side with older versions of ArcGIS. These reasons alone move it ahead of ArcGIS Engine in my consideration of tools to use when developing ESRI-centric applications.</p>

<p>I also attended the session on the <a href="http://www.hifldwg.org" target="_blank">HIFLD</a> working group. This was something of a 10-year retrospective on the group that included a series of lightning talks about current efforts across participating agencies. I was in the room for the first meeting back in 2002 and <a href="http://www.zekiah.com" target="_blank">my company</a> continues to support it to this day. Today, it's primarily noted for for coordinating requirements for <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IEhjN2y-o54" target="_blank">HSIP</a> (video link). HSIP does have some issues, <a href="http://www.epcupdates.org/2011/09/nga-release-homeland-security.html" target="_blank">fairly accurately portrayed here</a>, but the support team is making a good-faith effort to move to a more collaborative model while also trying to balance the often-competing priorities of the various stakeholders. It's not been easy and progress has been incremental but it's been a quiet, if qualified, success story so far in terms of applying GIS to homeland security issues.</p>

<p>After that session, I headed out to the social. By this, I don't mean the official social at the Air and Space Museum. While this was an ESRI conference, ESRI tools are not the only ones I use. Due to the fact that the Federal GIS Conference draws an increasing number of geospatial users from around the country, an informal gathering has taken place at <a href="http://www.lovethebeer.com/rfd.html" target="_blank">RFD</a> over the last few years. This gathering typically includes not only conference attendees but also people with other DC-area geospatial companies such as <a href="http://www.geoiq.com" target="_blank">GeoIQ</a>. Some people attend the ESRI event and drop by RFD later. What usually results is a good mix of discussion. I have come to realize that I value these types of gatherings as a way to reconnect with people I don't get to see often, meet new people, and generally recharge my batteries. This informal gathering gives me a chance to throw a lot of different things into my melting pot and let them stew for a bit. I have come to view it as being almost as valuable as the conference itself.</p>

<p>I didn't attend the last day because two days out of the office leaves a lot to catch up on. I was happy to catch up with everyone (far too numerous to name here) and look forward to the chance to do so again in the near future. For those who had to travel to DC to attend, I wish you safe travels home.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Esrifedcon Day One Users Will Be Happy]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/23/EsriFedCon-Day-One-Users-Will-Be-Happy/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/23/EsriFedCon-Day-One-Users-Will-Be-Happy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I didn't catch the first half of the Esri Federal GIS Conference plenary but James did a <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2012/02/22/the-esri-federal-gis-conference-plenary/" target="_blank">good recap of it on his blog</a>. I did, however, catch the second half and the opening of the exhibit hall.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/feduc2.png"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-2499" height="359" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/feduc2.png" title="feduc2" width="640" /></a><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">GIS letters from the road<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>This year was a departure from previous years in that it wasn't a litany of the new things coming in each component of the Esri stack. The "GIS letters from the road" theme drew attention to problems that can be solved by leveraging the entire stack as a unit. It was a good twist that made it impossible to just drop in, hear about your favorite Esri product, and drop out. I have to give kudos to Esri's marketing team for taking it in this direction. <!--more--></p>

<p>Overall, what I saw with 10.1 is that end users will be very happy. The whole user experience is smoother and just easier to use for end users. Some of what I saw was capability that has been around for quite some time but not presented to the user very well. Others, such as the drag-and-drop imagery handling is capability that eliminates work that technicians used to invest a lot of time into. Esri has really stepped up to automate a lot of bread-and-butter geoprocessing and include it in the core products as standard capability.</p>

<p>Some of things I saw, such as the entire situational awareness demo, didn't show anything that I hadn't seen implemented by consultants and business partners in the past. In fact, the entire capability of the situational awareness demo was very close to something I built for an ops center in 2003. Additionally, niche capabilities such as drag-and-drop CSVs are things that would have once been left to business partners.</p>

<p>So, what's different? Esri understands their customer better now; especially the Federal government. A world where an organization needs to take a balkanized approach to building the full capability they need, with a core stack from Esri and a bunch of add-on extensions from business partners, is a procurement nightmare for Federal organizations. The fact that such third-party tools sit outside of an ELA doesn't help. The end result is a less-than-satisfactory experience for users and perhaps a lot of unnecessary in-house development to avoid additional procurement. So, stuff all of this user-friendly capability into the core product and move on. I actually don't have much of a problem with that.</p>

<p>All of this will be great for Esri and its end users. It might be less great for GIS technicians and certain kinds of business partners. With regard to analysts, all was not dark. Geoprocessing packages are a very powerful tool to encapsulate custom GIS analysis methods into standardized, repeatable processes that can be executed by end users. See that? End users again. If you're an experienced analyst who understands complex spatial modeling techniques, there's a bright future being the go-to person for such things. The technicians who did all the mundane data prep might want to start touching up their resumes, however.</p>

<p>What I saw yesterday leads me to the same conclusion for both analysts and business partners: the ones who will thrive will be those who have a deep understanding of a vertical domain to which GIS can be applied. What I didn't see yesterday was a big push by Esri to get into the various verticals. This makes sense as is it would quickly spread them too thin. Business partners who made a living building generic add-on tools to plug gaps in ArcGIS probably have a limited time left. Business partners who really understand something like climate modeling, solar panel placement optimization, wildlife migration patterns, oil and gas exploration or a host of other vertical disciplines and understand how to apply GIS to them and build tools on top of the ArcGIS platform to support them will probably have nothing to worry about.</p>

<p>The same goes for analysts. Current GIS analysts with deep experience will continue to be in demand. If, however, you are currently in college with the idea of being a "GIS Analyst", I strongly advise you to switch to another discipline and work toward becoming an analyst within that discipline who happens to know how use GIS as a tool.</p>

<p>What about developers? Between all of the platforms on which ArcGIS is running and all of the tools needed in the various vertical domains, I think things will be wide open for quite some time. And, as the demos yesterday showed, there's a lot of value in being the person who can write the code that turns imagery preparation into a drag-and-drop process.</p>

<p>What I saw yesterday was that Esri understands the value of the infrastructure they have put in place and that they also possess a mature, holistic understanding of their user base and are now happy to step on the gas pedal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Esri Fed Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/21/Esri-Fed-Conference/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/21/Esri-Fed-Conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'll be attending the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/fedcon/index.html" target="_blank">Esri Federal <del datetime="2012-02-21T11:14:37+00:00">User</del> GIS Conference</a> this week. For various reasons, I'll be attending on the "Increased Carbon Footprint Plan" and commuting to and from the conference each day.</p>

<p>I'm looking forward to the reprise of the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/fedcon/agenda/dev-geo.html" target="_blank">DevGeo</a> session this year as well as a number of the sessions and also meeting up with a lot of my geo-geek friends. I haven't heard the details on #geoglobaldomination yet but I'm sure it will occur.</p>

<p>I'll try to blog more during the course of the conference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FOSS4G North America to Be Held In Washington, DC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/23/FOSS4G-North-America-to-Be-Held-In-Washington-DC/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/23/FOSS4G-North-America-to-Be-Held-In-Washington-DC</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm quite happy to see (HT, <a href="http://blog.gisuser.com/2012/01/23/north-america-gets-their-own-foss4g-conference-in-d-c/" target="_blank">Glenn Letham</a>) that <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/" target="_blank">OSGEO</a> is inaugurating an annual <a href="http://foss4g-na.org/" target="_blank">FOSS4G North America</a> conference this year in Washington, DC on April 10-12, 2012.</p>

<p>DC is an appropriate place for this event because of the presence or arguably the single largest user of geospatial technology, the US Federal Government. I'm happy to see that <a href="http://twitter.com/Byrne_Tweets" target="_blank">Michael Byrne</a> is the keynote speaker as the <a href="http://broadbandmap.gov/" target="_blank">FCC National Broadband Map</a> has been a great success story in the use of open-source geospatial tools at the Federal level. I've been seeing more activity within the Federal Government recently but there's still a long way to go.</p>

<p>I know a lot of people in this area that couldn't make it out to Denver last year for FOSS4G. I hope many of them come to this edition to see the state of the art in open-source geospatial tools. I know this conference is targeted to North America as a whole but, if you are in the DC area and active with geospatial technology, FOSS4G North America should be on your calendar.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Day At the 2011 FedUC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/21/My-Day-At-the-2011-FedUC/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/21/My-Day-At-the-2011-FedUC</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a variety of reasons, I only spent one day at the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/feduc/index.html">FedUC</a> this year. I chose Thursday because that was the day of the DevGeo session, as well as the National Security Session and a SIG in which I was interested. As a result, I did not see the plenary or any of the big-screen demos. With a few meetings crammed in, my day was a whirlwind. What follows is my view of the FedUC but it is by no means comprehensive. To get a more complete picture, I suggest checking out <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9273-Update-3-Wed-Morning-Plenary-FedUC.html">Adena's</a> <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9275-Update-Wed-Afternoon-Plenary-FedUC.html">updates</a> <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9282-Hottest-Thing-on-FedUC-Floor-Zebra-Imagings-Holograms.html">over</a> at <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9278-FedUC-Session-on-Geospatial-Platform-and-Geodata.gov.html">Directions</a>.</p>

<p><img alt="#FedUC" src="http://www.esri.com/news/graphics/feduc.jpg" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I started out in the National Security Session where I saw demos of some mobile apps done for warfighter use and some web-based common operational picture apps targeted at the homeland security community. Perhaps it was the use case that was discussed, combined with my background doing similar work but the Android app, as it was shown, rang a little hollow for me. I thought homeland security demos were on more solid ground. The use cases were familiar, being similar to those shown in previous years, but the tools are now more advanced and the applications more effective. I have worked with most of the tools discussed (ArcGIS Server, the web APIs, geoprocessing tools, etc.) in similar contexts so I thought the technical content was on target. I am a little concerned that multiple agencies seem to be building similar systems under the guise of addressing their own unique requirements. The proliferation of operating pictures and services and such is quickly creating a hydra that may bog down under the weight of its own redundancy. This is not strictly a technology or GIS problem but all of the nice mapping apps put a very visible face on the issue of lack of coordination.</p>

<p>My next stop was the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/feduc/agenda/dev-geo.html">DevGeo</a> session. Because of overlap with the National Security session, I missed the first part on the iOS API but arrived in time for discussion of the Microsoft APIs. The session was technically an all-day thing but I like the way <a href="http://twitter.com/jimbarry">Jim Barry</a> and team broke it up by technology (with specific time slots for each). This made it easy to drop in for the APIs which interested you but also cut out for other sessions during times when other APIs were being discussed.</p>

<p>Before I get too far into the meat of the DevGeo, I want to point out that this is a case where <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> listened to feedback regarding the FedUC. Back in the fall, I suggested to <a href="http://twitter.com/jsteffenson">John Steffenson</a> that some flavor of the DevGeo session they did in Silicon Valley would be a great thing to add to the FedUC. Much to my surprise, John took the idea forward and it happened. I think the addition of DevGeo, which is much more technically focused than the FedUC content tends to normally be, was a good way to round out the conference.</p>

<p>Jim Barry also told me that they are planning five more dev meetups in the DC area in 2011. I'm not sure about other regions, but developers in this area tend to spend a lot of time in cubicles in windowless rooms behind cipher locks so I think these meetups are a good way to foster more collaboration. I know I won't make all five but I'll hit what I can.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="" height="274" src="http://youcube.us/wp-content/uploads/2008/08/officespace.jpg" title="This guy could stand to get out more." width="412" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">This guy could stand to get out more.<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>As for the session itself, I saw the various Microsoft APIs and then also the Android API. I work a lot with the Silverlight API so I'm familiar with it but I did see the Sharepoint tools. It's no secret that I'm not a Sharepoint fan but Esri has done a lot of work to provide web parts that make it pretty easy to insert maps and GIS tools without a lot of code. These parts seem to be targeted at Sharepoint administrators and they make it very easy to map data contained in Sharepoint lists and such. I think Esri succeeded in creating tools that integrate well with workflows with which a Sharepoint administrator is comfortable.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing is the upcoming Silverlight App Builder. This is a wizard-like tool that allows you to build a baseline application framework by choosing a basemap, components such as the navigator, various toolbars and tools, behaviors, actions and the like. What it does is roll up a lot of the tools that the Silverlight API team has been putting out for a while now so you can pick what you want to start with for your application.</p>

<p>I have not actually touched the app builder yet but it seems to create a baseline solution which will build a functioning app with the components you chose. From there, you can deploy the app as-is or begin extending it with your own code. To be perfectly honest, it's probably not something I would use (out of personal preference, not a commentary on the app builder) but I can see its value. I have worked in settings where developers start a Silverlight API app by taking the Silverlight Showcase and stripping out what they don't need. That's a good way to create a mess and I think the app builder provides the opportunity for building a cleaner baseline by adding in only what you do need. It's supposed to be in beta by the the time of the Dev Summit.</p>

<p>The Windows Phone API looked as effective as any other API. Esri is getting pretty good at turning out APIs for various platforms now so it's no surprise that they are on top of Windows Phone. Really, I have nothing to say about the API itself as I was fascinated by the room as the topic transitioned to Windows Phone. The room was filled to capacity (between 150 and 200 people) and only one person had a Windows Phone. As the discussion of the API progressed, people started to leave. I found the lack of interest in the platform almost palpable.</p>

<p>From there, I went to lunch and ditched my backpack. I never once opened my laptop but had my iPad all day. Tablets rule. The days of the laptop are numbered.</p>

<p>I took a swing through the exhibit hall to specifically catch up with the Brian and Jack Flood of <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> and also Brian and Ryan at <a href="http://voyagergis.com/">VoyagerGIS</a>. Arc2Earth is really expanding its cloud support. Upcoming changes are going to greatly simplify pushing data to Google AppEngine. The current version of Arc2Earth Cloud Services is a little cumbersome in that regard and they have been working on streamlining the process. Additionally, they are adding support for the full range of Google geospatial services, including Fusion Tables. This will bring these services right into ArcMap where they can augment existing workflows and data sources. (Disclaimer: <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">My company</a> is an Arc2Earth reseller.)</p>

<p><img alt="Arc2Cloud" src="http://www.arc2earth.com/images/slide1.png" /></p>

<p>I hadn't really seen VoyagerGIS since GIS in the Rockies but they continue to expand their product. At first glance, it looks like a search tool (which it is) but I've always been more impressed by the insights it can give you into your own data use. One of the earliest features that impressed me was the ability to easily identify duplicate data sets, not only by content but by schema (structure). These two things alone can go a long way to helping reduce data redundancy. Additionally the tool indexes ArcMap documents. With this information, you can begin to get insight into what data sets are actually being used in your organization. Basically, the act of indexing your data for search provides the potential for a lot more insight. VoyagerGIS seems to have really hooked into this concept. But don't take my word for it, <a href="http://voyagergis.com/account/signin">download it and try it</a>.</p>

<p>After that, I sat in on a SIG related to infrastructure protection. It gave me a lot of flashbacks and I could probably write an entire (very boring) post on just that. Let's just say there needs to be a lot more thought put into understanding infrastructure interdependence and that federal efforts to engage states on this issue still have a long way to go.</p>

<p>I then swung back through DevGeo for the Android API before my brain was full and my feet hurt. In general, DevGeo was pretty high-level. I would call it a topical overview of the various developer tools provided by Esri but seeing some live demos (Of code...yes, I am a geek because I'd rather see live coding than a PowerPoint any day.) and being able ask some questions is much more valuable than browsing the resource center (at least for me).</p>

<p>I did not go to the Esri shindig at the Natural History Museum as I instead went to the #geoglobaldomination at RFD. Quite a few people from the DC geo scene were there (such as a large crew from <a href="http://www.fortiusone.com">FortiusOne</a>). One of the great things about Esri's conferences is that they act as something of a center of gravity for geo types of all stripes. So there was a great mingling of ideas and catching up with some people that I hadn't seen in a long time. Then, it was time to head for home.</p>

<p>So that closes the books for me on this year's FedUC. Due to scheduling, this will be the only one of the big Esri conferences I'll hit this year so I'll be looking for another backchannel from the <a href="http://www.dtsagile.com/">DTS</a> guys to keep up with the Dev Summit and the International User Conference. :-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
