<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: FCC | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/fcc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-07T20:06:22-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilson Center to Discuss FCC National Broadband Map]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/09/wilson-center-to-discuss-fcc-national-broadband-map/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/09/wilson-center-to-discuss-fcc-national-broadband-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most compelling recent success stories for open-source geospatial tools in the Federal Government has been the <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/" target="_blank">Federal Communications Commission</a> (FCC) <a href="http://broadbandmap.gov/" target="_blank">National Broadband Map</a> initiative. It has been a very visible example of the stability, scalability, flexibility, and power of open-source geospatial tools.</p>

<p>The Woodrow Wilson Center will be hosting <a href="http://www.wilsoncenter.org/event/the-national-broadband-map-case-study-open-innovation-for-national-policy" target="_blank">a case study of National Broadband Map</a> on October 15th, 2012. The event's page also includes a link to the full paper (PDF), authored by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=113470334" target="_blank">Zachary Bastian</a> of the Wilson Center and <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=10690378" target="_blank">Michael Byrne</a> of the FCC.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2933" height="285" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/nbm.png" title="nbm" width="640" /></p>

<p>The full paper, in my opinion, is recommended reading for anyone working with geospatial technologies in the government space. While the Broadband Map has rightfully garnered significant attention based upon its success, especially in terms of performance and scalability, the paper does a good job of reminding us that the map is not an end goal in itself, but a step toward the larger policy goal of expanding broadband access. The paper does an excellent job of illustrating how top-level policy goals were broken down into actionable parts that resulted in a concrete product such as the Broadband Map. In so doing, it walks us through the introduction and fostering of an open culture within the FCC that resulted not only in the Broadband Map but also in the development of open APIs and the availability of FCC tools as open-source projects themselves.</p>

<p>In its conclusions, the paper also makes compelling observations about the power of focused policy goals to drive the use of technology standing in stark contrast to generic overarching technical policies, such as the National Spatial Data Infrastructure (NSDI) which are disconnected from specific policy goals and achieve little traction.</p>

<p>If you are interested not only in geospatial technologies, but also the link between policy and technology implementation, and the cultural change that can be brought about by open-source technologies, you should consider attending the event at the Wilson Center on the 15th. While not a universal blueprint, the National Broadband Map makes a compelling case study.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FCC Open-Sources MapBox Module for Drupal]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/03/20/fcc-open-sources-mapbox-module-for-drupal/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/03/20/fcc-open-sources-mapbox-module-for-drupal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>See the FCC announcement <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/blog/opening-hood%E2%80%94and-code%E2%80%94-behind-fccgovmaps" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://mapbox.com" target="_blank">MapBox</a> has been winning a lot of high-profile converts lately, such as <a href="http://mapbox.com/blog/foursquare-switches-mapbox-streets-openstreetmap/" target="_blank">Foursquare</a>. In my opinion, it's one of the more perfect web mapping solutions, commercial or open-source, to come along in a while. The combination of cartographic engine (<a href="http://mapnik.org/" target="_blank">Mapnik</a>), tile generation (<a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill</a>) and storage (<a href="http://mapbox.com/mbtiles-spec/" target="_blank">MBTiles</a>) make MapBox one of the most elegant ways to serve beautiful maps currently available. <!--more--></p>

<p>The Federal Communications Commission (FCC) has been using MapBox to make a number of <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/maps" target="_blank">compelling maps</a> available to the public. Additonally, the FCC's site has been built on the open-source content management system <a href="http://drupal.org/" target="_blank">Drupal</a>. Today, the <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/blog/opening-hood%E2%80%94and-code%E2%80%94-behind-fccgovmaps" target="_blank">FCC announced</a> that they are making the source code to their MapBox module for Drupal, SlashMap, <a href="http://drupal.org/project/slashmaps" target="_blank">available</a>. This should provide a straightforward way to integrate MapBox maps with a Drupal site.</p>

<p>The FCC has been very active in using open-source tools for their work and it's great to see them giving back to the community in this manner. It's a phenomenon that I think we'll see a lot more of from all levels of government as understanding of and comfort with open-source models increases.</p>

<p>So, if you are a Drupal user, you may want to check out SlashMaps as a way to integrate some very nice web maps. Kudos to <a href="http://twitter.com/byrne_tweets" target="_blank">Michael Byrne</a> and his team at the FCC for taking this step.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FCC Broadband Map Featured by CBS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/28/fcc-broadband-map-featured-by-cbs/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/28/fcc-broadband-map-featured-by-cbs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/Byrne_Tweets">Michael Byrne</a> of the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) gave a really good talk at FOSS4G, telling the story of the FCC <a href="http://www.broadbandmap.gov">National Broadband Map</a> application, which is built on open-source geospatial tools. In addition to being open-source, it's a modern web system that makes diligent use of caching and other techniques to achieve great performance. I do a lot of work in the Federal space and, in my opinion, it's one of best public-facing Federal web tools deployed in recent memory.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/fccmap2.png"><img alt="" height="368" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/fccmap2.png" title="FCC National Broadband Map" width="590" /></a><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">FCC National Broadband Map<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>CBS News, <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-501465_162-20127020-501465/fcc-approves-$4.5-billion-for-broadband-in-era-of-steve-jobs/">in discussing a new $4.5 billion broadband fund by the FCC</a>, features a nice screenshot of the system. It's nice to see good work and innovation get recognized. Michael and his team should be proud.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
