<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Geospatial Sources Sought and Presolicitation notices]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[FBO extract of early stage geospatial opportunities]]></description>
        <link>http://example.com</link>
        <image>
            <url>http://example.com/icon.png</url>
            <title>Geospatial Sources Sought and Presolicitation notices</title>
            <link>http://example.com</link>
        </image>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="http://example.com/geospatial.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        <copyright><![CDATA[2015 Bill Dollins]]></copyright>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <managingEditor><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></managingEditor>
        <webMaster><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></webMaster>
        <docs>http://example.com/rss/docs.html</docs>
        <ttl>60</ttl>
        <category><![CDATA[GIS]]></category>
        <category><![CDATA[geospatial]]></category>
        <category><![CDATA[FBO]]></category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - R--A-E Studies, Geotechnical Engineering Services IDIQ Contract (Unrestricted)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - Solicitation No. W9128F-14-R-0027 (Unrestricted) <br>  <br> 1. CONTRACT INFORMATION <br>  <br> This contract(s) is being procured in accordance with the Brooks A-E Act as implemented in FAR Subpart 36.6.  Firm(s) will be selected for negotiation based on demonstrated competence and qualifications for the required work.  A-E services will consist primarily of preparation of investigations, studies, analyses, designs, and engineering construction support services for dams, levees, military facility construction, and military airfields.  A-E Services may include, but are not limited to: Geotechnical Engineering and Engineering Geology investigations, studies, designs, and engineering construction support; drilling and subsurface investigations; laboratory testing of soil, rock, aggregate, and concrete/asphalt materials; computer analysis/modeling; geophysics; land-based surveying; computer-aided drafting and design (CADD); and geographical information systems (GIS).  These services will be provided for the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers (USACE) districts of Northwestern Division and their respective customers.  One (1) indefinite delivery indefinite quantity (IDIQ) contract will be negotiated and awarded with a five-year ordering period (three (3) year base with a two (2) year option period) and $4,950,000 in capacity.  There is no specific task order limit except the limit of the contract.  Work will be issued by negotiated firm-fixed-price task orders. North American Industrial Classification System code is 541330, which has a size standard of $15,000,000 in annual average gross receipts over the past three years. This announcement is open to all businesses regardless of size.  If an other-than-small (i.e.  quote mark large quote mark ) business firm is selected for this contract, it will be required to submit a detailed subcontracting plan (reference FAR Subpart 19.7 and FAR Clause 52.219-9) during contract negotiation.  The subcontracting goals that will be considered in the negotiation of this contract are as follows: a minimum of 40.0% of the contractor's intended subcontract amount be placed with Small Businesses (SB), 3.0% be placed with Small Disadvantaged Businesses (SDB), to include Historically Black Colleges and Universities or Minority Institutions (HBCU/MIs), 7.0% be placed with Women-Owned Small Businesses (WOSB), 1.0% be placed with HUBZone Small Businesses, 2.0% be placed with Veteran Owned Small Businesses (VOSB), and 3.0% be placed with Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned Small Businesses (SDVOSB).  The subcontracting plan is not required with this submittal, but will be required with the proposal of the firm selected for negotiations. quote mark  Selected and successful firm will be required to comply with the subcontracting limitations as set forth by the FAR Clause 52.219-14 LIMITATIONS ON SUBCONTRACTING, wherein stated in pertinent part,  quote mark Services (except construction).  At least 50% of the cost of contract performance incurred for personnel must be expended for employees of the concern. quote mark   When two or more indefinite delivery contracts (IDCs) available to the procuring agency contain the same or overlapping scopes of work so that a particular task order might be issued under more than one IDC, the contracting officer will consider the following factors in deciding which contractor will be selected to negotiate an order: performance and quality of deliverables under the current contract, current capacity to accomplish the order in the required time, uniquely specialized experience, and equitable distribution of work among the contractors.  The minimum guarantee amount for this contract is $2,500.00.  To be eligible for contract award, the Contractor must be registered in the System for Award Management (SAM).  Registration is free and can be accessed at: http://www.sam.gov.  <br>      <br> 2. PROJECT INFORMATION <br>  <br> Geotechnical Engineering and Engineering Geology investigations, studies, designs, and engineering construction support work may include literature search/existing data compilation; field reconnaissance; determining design and study parameters; site characterization/exploration planning; producing project work plans; design and study data acquisition; obtaining work permits; soil and rock mechanics analyses; ground water characterization including field permeability testing; in situ concrete/asphalt testing; design computations; developing technical input to contract documents; developing project plans and specifications; project cost estimates; technical oversight of construction activities; project progress and completion reporting; and expert services. <br>  <br> Drilling and subsurface investigations work may include geotechnical drilling utilizing auger, fluid rotary, percussion, rotosonic, and direct push techniques; cone penetrometer testing; excavated test pits; subsurface instrumentation placement such as monitoring wells, piezometers, inclinometers, remote sensing instruments, etc.;  in-situ soil and rock testing; disturbed and undisturbed soil sampling; rock/concrete/asphalt coring; and field logging subsurface materials. <br>  <br> Laboratory work will be performed by a USACE certified laboratory and may include typical geotechnical testing of soil, rock, aggregate, concrete, asphalt, etc., materials in accordance USACE guidelines, standards, and regulations or other appropriate industry standards. <br>  <br> Computer analysis/modeling will be performed utilizing commercially available software and work may include analyses for slope stability, ground water, dewatering, seepage, consolidation/settlement, foundation design (pile, pier, footing, excavation, etc.), retaining walls, drains, material strengths, and site optimization. <br>  <br> Geophysics work may include borehole/downhole, surface, and airborne surveys employing nuclear, electrical resistivity, electromagnetic, ground conductivity, seismic, magnetometer, gravity, thermal, and radar techniques. <br>  <br> Land-based surveying work may include determining geospatial reference data (coordinates and elevation) for key project features with both traditional land surveying equipment and techniques as well as Global Positioning Satellite (GPS) techniques. <br>  <br> Computer-aided drafting and design (CADD) work may include developing design drawings, site plans, interpretive subsurface logs and cross-sections, and figures for reports and presentations.  CADD work products will be produced utilizing the most recent version Microstation, AutoCAD, gINT, or other commercially available software as specified in each task order.   <br>  <br> Geographical information systems (GIS) work may include integrating project information on to GIS platforms for comprehensive data interpretation, analysis, manipulation, and archiving. <br>  <br> All specifications shall be developed and edited using the SpecsIntact automated specifications processing system.   <br>  <br> All work will comply with USACE standards, guidelines, regulations or industry standards as appropriate. <br>  <br> Offerors are advised that there could be requirements for performance of work on U.S. Government Federal Properties or Military Installations requiring proper identification and appropriate clearances for personnel to gain access.  <br>  <br>  <br> 3. SELECTION CRITERIA <br>  <br> The selection criteria for this particular project are listed below in descending order of importance.  Criteria a-e are primary.  Criterion f is secondary and will only be used as  quote mark tie-breakers quote mark  among firms that are essentially technically equal.  Page restrictions are outlined per criterion.  A page is defined as a single side of an 8 -inch by 11-inch sheet with print font no smaller than 10. <br> (a) Specialized Experience and Technical Competence (SF 330, Part I, Section F & G):   Section F will provide examples of not more than 10 projects completed within the last 5 years that best demonstrate experience and competency in the areas outlined below.  All projects cited will identify start/completion dates as well as the project size (cost and scope).  Project examples will not exceed 1 page per example.   <br>  <br> Demonstrated experience and competency to complete: <br>  	Geotechnical Engineering and Engineering Geology services <br>  	Drilling and subsurface investigations <br>  	Geotechnical laboratory testing <br>  	Computer analysis/modeling <br>  	Geophysics <br>  	Land-based land surveying <br>  	CADD <br>  	GIS <br>  	Quality Assurance/Quality Control (QA/QC) for engineering support during construction <br>  <br> Section G will list key personnel proposed for this contract and their respective roles in example projects cited in Section F.  Section G will not exceed 2 pages. <br>  <br> (b) Capacity (SF 330, Part I, Section H): Capacity is the ability to effectively complete task orders.   Firms shall demonstrate the capacity to accomplish at least two (2) $250,000 simultaneous individual task orders within a one-year period.   Evaluation will consider resources, team organization, coordination of in house disciplines and consultants, and prior experience of the prime firm and any of their significant consultants on similar projects.  The evaluation will consider the key persons identified in Sections D, E, and G of the SF330, as well as other available staff and information provided in Section H. <br>    <br> A proposed Management Plan shall be presented that includes an organization chart (reference SF330, Part I, Section D) and addresses team organization (reference SF330, Part I, Section C), any anticipated sub-contractors or entities to supplement the in-house team, quality control procedures, cost control, coordination of in-house disciplines and consultants required to meet work capacity, and interaction with USACE. The SF 330 shall clearly indicate the primary office where the work will be performed and the staffing at that office.  Additionally, key equipment assets (e.g. drill rig(s), laboratory testing facilities/equipment, geophysical instruments, etc.) will be acknowledged and respective locations identified. <br>  <br> If necessary, the organization chart may be presented on a single side of an 11-inch by 17 inch sheet neatly fold to an 8 -inch by 11-inch format. <br>  <br> (c) Knowledge of Locality Knowledge of locality will mean knowledge of regional or local geology, hydrology, soils, topography, climatic conditions, local methods that are unusual or unique, etc.  The firm's office location(s) is not necessarily indicative of knowledge of locality.  The location of Engineering Services will include USACE districts of Northwestern Division and their respective customers.   <br>  <br> (d) Professional Qualifications (SF 330, Part I, Section E):  Evaluation of education, training, registration, certifications, overall and relevant experience, and longevity with the firm of key management and technical personnel.  This criterion is primarily concerned with the qualifications of key personnel, not the number of personnel. Certifications and/or licensing are required for the following: Professional Engineer (Geotechnical/Civil), Professional Geologist, Driller, Professional Land Surveyor/Registered Land Surveyor, and Project Management Professional (PMP).  Other key personnel that will be identified include:  laboratory manager, laboratory technician, GIS professional, geophysicist, CADD professional, and technical editor.  If after submission of the proposal or after award of a contract, the proposed individuals are unable to fulfill the obligation of the solicitation, any proposed replacements will have similar or greater education and experience credentials.  Those credentials shall be provided in writing to the Contracting Officer for review and approval.  Professional qualification information will not exceed 1 page per key personnel position and will not exceed 20 pages cumulatively. <br>  <br> (e) Past Performance: Past Performance on DoD and other contracts with respect to cost control, quality of work, and compliance with performance schedules, as determined from ACASS and other sources. (May be evaluated from ACASS information obtained by the Omaha District Office)  <br>  <br> Past Performance Questionnaires (PPQ) may be used to provide or supplement a firm's past performance with other than U.S. Governmental clients.  Firms which choose to use the PPQ may obtain a PPQ standard form by submitting a request to the below referenced POC to the Contract Specialist. <br>    <br> Secondary Selection Criteria:  Secondary criteria will only be used by a selection board as a  quote mark tie-breaker quote mark , if necessary, in ranking the most highly qualified firms.   <br>  <br> (f) Equitable Distribution of Department of Defense (DoD) Contracts (SF 330, Part I, Section H): Volume of DoD A-E contract awards in the last 12 months, with the objective of effecting an equitable distribution of DoD A-E contracts among qualified firms, including SB and SDB.  DoD contract information shall not exceed 2 pages. <br>  <br>  <br> Evaluation Ratings <br>  <br> The following ratings will be used to evaluate the submitted information: <br>  <br> Exceptional. All or almost all of the significant disciplines and attributes are <br> rated  quote mark exceptional. quote mark   No discipline or attribute should be  quote mark marginal quote mark  or  quote mark unsatisfactory quote mark  in an  quote mark exceptional quote mark  performance evaluation. <br>  <br> Very Good.  A majority of the significant disciplines and attributes are rated  quote mark exceptional quote mark  or  quote mark very good. quote mark   No significant discipline or attribute should be  quote mark marginal quote mark  or  quote mark unsatisfactory quote mark  in a  quote mark very good quote mark  performance evaluation. <br>  <br> Satisfactory.  No significant discipline or attribute should be  quote mark unsatisfactory. quote mark  Quality of final work is acceptable in an overall sense; however, it may have been necessary to get the firm to correct some unacceptable work. <br>  <br> Marginal.  One or two significant disciplines or attributes are rated  quote mark unsatisfactory, quote mark  or all or almost all disciplines or attributes are rated  quote mark marginal. quote mark   An unusual amount of extra effort and follow-up on the part of the Government was required in order to get an acceptable product. <br>  <br> Unsatisfactory.  Several significant disciplines and attributes are rated <br>  quote mark unsatisfactory. quote mark   This rating is appropriate for a firm that does not produce acceptable work despite extensive effort by <br>  <br>  <br> 4. SUBMISSION REQUIREMENTS: <br> Interested firms having the capabilities to perform this work must submit five (5) copies of SF 330 Part I, and five (5) copies of SF 330 Part II for the prime firm and all consultants/subcontractors, to US Army Corps of Engineers, Omaha District, ATTN: Tyler Hegge (CENWO-CT-M), 1616 Capitol Ave., Omaha, NE, 68102, not later than 2:00pm Central time on the 6th of October, 2014.  SUBMITTAL PACKAGES MUST ALSO INCLUDE A CD CONTAINING A COMPLETE COPY OF THE SUBMITTAL (AN SF 330 PART 1 + SF 330 PART II FOR THE PRIME FIRM AND ALL CONSULTANTS/SUBCONTRACTORS), AS A SINGLE PDF FILE. Regulation requires that the Selection Board not consider any submittals received after the specified time and date.  Late proposal rules in FAR 15.208 will be followed for submittals received after 2:00pm Central time on the closing date specified in this announcement.  The SF 330, 03/2013 edition, must be used, and may be obtained from the following web site: http://www.gsa.gov/portal/forms/download/116486.  Include DUNS number and CAGE code in SF330 Part I, Section B, Block 5.  Additionally, the DUNS number and CAGE code should be identified in SF 330 Part I, Section C, Block 9, for EACH TEAM MEMBER.  The submittal shall have a page limit of 100 pages.  A page is one side of a sheet.  Blank sheets/Tabs separating the sections within the SF 330 will not count against the maximum page count. All fonts shall be at least 10 pitch or larger.  Pages shall be 8-1/2 inches by 11 inches.  Organizational charts may be presented on a sheet up to 11 inches by 17 inches. If an 11 inch by 17 inch sheet is used it shall be neatly folded to 8-1/2 inches by 11 inches, bound in the SF 330 at the proper location, and counted as one page.  A Part II is required for each branch office of the prime firm and any consultants/subcontractors that will have a key role in the proposed contract (i.e. a Part II is required for all entities identified in SF 330 Part I, Section C of the submittal).  Cover letters, company literature and extraneous materials are not desired and will not be considered.  Sections E and G of SF 330 Part I must include only individuals proposed to perform the anticipated work, including all consultants/subcontractors.  In SF 330 Part I, Section G, Block 26, along with the name, include the firm with which the person is associated.  A maximum of ten (10) projects including the prime and consultants/subcontractors will be reviewed for SF 330 Part I, Section F.  Use no more than one page per project.  When listing projects in SF 330 Part 1, Section F, an Indefinite Delivery Contract (IDC) with multiple Task Orders as examples is not considered a project. A task order executed under an IDC contract is a project.   For all types of contracts, do not include for consideration options that have not been exercised.  Joint ventures shall submit the following additional documentation of the evidence of a joint venture entity: 1) Firms shall provide a copy of a legally binding joint venture agreement, and 2) Identification of the party who can legally bind the joint venture.  FACSIMILE AND EMAIL SUBMISSIONS WILL NOT BE ACCEPTED.  Solicitation packages are not provided and no additional project information will be given to firms during the announcement period.  This is not a request for proposal.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA45/W9128F-14-R-0027/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA45/W9128F-14-R-0027/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - R--Geospatial Information System Support Services]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - Mission & Installation Contracting Command Center (MICC) - Fort Bragg, North Carolina will issue solicitation W91247-15-T-0045 for a requirement to provide services for Geospatial Information System Support Services at Fort Bragg, North Carolina. The Contractor shall support the oversight on the creation, maintenance, and management of Installation geospatial data as defined in this Performance Work Statement (PWS). The Contractor shall perform to the standards in this contract. The requirement will be set-aside for HubZone, under NAICS Code 561110, with a size standard of $7.5M. A Firm-Fixed Price (FFP) contract is anticipated under solicitation number W91247-15-T-0045 and will be available for downloading at the Army Single Face to Industry website https://acquisition.army.mil/asfi.   <br>  <br> Potential Responders are responsible for monitoring this site for release of the solicitation package and any amendments.   <br>  <br> All offerors must be registered with the System for Award Management (SAM) per FAR Clause 52.212-4(t) - Contract Terms and Conditions - Commercial Items (May 2015). Offerors must also complete Offeror Representations and Certifications on-line at www.sam.gov prior to submitting an offer.  No paper copies of the solicitation will be mailed and telephone requests will not be honored.  The Government anticipates posting of the Request for Quote (RFQ) on or about 09 September 2015. <br>   <br> The point of contact is Contract Specialist, Nicole Jones at email: nicole.m.jones2.civ@mail.mil. Phone Number 910-643-7221. <br>  <br> The alternate point of contact is the Contracting Officer, Heather Clifton at email: heather.d.clifton.civ@mail.mil. Phone Number 910-908-1964. <br>  <br> Contracting Office Address: <br> Mission & Installation Contracting Command (MICC) Center - Fort Bragg, North Carolina, ATTN: CCMI-CBR-BR, Building 2-1105 C-Stack, Macomb Street, Fort Bragg, North Carolina 28310-5000. <br>  <br>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/bc79a868a193ce35a88ea10f42323aef</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/bc79a868a193ce35a88ea10f42323aef</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - Canadian FLIPs]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Other Defense Agencies - This posting constitutes the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency's intent to award, on a sole source basis, a contract to acquire Canadian Flight Information Publications (FLIPs) to NAV Canada Corporation in accordance with (IAW) DFARS 225.870-1(c)(3) and FAR 6.302-1(a)(1). The required publications are only available from one Canadian firm. The estimated award amount is $112,348.63. The statutory authority for the sole source acquisition is 10 U.S.C. 2304 (c)(1) as implemented by FAR 6.302-1. The Government intends to acquire commercial items using FAR Part 13.1. The applicable NAICS code is 511120 and the size standard is 500 employees. This notice of intent is not a request for quotation or solicitation of offers. There is no solicitation available.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/ODA/NIMA/PCSL-13/NS68G85029AS01/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/ODA/NIMA/PCSL-13/NS68G85029AS01/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - Information Technology (IT) Services and Support for Regions 7, 8, 9 and 10]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Environmental Protection Agency - In preparation for a future procurement, the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 9 is conducting market research to determine the number of 8(a) small business concerns capable of performing the tasks listed in the draft statement of work for Information Technology (IT) Services and Support (See Attachment).

The requirement will provide a full complement of Information Technology supplemental services necessary to (1) support and maintain the day-to-day computing environment for staff and (2) implement and support implementation and compliance activities as needed under a variety of administrative and environmental regulations for region 9 which includes California, Nevada, Arizona, Hawaii, Guam, American Samoa, the Territories in the Pacific and Tribal Land.  The requirement will also include EPA Regions 7, 8, and 10.  

The services include: Desktop Management and Help Desk; Work Orders/ Technical Direction (Projects); Training; Account & Access Management ( User Set-up); Hardware Maintenance/Repair/Disposal; Inventory Management; Continuity of Operations Plan (COOP); REOC Support; Enterprise Connectivity; Application Services; Laboratory Information Management System (LIMS); Geospatial (GIS) Support; Web Design and Support Services; Voice Services and Audio/Video Support; Production Support; and Graphics Support.

The applicable NAICS code is 541519 with a size limitation of $27.5 million according to the Small Business Administration (www.sba.gov). Interested 8(a) firms that meet the small business size standard may submit a capability statement in response to this announcement. When submitting a capability statement, interested firms must demonstrate the capability and capacity to perform the work described in the draft statement of work as it relates to information technology support and services. As part of the demonstration of capacity, firms should include information regarding the size and scope of previous efforts pertaining to Information Technology support services.

Interested firms must also demonstrate that they have the necessary personnel with the requisite experience, labor, materials, services, equipment, and facilities to support the efforts delineated in the draft SOW. Also, firms must include the number of employees and size standard in millions of dollars to determine eligibility as well as the 8(a) sub-category. 

Only electronic submissions of capability statements will be accepted. Electronic responses shall be limited to 10 pages, including attachments, on 8.5 x 11 pages. Font size shall be no smaller than 11 pt. Submissions shall be in English. PDF or MS Word document formats are acceptable. Capability statements shall be sent to Mr. Rede Shifferaw at shifferaw.rede@epa.gov no later than 5:00 PM Pacific Daylight Time on September 21, 2015. Standard company brochures and literature will not be considered a sufficient response to this Sources Sought Notice. Please submit any questions regarding this notice in writing to Mr. Rede Shifferaw at shifferaw.rede@epa.gov.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/EPA/OAM/RegIX/SOL-R9-15-00016/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/EPA/OAM/RegIX/SOL-R9-15-00016/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - Cyberspace Infrastructure Planning System (CIPS)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Air Force - This acquisition will provide essential capabilities for the sustainment, maintenance and modernization of the Cyberspace Infrastructure Planning System (CIPS). CIPS is the System of Record for official processing of infrastructure related information technology /National Security System (IT/NSS) documents (formally known as Computer Systems Requirements Documents (CSRD) or AF Form 3215); Air Force wide processing of IT Infrastructure funding requests; Integrated project funding management; base outside cable plant infrastructure documentation; and communications layer of the Installation Geospatial Information and Services (IGI&amp;S). Other CIPS capabilities and information include the ability to document IT assets, real property assets, and contracts; manage user accounts and permissions; link graphical and database information; perform work order management, project management, and portfolio/program management. The CIPS contractor will provide the Operations and Maintenance (O&amp;M) for a secure, reliable, and flexible enterprise-level automated information system (AIS) for planning, installing, and managing the Air Force's (AF) communications infrastructure. CIPS is organized based on data elements required to support a lifecycle-based business process that includes cyber infrastructure assessments, requirements management, cost estimates, project planning, prioritization of plans, funding allocation, program management, project management, and documentation of baseline infrastructure changes. The service will be performed at the 38 CEIG, Tinker AFB OK. The solicitation will include a base year and four, one-year options. The service period of performance is 01 Jul 2016-30 Jun 2021. A six month option to extend services in accordance with (IAW) Federal Acquisition Regulation (FAR) 52.217-8 will also be included in the solicitation.&nbsp;&nbsp;Solicitation issuance is contemplated&nbsp;prior to 30 Sep 2015.&nbsp;
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/0006a1ce7cdc772f334ec1a0cbb4a61c</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/0006a1ce7cdc772f334ec1a0cbb4a61c</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - A--Research and Development Source Sought, FY16 Living Marine Resources (LMR) Program Environmental Need Topics]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Navy - This announcement constitutes a Broad Agency Announcement (BAA) for the Naval Facilities Engineering and Expeditionary Warfare Center (NEXWC) under FAR 6.102(d)(2) and 35.106. A formal Request for Proposals (RFP), other solicitation, or additional information regarding this announcement will not be issued.

FAR Part 35 restricts the use of BAAs, such as this, to the acquisition of basic and applied research and that portion of advanced technology development not related to the development of a specific system or hardware procurement. Contracts made under BAAs are for scientific study and experimentation directed towards advancing the state of the art and increasing knowledge or understanding.
  This announcement is not for the acquisition of technical, engineering, or other types of support services.

The Naval Facilities Engineering and Expeditionary Warfare Center, through the Living Marine Resources (LMR) program, is soliciting pre-proposals for efforts related to any one of the two (2) need topics listed below. If invited, offerors will be asked to submit a full proposal.

NEED TOPICS:

NEED TOPIC 1: BEHAVIORAL RESPONSE RESEARCH TO STUDY THE EFFECTS OF SOUND ON MARINE MAMMALS. (LMR N-0102-16). There are two high priority behavioral response research topics in the order of interest to the Living Marine Resources program:

1.	Behavioral response research to improve our understanding of the potential effects from Navy training and testing activities.
 Studies of priority interest include questions such as: (a) range dependent effects on behavioral responses; (b) in priority order, behavioral response to Navy active sonar sources transmitting in the frequency ranges of: i) 1-10 kHz; ii) 10-100 kHz; iii) 100-1000 Hz; (c) link between behavior state and response.  For all proposed studies, baseline data on animal behavior should be obtained or previously collected for comparison with behavioral response data. 
2.	Demonstration of medium and long-term tags, which utilize Fastloc GPS satellite technology and collect high-fidelity dive profile and possibly measure sound exposure data, to study animal movement and behavioral response. There is a need to demonstrate developed tag technologies that can record animal movement and behavioral responses over a longer-term duration from weeks to months.
 

See Appendix A for LMR priority species and geographic regions. Proposals should include appropriate research approaches including but not limited to:  controlled exposure experiment on captive and free-ranging animals, observational studies in relation to exposure to real Navy sources, etc. In addition, proposals should include appropriate methods including but not limited to tagging, direct measurement, passive acoustics, etc.  

NEED TOPIC 2: MARINE SPECIES HEARING RESEARCH RELATED TO THE ACOUSTIC EFFECTS CRITERIA. (LMR N-0103-16). There are three high priority hearing research topics of interest to the Living Marine Resources program:

1.	Audiograms of hearing capability in marine species that have limited data available or have not been previously studied.
 Species priority includes:  marine mammals (beaked whales, small delphinids, mysticetes), diving sea birds (e.g. Auk family), and sea turtles. 
2.	Hearing research to study temporary threshold shift (TTS) at multiple frequencies for marine species, to include marine mammals, sea turtles, and possibly diving sea birds, with sufficient audiometric data.
3.	Effects to fish from the detonation of explosive devices of various charge sizes, depths, and distances to the subjects. Must include data on well characterized received and estimated source levels.

Priority interest is in species where we have no or insufficient data available. Results from these studies will be used to refine the Navy acoustic effects criteria for determining impact.
  

SUPPORTING INFORMATION:
For more information on what is required in a proposal, guidance on LMR priority species and geographic regions, how to submit a proposal via the LMR website, and how proposals are evaluated, refer to Appendix A. Offerors will be required to adhere to the data rights and handling procedures agreement (Appendix B) and the geospatial data requirements (Appendix C). Modifications to the data rights and handling procedures agreement or geospatial data requirements should be discussed with the LMR program staff prior to proposal submission. Offerors will also need to comply with the U.S. Navy Handling Procedures for Ocean Observing Systems (OOS) Data (Appendix D) and the Ocean Observing Systems Awareness and Compatibility Memorandum (Appendix E).
  Offerors should note, however, that locations labelled in red in Appendix E as incompatible with acoustic OOS actually overlap with some of the LMR priority geographic regions outlined in Appendix A. Strict adherence to passive acoustic monitoring site selection, passive acoustic device deployment notification and data custody guidance will be required. Site selection should be discussed with the LMR program staff prior to submission of the proposal package. DoD is still finalizing their plan to meet the goals and requirements of the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy (OSTP) memorandum titled Increasing Access to the Results of Federally Funded Scientific Research issued 2013 February 22.
 All projects funded by LMR would be subject to DoD policy once it is finalized.

WEB-BASED SUBMISSION PROCESS: 
Submissions should be made via the LMR program website, www.lmr.navy.mil, identifying one, and only one, of the three listed need topic areas as the primary focus of the pre-proposal. Pre-proposals and full proposals will only be evaluated under one need topic.

SUBMISSION DEADLINE: 
To be considered for funding in FY 2016, pre-proposals must be received no later than 5:00 pm, Pacific Standard Time on 23 OCTOBER, 2015. If invited to submit a full proposal, these will be due 30 days after notification.  

EVALUATION PROCESS: 
Offerors will receive an automated email message acknowledging successful submission to the LMR program website.
 Following a 2 month evaluation and approval process, successful pre-proposal offerors will receive an email inviting submission of a full proposal, also via the LMR program website. Unsuccessful pre-proposal offerors will receive an email via the LMR program website, but will not receive a detailed description of the reasons for pre-proposal rejection, due to the anticipated volume of submissions. Awards to non-government entities (academic institutions, not-for-profit organizations, industry) will be in the form of contracts. A nominal award amount has not been provided because the scope of the need topics varies considerably. However, proposals less than $300K/year are more likely to be funded given the limited budget of the LMR program in FY 2016.
  The nominal duration of a project is expected to be 1-3 years, with a maximum of 5 years. Applicants are strongly encouraged to use realism of cost for the proposed effort as their metric, as this will be a critical element in the review process.  Otherwise meritorious pre-proposals and full proposals will be rejected if cost does not accurately reflect the proposed scope of work.

Proposed efforts involving interaction with and contact with marine mammals or endangered species may require research permits including but not limited to a Marine Mammal Protection Act (MMPA) Research Permit, Endangered Species Act (ESA) scientific research permit, and/or Department of Defense Animal Care and Use authorization.
 If the offeror currently possesses a permit or other documentation, it should be mentioned in the pre-proposal and submitted as part of the full proposal. If your project involves developing or demonstrating a technology, an agreement with NAVFAC EXWC will need to be established to describe the ownership/use of the technology. Contracts will not be awarded without appropriate regulatory documentation and all agreements in place.

EVALUATION CRITERIA: 
The pre-proposals and full proposals will be evaluated based on the following criteria, of approximately equal weight.

1.	TECHNICAL APPROACH: The scientific/technical merits and objectives in terms of meeting the stated need topic, as well as evidence that the science/technology is mature enough for applied research funding, and the performance criteria to measure success of the research effort.
 

2.	OFFEROR’S EXPERIENCE: For the pre-proposal phase, the offeror should clearly provide evidence or examples showing experience related to the solution being proposed. The organization’s capabilities related to experience, techniques, or a unique combination of these that are integral factors in achieving the contractors proposed objectives. This equates to past performance, and will be assessed based on both relevance and confidence. If invited to submit a full proposal, NAVFAC also requires the offeror to provide their EMR and DART ratings. Safety is an integral and important aspect in all NAVFAC work. If the offeror does not have an EMR/DART rating, they should state this and provide a narrative rationale.
 See NFAS 15.304. 

3.	PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR’S AND KEY MEMBER’S RELATED EXPERIENCE: For the pre-proposal phase, the offeror should provide the name, highest degree earned, organization/affiliation, location, and years of experience for the Principal Investigator and key personnel who are critical in achieving the objectives of the proposal. Principle Investigators and key personnel should be identified in the pre-proposal as such. If invited to submit a full proposal, the offeror will need to upload CVs for the Principal Investigator and key personnel.

4.	COST/PRICE: The cost relative to the proposed scientific/technical approach. For the pre-proposal phase this information may be limited to a total cost estimate by calendar year (Jan 1 – December 31).
 Assume for Year 1 of your project that effort will begin in August due to the time it takes to get a contract in place. It is assumed in Year 1 (August-December) of the project your cost estimate should only include effort associated with basic initiation of the project and that the majority of effort would take place in Year 2 and beyond. In addition to any other relevant travel required for the project, please include a trip for the PI to attend the In-Progress Review (IPR) meeting each year (fall) in Port Hueneme, CA to present on the progress of the project. If invited to submit a full proposal, additional guidance on cost/price information will be provided. This is not prescriptive, and can be submitted in the contractor’s format.
 However, the same information will be required.

5.	NAVY BENEFITS AND IMPACT: Expected benefits of the proposed project, key issues the proposed solution addresses, potential application of the results of the project, and advantages over current approaches.

6.	PRODUCT IMPLEMENTATION: Describe the intended product(s) and all associated deliverables, the requirements for implementing the proposed products of this effort by the Navy, and the potential technical risks that may pose a challenge to successful implementation.

NOTES:
1.	An eligible pre-proposal or full proposal does not guarantee a contract. Multiple contracts may result.

2.	An offeror is required to register with the system for award management (SAM).
 No contract award will be made to any offeror that is not registered. Registration may take up to three weeks. SAM may be accessed at https://www.sam.gov. Registration is not required for proposal submission, but must be completed prior to initiation of award negotiation.  To avoid delays in the award process, applicants are encouraged to initiate SAM registration early in the submission and review process.  Non-government awardees will also need to provide a DUNS (Dunn  and  Bradstreet) number (http://fedgov.dnb.com/webform/displayHomePage.doc) and CAGE (Commercial and Government Entity) code (http://govwin.com/knowledge/ccr-registration) before an award can be made. 

3.	The preceding data should be sufficient for completing the pre-proposal form.

4.	There are no solicitation documents applying to this LMR program BAA.
 Request for a solicitation package will not be acknowledged. Those interested in participating in the LMR program BAA must follow the instructions to submit a pre-proposal.

5.	There is no commitment by the Navy either to make any contract awards or to be responsible for any money expended by the contractor before a contract award.

6.	As no funding for contracts has been reserved in advance, NEXWC will be sharing qualified pre-proposals with other Federal Government activities to seek demonstration sites and/or funding. Some Federal Government activities may employ civilian contractors to determine the applicability of an offered technology to specific projects. Technical and cost pre-proposals and full proposals submitted under this BAA will be protected from unauthorized disclosure in accordance with FAR 3.104-4 and 15.207.
 The cognizant Program Manager and other scientific experts will perform the evaluation of technical proposals. Restrictive notices notwithstanding, one or more support contractors may be utilized as subject-matter-expert technical consultants in accordance with FAR 37.204. However, pre-proposal and full proposal selection and award decisions are solely the responsibility of Government personnel.   Each support contractor’s employee having access to technical and cost pre-proposals and full proposals submitted in response to this BAA will be required to sign a non-disclosure statement prior to receipt of any pre-proposal or full proposal submissions. An offeror may require the non-government personnel to execute a supplemental non- disclosure agreement by including a copy of their institutional NDA with their proposal.
 However, note that a failure to come to an agreement may impact the ability to make an award. Please review FAR 37.204 and NFAS 15.303(d)(4). Eligibility notification will be sent to all contractors who have submitted a pre-proposal, after the Technical Review Committee (TRC) and Living Marine Resources Advisory Committee (LMRAC) have reviewed all pre-proposals submitted by the solicitation cut-off date.

7.	For questions regarding this BAA, contact NAVFAC EXWC at (805) 982-4853 or (805) 982-5872 or via this e-mail address: exwc_lmr_program@navy.mil. Correspondents are advised not to include Personally Identifiable Information (PII), business proprietary, or competition-sensitive information via email.
  Offerors will receive an automated email message acknowledging successful submission to the LMR program website. If the contractor does not receive a notification of pre-proposal receipt, the contractor should call or e-mail NEXWC by using the phone number or e-mail address provided in this section.

8.	Historically Black Colleges/Universities and Minority Institutions (HBCU/MI) will be recognized according to DFARS 226.3. All responsible sources from academia and industry may submit proposals. No portion of this BAA will be set aside for HBCU and MI participation, due to the impracticality of reserving discrete or severable items of this research for exclusive competition among the entities.
  Federally Funded Research and Development Centers (FFRDCs) including Department of Energy National Laboratories, are not eligible to receive awards under this   BAA. However, teaming arrangements between FFRDCs and eligible principal bidders are allowed so long as they are permitted under the sponsoring agreement between the Government and the specific FFRDC. 

DFARS 235.017-1 allows DOD FFRDCs which function primarily as research laboratories to apply. Naval laboratories and Warfare Centers as well as other DOD and civilian agency laboratories are not eligible to receive awards under this BAA and should not directly submit proposals in response to this BAA. If any such organization is interested in one or more of these program areas, they should contact the NEXWC program office to discuss its interest.
 As with the FFRDCs, these organizations may team with other responsible sources from   industry and academia that are submitting proposals under the BAA. University Affiliated Research Centers (UARC) are eligible to submit proposals under this BAA unless precluded from doing so by their DOD UARC contract or an organizational conflict of interest.

9.	Do not call the Contracting Office for verification. The pre-proposal is not received by the Contracting Office.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/5608a613b3ea3698113a69b3f35ad930</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/5608a613b3ea3698113a69b3f35ad930</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - C--FACILITY PLANNING SERVICES A-E IDIQ, NAVAL FACILITIES ENGINEERING COMMAND SOUTHWEST SAN DIEGO, CALIFORNIA]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Navy - This is a Sources Sought Synopsis announcement, a market survey for information to be used for preliminary planning purposes. The information received will be used within the Navy to facilitate the decision making process and will not be disclosed outside of the agency. 

The intent of this Sources Sought Synopsis is to identify potential qualified Small Businesses, U.S. Small Business Administration (SBA) certified 8(a) Businesses, SBA certified HUBZone Businesses, Economically Disadvantaged Woman-Owned Small Businesses and/or Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned Small Businesses. 

This Sources Sought Synopsis is one facet in the Government’s overall market research in regards to whether the proposed solicitation will be issued as a competitive set-aside or as full and open (unrestricted).
 No procurement strategy will be determined based solely on the information received in response to this Sources Sought Synopsis. 

No reimbursement will be made for any costs associated with providing information in response to this announcement or any follow-up information requests. This notice does not constitute a Request for Proposal and is not to be construed as a commitment by the Government for any purpose other than market research. Respondents will not be notified of the results of the evaluation.

Naval Facilities Engineering Command Southwest is seeking Small Business, SBA certified 8(a), SBA certified HUBZone, Economically Disadvantaged Woman-Owned Small Business (EDWOSB) and/or Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned Small Business (SDVOSB) sources with current relevant experience, personnel, and capability to perform the Architect/Engineering (A/E) services required for a firm fixed price Indefinite-Delivery, Indefinite-Quantity (IDIQ) contract for Facility Planning Services at various government installations located in Arizona, California, Colorado, Nevada, New Mexico and Utah.
 It is anticipated that most projects will be performed in California. 

Primary required A-E Services are required for:
PROJECT PLANNING DOCUMENTS: Military Construction (MILCON) and Special Project planning documentation (DD Form 1391) using Electronic Project Generator (EPG);  demolition / footprint reduction;  preliminary and parametric cost estimates; life cycle analysis; economic analyses (using the latest version of the Government’s ECONPACK software); site approvals (ordnance, explosive safety, etc.); Anti-Terrorism/Force Protection (AT/FP); Asset Evaluations (AE); Basic Facilities Requirements (BFR) documentation; 
Facilities Planning Documents (FPD) using the government’s web-based iNFADS program.

Secondary required A-E services may include:
SUSTAINABILITY MASTER PLANNING:  Local and regional planning to include sustainable urbanism, healthy community planning, campus planning, form-based planning, energy and renewable master planning, transportation planning, landscape architecture, water conservation planning, and electronic/web-based master planning and other planning documents which incorporate sustainability principles such those outlined in UFC 2-100-01 Installation Master Planning.
GEO-SPATIAL INFORMATION  and  SERVICE:  The preparation of Geo-Spatial Data services includes: a) spatial and non-spatial data acquisition; loading data into enterprise GIS database systems in accordance with current spatial data standards (SDSFIE 3x); b) preparation of maps, datasets, data models, geo-processing models, automation scripts utilizing Microsoft Office, Adobe Acrobat, Oracle, AutoCAD, ESRI ArcGIS Product Suite; and c) GPS services which include the collection of global positioning system (GPS) data using GPS equipment compatible with the NAVFAC SW Geo-Readiness Center (GRC).

Required A-E support services may include: renewable energy research and or studies; architectural studies; civil engineering studies; land surveying and topographic mapping; and hazardous materials test and abatement studies.
  These services are limited to use in support of Project Planning Documents and Sustainable Master Planning Documents as described above.

The North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) Code is 541320 (Landscape Architectural Services) with a Small Business Size Standard of $7.5 million. The proposed contract will be for one base year with 4 one-year renewable options, resulting in the contract performance period maximum of 5 years. The estimated total contract price for the base year and all option years combined is $30,000,000. The maximum value of individual task orders would be $1,500,000. The minimum value of individual task orders would be $150,000.

Interested Small Business, SBA certified 8(a), SBA certified HUBZone, Economically Disadvantaged Woman-Owned Small Business and/or Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned Small Business sources are invited to respond to this sources sought announcement by completing the following sections of the SF330 Architect-Engineer Qualifications in the following manner:  

Part I – Contract Specific Qualifications:  

Note:  In sections where recent experience is requested, all experience will be evaluated for market research purposes only.
  Firms are advised that while experience older than five years may demonstrate capability to perform the scope of work, it may not indicate that the firm could be competitive during a future solicitation where only the most recent five years of experience will be accepted.  NAVFAC may make an acquisition strategy determination based on the likelihood that a sufficient pool of qualified contractors will be competitive on a future solicitation.

Complete Section A – Contract Information.  

Complete Section B – A-E Point of Contact.  In addition to name of firm in Block 5, provide your firm’s Dun and Bradstreet Number (DUNS) and state if your firm is SBA Certified 8(a), SBA Certified HUBZone, SDVOSB, EDWOSB or Small Business.
  A set-aside cannot be reasonably determined without size and socio-economic designations. 

Section E – Resumes: Provide a minimum of three (3) and a maximum of 5 (5) resumes for key personnel on your team that would be directly responsible for performing the required services. Include the geographic office location of the individual on the resume.  At least one (1) of the key personnel shall be a professionally registered planner certified by the American Institute of Certified Planners (AICP) and be on staff of the Prime A-E firm. At least one (1) of the key personnel shall be a Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design (LEED) Green Associate (GA) or Accredited Professional (AP) by the US Green Building Council (USGBC) and be on staff of the Prime A-E firm.
 Each resume shall include a minimum of three (3) and a maximum of five (5) specific, recently completed projects that best illustrate the individual member’s qualifications in performing the required A-E services. A specific project is a single project or a single task order under an indefinite quantity contract or on-call type contract.  “Recent” is defined as professional A-E services completed within the past five years prior to this Sources Sought Synopsis announcement due date.  

Section H – Additional Information:  On a maximum of two pages, list a minimum of five (5) and a maximum of ten (10) specific, recently completed projects that best illustrate proposed team’s qualifications in the required services.
 Include the A-E fee for the services performed. At least three (3) of the projects shall have both a minimum A-E fee of $500,000 and be self-performed by the Prime A-E firm. A specific project is a single project or a single task order under an indefinite quantity contract or on-call type contract.  “Recent” is defined as professional A-E services completed within the past five years prior to this Sources Sought Synopsis announcement due date.  Select projects where multiple team members worked together, if possible, that demonstrate the team’s capability to perform the required services. List each project as a brief paragraph listing the project title, location, team members involved, cost, completion date and how each project reflects experience in the required services.

Section H – Additional Information:  On a maximum of one (1) page, provide two brief paragraphs, one addressing “Location” and one addressing “Capacity”.
  Entitle the first paragraph “Location” and within that paragraph indicate the location of the firm’s main office and branch offices, and describe the team’s knowledge and availability to work in the proposed geographical area. Entitle the second paragraph “Capacity” and within that paragraph indicate the number of employees within the firm responsible for the required A-E services and address the firm’s capacity to accomplish multiple small and large task orders simultaneously. The Offeror/Contractor must demonstrate adequate in-house staffing capable to self-perform at least 50 percent of the cost of the contract as required by FAR Clause 52.219.14 (b)(1) Limitation on Subcontracting.  

Section I – Authorized Representative:  Ensure the authorized representative of the firm signs the page attesting to the information provided in the sources sought response.
 

Part II General Qualifications: Complete SF330 Part II - General Qualifications for the Prime Firm responding to this Sources Sought Notice.

Responses to this Sources Sought announcement are due no later than 2:00 p.m. (Pacific Standard Time) on September 21, 2015.  Please address your response to Naval Facilities Engineering Command Southwest, Attn: Hal Hayes, Code RAQ20.HH, 1220 Pacific Highway, San Diego, CA 92132-5190. You may also email your response, in a PDF format, to harold.hayes@navy.mil.  Facsimile submittals will not be accepted.  All NAVFAC Southwest solicitations are posted on the Navy Electronic Commerce Online (NECO) website at https://www.neco.navy.mil and begin with N62473.
 

Additional Info: 
https://www.neco.navy.mil 
Contracting Office Address: 
N62473 - NAVFAC SOUTHWEST, CAPITAL IMPROVEMENTS CONTRACTS CORE, Attn: Code RAQ20, 1220 Pacific Highway, San Diego, CA 92132 
Point of Contact(s): 
Hal Hayes, Contract Specialist, Email: harold.hayes@navy.mil; 619-532-1251.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DON/NAVFAC/N68711AC/N6247315RFACP/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DON/NAVFAC/N68711AC/N6247315RFACP/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - CI 102 CCIM Market Analysis Course Equivalent]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[General Services Administration - I have the following course description from the CCIM website:<br />CI 102<br />Market Analysis for Commercial Investment Real Estate<br />You can't make intelligent real estate decisions without learning about the CCIM Strategic Analysis Model for investors, lenders, developers, brokers and other real estate professionals. Learn how financial analysis and market analysis are two separate, yet completely interrelated components of the strategic analysis process.
<p>Work with four case studies covering each of the major property types: office, industrial, multi-family, and retail. Each case study will build around the CCIM Strategic Analysis Model, which contains four components: Market and Competitive Analysis, Political and Legal Analysis, Location and Site Analysis, and Financial Analysis.</p>
<p>After completing this course, you will be able to:</p>
<p>Apply the CCIM Strategic Model to make a "go" or "no-go" investment decision.<br />Use state-of-the-art geospatial technology for analyses.<br />Examine real-world case studies of comprehensive analyses for each of the four major property types: office, industrial, residential, and retail.</p>
&nbsp;<br />Looking to see if there is another contractor that can offer a similar course or equivalent. &nbsp;&nbsp;]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/GSA/PBS/4PEY/EQ4PS-15-5000/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/GSA/PBS/4PEY/EQ4PS-15-5000/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - ArcGIS Software]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - SOURCES SOUGHT SYNOPSIS
<p>THIS IS A Sources Sought Notice ONLY. The U.S. Government currently intends to award a contract for ArcGIS Software Maintenance on an SOLE SOURCE basis, but is seeking vendors that may be able to perform this requirement in order to support a competitive procurement. Accordingly, the U.S. Government highly encourages all interested businesses (large and small) to respond to this sources sought synopsis. In addition, small businesses, in all socioeconomic categories (including, 8(a) Business Development Program, Small Disadvantage Business, Historically Underutilized Business Zone, Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned, Women-Owned Small Business concerns), must describe their identifying capabilities in meeting the requirements at a fair market price, i.e., information which may help support a set-aside.</p>
<p>The proposed sole source Firm Fixed Price (FFP) Purchase Order contract to Environmental Systems Research Institute, Inc. (ESRI) for ArcGIS Software Maintenance. The statutory authority for the sole source procurement is: 10 United States Code 2304(c)(1) as implemented in Federal Acquisition Regulation 6.302-1(a)(2)(iii), Only One Responsible Source and No Other Supplies or Services Will Satisfy Agency Requirements).</p>
<p>Government Requirements: GIS Software Maintenance</p>
<p>Integrates, stores, edits, analyzes, shares and displays geographic information for informed decision making. Software warranty provides for access to updates and fixes for coding conflicts and failures and to maintain the net-worthiness of the software. In support of ADCCP efforts to consolidate resources ArcGIS is provided from a central datacenter to reduce costs for physical footprint and logical consolidation of services. Impact-Capability of fulfilling the requirements OPORD 11-157 Army Data Center Consolidation Plan (ADCCP) may be severely hindered and prevent the success of the execution phase of OPORD 11-157.</p>
<p>Service agreement: In addition to license purchase:</p>
<p>One (1) year warranty on all items<br />Software and firmware updates/patches upon release<br />Priority service and privileges over non-Service Maintenance Agreement (SMA) holders<br />On call service technician for pre-determined events<br />Unlimited emergency service calls during normal business hours (M-F 8-5)</p>
<p>Software compatibility and interoperability:</p>
<p>The SW provided under this contract must be completely covered by service agreement terms for item:</p>
<p>10 1 52384 GIS0001MP<br />ArcGIS for Desktop Advanced (formerly ArcInfo) Concurrent Use Primary Maintenance</p>
<p>1010 1 86497 GIS0100MP<br />ArcGIS for Desktop Standard (formerly ArcEditor) Concurrent Use Primary Maintenance</p>
<p>2010 1 87194 GIS0200MP<br />ArcGIS for Desktop Basic (formerly ArcView) Concurrent Use Primary Maintenance</p>
<p>3010 1 87232 GIS0400MP<br />ArcGIS Spatial Analyst for Desktop Concurrent Use Primary Maintenance</p>
<p>4010 1 87198 GIS0300MP<br />ArcGIS 3D Analyst for Desktop Concurrent Use Primary Maintenance</p>
<p>5010 1 87236 GIS0500MP<br />ArcGIS Geostatistical Analyst for Desktop Concurrent Use Primary Maintenance</p>
<p>6010 1 98696 GIS0800MP<br />ArcGIS Publisher for Desktop Concurrent Use Primary Maintenance</p>
<p>7010 2 109215 GIS2200M<br />ArcGIS for Server Enterprise Advanced Up to Four Cores Maintenance</p>
<p>110101 114511 MT111<br />ArcPad Maintenance</p>
<p>Project timeline: 1 year (1 Oct 2015 - 30 Sep 2016)</p>
<p>This notice does not constitute a Request for Quote (RFQ)/Invitation for Bid (IFB)/Request for Proposal (RFP) or a promise to issue an RFQ, IFB or RFP in the future. This notice does not commit the U.S. Government to contract for any supply or service. Further, the U.S. Government is not seeking quotes, bids or proposals at this time and will not accept unsolicited proposals in response to this sources sought notice. The U.S. Government will not pay for any information or administrative costs incurred in response to this notice. Submittals will not be returned to the responder. A determination not to compete this requirement, based upon responses to this notice, is solely within the discretion of the Government. However, if a competitive solicitation is released, it will be synopsized on the Governmentwide Point of Entry. It is the responsibility of potential offerors to monitor the Governmentwide Point of Entry for additional information pertaining to this requirement. The NAICS code(s) is: 511210, Software Publishers and the SBA standard size is 500 employees.</p>
<p><br />In response to this sources sought, please provide:</p>
<p>1. Identify any condition or action that may be having the effect of unnecessarily restricting competition with respect to this acquisition and identify alternatives or solution solutions. Also contact the MICC Advocate for Competition, Dean Carsello, at dean.m.carsello.civ@mail.mil or 210-466-2419, if you believe that this action is unreasonably restricting competition. Include the subject of the acquisition, this announcement, and the MICC POC information from the Sources Sought Synopsis. Provide the specific aspects that unreasonably restrict competition and the rationale for such conclusion.</p>
<p>2. Name of the firm, point of contact, phone number, email address, DUNS number, CAGE code, identify business size (large business or a small business), and if applicable, a statement regarding small business status (including small business type(s)/certifications(s) such as SDB, 8(a), HUBZone, SDVOSB, WOSB, etc.) and the corresponding NAICS code.</p>
<p>3. Identify whether your firm is interested in competing for this requirement as a prime contractor or not. Identify subcontracting, joint ventures or teaming arrangement that will be pursued, if any.</p>
<p>4. Information in sufficient detail regarding previous experience (indicate whether as a prime contractor or subcontractor) on similar requirements (include size, scope, complexity, timeframe, government or commercial), pertinent certifications, etc., that will facilitate making a capability determination.</p>
<p>5. Information to help determine if the requirement (item or service) is commercially available, including pricing information, basis for the pricing information (e.g., market pricing, catalog pricing), delivery schedules, customary terms and conditions, warranties, etc.</p>
<p>6. Identify how the Army can best structure these contract requirements to facilitate competition, including competition among small business concerns.</p>
<p>7. Recommendations to improve the Army's approach/specifications/draft PWS/PRS to acquiring the identified items/services.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/8826edf23a19e5ae777ab092961cc7c1</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/8826edf23a19e5ae777ab092961cc7c1</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - RFI - Chief Data Office Support Services for the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau (CFPB)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Treasury - The Bureau of the Fiscal Service (BFS), on behalf of the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau (CFPB), is conducting Market Research in regards to Data, Data Governance, Business Intelligence, Privacy and Paperwork Reduction Act (PRA) Support.
<p>This is a Request for Information (RFI) only and does not constitute a request for a proposal nor commit the Government to make purchase of any supplies or services now or in the future. The information sought and provided will be used for planning purposes only (FAR 52.215-3). In addition, all documentation or information marked proprietary will be handled in accordance with applicable Government regulations. Please be advised that all submissions become property of the Government and will not be returned.</p>
<p>Support shall encompass the following:</p>
<p>1.0 OBJECTIVES</p>
<p>The Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act of 2010 ("Dodd-Frank Act"), Pub. L. 111-203, established the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau ("CFPB" or the "Bureau") to regulate the offering and provision of consumer products or services under federal consumer financial laws. Consistent with the purposes of the Dodd-Frank Act, the CFPB's mission is to establish and enforce clear, consistent rules for the financial marketplace, protect American families from unfair financial practices, and develop and implement a strategy to improve the financial literacy of consumers. For more background on the CFPB, please see http://www.consumerfinance.gov/the-bureau/.</p>
<p>The teams within the Chief Data Office (CDO) provide vital high-level data analytics to other groups at the Bureau. One of the mandates from the Dodd-Frank Act of 2011 is for the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau (CFPB) to monitor the financial marketplace to ensure financial institutions are complying with applicable laws and regulations. Data received from consumer complaints is one of the most common ways CFPB is able to analyze consumer complaint data. CFPB is able to monitor those complaints for evidence of patterns that may be warning signs of corporate wrong-doing, monitor trends in consumer financial markets such as credit cards and mortgages, as well as enable deeper insights into data, used to bring enforcement actions against companies that may be violating consumer financial laws.</p>
<p>The contractor shall provide support to the Chief Data Office to provide day-to-day data management and operations, high-level data analytics, visualizations as well as compliance with Privacy, Paper Reduction Act and Data Governance policies and laws. Contractor shall deliver reliable and readily available Data Scientists, Data Engineers, Data Governance Professionals, Business Intelligence Analysts, Privacy Specialists and PRA Specialists, as well as other resources that will allow the CFPB to fulfill its mission.</p>
<p>The CFPB will provide:</p>
<p>&bull; Detailed assignments and outlines covering key points. <br />&bull; CFPB subject matter experts as sources and collaborators.<br />&bull; Guidance on project length, purpose, audience, and use.<br />&bull; Clear deadlines for submissions and revisions.</p>
<p>2.0 CONTRACTOR QUALIFICATIONS &amp; SCOPE</p>
<p>WEB ANALYTICS<br />Contractor Qualifications <br />CFPB seeks Web Analytics Specialists with one (1) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Perform web analytics work, such as setting up customized dashboards, visualizations and reports using Tableau and experience in working with and managing Google Analytics accounts.<br />&bull; Assist in creating and executing enterprise-level digital analytics measurement strategies, including product conception and development and helping to define appropriate goals, engagement funnels, and conversions.<br />&bull; Establish a scalable reporting processes and standards for multiple digital products.<br />&bull; Meet with various CFPB stakeholders, as needed, to identify measurable goals and to provide actionable recommendations on how web products can meet their needs.<br />&bull; Prioritize web analytics requests, tasks and deliverables according to business needs and resources.<br />&bull; Work with front-end developers to create standard patterns for incorporating web measurement and analytics into various digital products. Ensure that these are implemented correctly and capture relevant metrics.<br />&bull; Provide expertise in Search Engine Optimization (SEO) technical implementation, as well as on and off-page optimizations. <br />Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />DATA OPERATIONS</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Data Operations Specialists with two (2) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Transfer data between environments such as external file transfer, internal databases and file systems.<br />&bull; Process and analyze data including but not limited to; financial market data, consumer complaints data and operational data that is under the jurisdiction of CFPB.<br />&bull; Perform data quality assurance tasks such as writing data validity, consistency and completeness checks.<br />&bull; Document and maintain processes associated with operational and data governance procedures, <br />&bull; Support business users with data management needs.<br />&bull; Develop &amp; analyze business requirements for implementing Extract, Transform, Load (ETL) techniques and data processing.<br />&bull; Work with data architects, business users and business managers to identify and develop data processing procedures, metrics and standards.<br />&bull; Manage PostgreSQL database configuration and orchestration.<br />&bull; Assist in development of procedures for securing massive amounts of data that is acquired on a frequent basis.<br />&bull; Manage partnerships with technical implementation teams.<br />&bull; Automate and support data ingest processes.<br />&bull; Microsoft Access frontend development.<br />&bull; Gather, maintain and update metadata.<br />Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />DATA ENGINEERING</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Engineers with one to five (1-5) or more years' experience, depending on the position.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Application development using programming languages such as Java, Python, Rust and Scala.<br />&bull; Complete software development lifecycle (SDLC) including writing requirements, implementation, testing, technical documentation and deployment of software applications.<br />&bull; Assemble data storage and processing infrastructure that allows working nimbly through extensive amounts of analytics data.<br />&bull; Design and build robust and scalable solutions for managing structured and unstructured data.<br />&bull; Develop and documenting service API's for the collection, cleansing, and storage of data.<br />&bull; Work with data scientists, database architects, data analysts, business users and business managers to identify and develop data processing use cases.<br />&bull; Work with data architects, business users and business managers to identify and develop data infrastructure, including data layers, API's, applications, and processing pipelines.<br />&bull; Orchestrate server environments on the data platform with tools such as Puppet and Ansible.<br />&bull; Develop interfaces and applications for accessing and visualizing data.<br />&bull; Develop line of business applications using Salesforce and SharePoint platforms for collecting and presenting data.<br />&bull; Work with business users and the data operations group to develop automated ETL routines to ingest disparate sources of data into SQL databases. <br />&bull; Work with other data architects to develop databases and data models for PostgreSQL, SQL Server using tools such as SQL PowerArchitect,<br />&bull; Document and maintain systems designs and operations manuals.<br />&bull; Complete software development lifecycle (SDLC) including writing requirements, implementation, testing, technical documentation and deployment of software applications.<br />&bull; Assemble data storage, processing, and integration infrastructure.<br />&bull; Provide automation of data management processes.<br />&bull; Tool development to support a team Data Architects, Data Analysts and Data Scientists.<br />&bull; Microsoft Access frontend development.<br />Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />DATA SCIENCE</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Data Scientists with two (2) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Statistical analysis and model development using programming languages such as Python, R and Julia.<br />&bull; Work with project stakeholders and software development team to develop data analysis and machine learning algorithms for business stakeholders. <br />&bull; Develop analytics solutions that are scalable, repeatable, effective and meet the expectations of the decision-makers and stakeholders.<br />&bull; Provide technical expertise for multiple advanced analytical techniques such as data mining, machine learning, geospatial analysis, natural language processing and predictive modeling.<br />&bull; Develop creative and accurate visualizations that communicate a story, trend, pattern etc., through collaborations with other team members.<br />&bull; Incorporate data from multiple sources (both relational and NoSQL environments) into the analytics workflow by writing appropriate querying and processing code.<br />&bull; Directly support users by developing advanced reporting and analytics.<br />&bull; Assisting users in choosing data sources and discovering new methods for achieving goals.<br />&bull; Work closely with a variety of teams to identify diagnose and resolve technical, strategic and analytical issues on behalf of business users.</p>
<p>Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />DATA ARCHITECTURE</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Data Architects with three (3) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope</p>
<p>&bull; Support development of complex logical and physical database design efforts using databases such as PostgreSQL, SQL Server, Hadoop, Spark, MPP and/or NoSQL platforms.<br />&bull; Identify and define data elements, development of user views, and generation of data models and Data Definition Language (DDL) using tool such as SQL Power Architect.<br />&bull; Develop rapid prototypes of robust high-volume production systems architectures. <br />&bull; Develop benchmarks, analyzes system bottlenecks and propose solutions to eliminate them. <br />&bull; Develop solutions for multiple large data warehouses/ operational data stores with good understanding of high scale or distributed Relational Database Management System (RDBMS), traditional RDBMS such as PostgreSQL, or Microsoft SQL. Server with hands on programming expertise in such environments.<br />&bull; Develop database procedures and functions using TSQL or PL/pgSQL.<br />&bull; Develop Extract Transform &amp; Load (ETL) processes using tools such as Talend, Pentaho, or SQL Server Integration Services (SSIS).</p>
<p>Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />PROJECT COORDINATION</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Project Coordinators with two to four (2-4) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Create detailed project plans for various initiatives.<br />&bull; Quickly identify and escalate issues, dependencies, or risks to team goals or project timelines.<br />&bull; Develop and present project status reports.<br />&bull; Work with staff to coordinate and prioritize work.<br />&bull; Assist team in meeting deadlines and fulfilling deliverables. <br />&bull; Manage projects using methodologies such as Agile, Waterfall. <br />Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />PROCESS MANAGEMENT</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Process Management Specialists with two to four (2-4) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Support the day-to-day management of Bureau-wide data management processes.<br />&bull; Identify and implement opportunities for process improvements.<br />&bull; Assist in preparing materials such as agendas and meeting minutes for formal meetings.<br />&bull; Write detailed, formal documents such as policies or operating procedures.<br />&bull; Serve as technical writing resource for large documentation efforts including but not limited to FAQs, process flows, reference guides, etc. in Microsoft Office, Visio, or similar software programs for process documentation.<br />&bull; Maintain formal documentation such as policies, standards and procedures in an organized, central repository.</p>
<p>Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />COMMUNICATION &amp; ENGAGEMENT</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Communications &amp; Engagement Specialists with two to four (2-4) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Design socialization and engagement strategies to raise awareness of data governance program and policy requirements.<br />&bull; Develop and distribute informational communications such as FAQs, training materials, or user guides.<br />&bull; Support the development and roll out of Bureau-wide training such as data governance, PRA and Privacy. <br />&bull; Train and educate Bureau staff, business analysts, data analysts, contractors, managers, and senior leaders on how to comply with all Bureau data governance policies and relevant information laws.<br />&bull; Maintain team wiki or similar medium for publishing information for team and Bureau-wide use.<br />&bull; Create and maintain internal webpages that provide information to Bureau staff about the various policies and procedures with respect to data governance.<br />&bull; Write drafts of FAQs, process flows, reference guides, and other materials in PowerPoint, MS Visio, etc. to help communicate data governance processes and best practices.<br />Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />DATA GOVERNANCE</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Data Governance Analysts with four to six (4-6) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Develop, review, and update policies and procedures.<br />&bull; Implementing data governance best practices across the Bureau.<br />&bull; Support Data Governance Team meetings and Bureau-wide data governance committees.<br />&bull; Assist in preparing materials for governance committee meetings including agendas, pre-read materials, and meeting minutes.<br />&bull; Develop reports for the executive audiences on data governance activities.<br />&bull; Write drafts of FAQs, process flows, reference guides, and other materials in PowerPoint, MS Visio, etc. to help communicate data governance processes and best practices.<br />&bull; Manage day-to-day process controls to ensure that use of Bureau data complies with all Bureau data governance policies and relevant laws. <br />&bull; Maintain all information governance policies, standards and procedures in an organized, central repository.<br />&bull; Support cross-Bureau processes for managing governance issues related to the intake, management, internal use, disclosure, and disposition of information across diverse functional areas. <br />&bull; Gather, maintain and update metadata.<br />&bull; Document purpose, scope, restrictions, and other policy requirements associated with Bureau data.<br />Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />BUSINESS INTELLIGENCE (BI)</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Business Intelligence Analysts with two (2) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope</p>
<p>&bull; Maintain up-to-date knowledge of best practices in data visualization and BI including but not limited to knowledge of cutting-edge features of Tableau.<br />&bull; Train users at the Bureau to implement best practices in Tableau.<br />&bull; Work with Bureau staff to develop requirements for Tableau reports. Develop prototype dashboards, visualizations and reports based on those requirements. Create and deploy dashboards, visualizations and reports in accordance with client needs.<br />&bull; Manage user requests for BI related software and software upgrades.<br />&bull; Field business-related questions through exploratory data analysis and ad-hoc reporting.<br />&bull; Identify relevant data sources and manipulate data to develop dashboards, visualizations and reports.<br />&bull; Extract and integrate data from multiple sources including relational and NoSQL environments into the reporting workflow by writing appropriate queries.<br />&bull; Coordinate with Data Operations and Data Architecture teams to identify requirements for data sources and optimize queries for specific reporting needs.<br />&bull; Assess and implement enhancements to the technical architecture to keep pace with changing business demands, scale and new software releases.<br />&bull; Work closely with a variety of teams to identify, diagnose and resolve technical issues on behalf of the Bureau's BI tool users.</p>
<p>Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p><br />PRIVACY</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Privacy Analysts with two (2) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Provide evaluations of information privacy policies and procedures. The Contractor shall advise the privacy team on pertinent developments in federal information privacy policy as it pertains to CFPB. When the Privacy team is called on to respond to newly proposed information privacy directives and similar policy documents, the Contractor shall assess the impact of these changes on a respective program and draft responses for review, approval, and submission by appropriate Government personnel.<br />&bull; Provide privacy support related to disclosure of data. The Contractor shall advise the privacy team on best practices, existing federal guidance, and recommendations around the disclosure of structured and unstructured data sets, including disclosure techniques, similar existing data releases, and risk profiles.<br />&bull; Preparing public facing or internal facing documents for publication, ensuring compliance with existing format or other requirements or best practices.<br />&bull; Preparing formal and informal process documents and training materials to demonstrate compliance with existing legal requirements or best practices.<br />&bull; Developing administrative controls to measure and monitor the progress of the work of the office, including maintaining a calendar of specific administrative deadlines.<br />&bull; Researching privacy issues related to existing or proposed projects, highlights possible risks related to collection, use, sharing, maintenance, or destruction of data.</p>
<p>Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>PAPERWORK REDUCTION ACT (PRA)</p>
<p>Contractor Qualifications<br />CFPB seeks Paperwork Reduction Act Specialists with three (3) or more years' experience.</p>
<p>Scope<br />&bull; Assist in the development of projects that support CFPB goals as assigned by the PRA Team leadership to perform initiatives designed to integrate the PRA and other information management laws, program requirements, CFPB data/information governance processes and best practices into all aspects of CFPB operations. <br />&bull; Assist in responding to inquiries from members or committees of Congress, media organizations, interest groups and the public on matters of the CFPB's information collection and PRA matters.<br />&bull; Collaborate with CFPB program offices or project teams addressing organization-wide information collection program and procedural matters. Uses knowledge of statutory, regulatory, or other requirements associated with an information collection program, e.g., PRA, Government Paperwork Elimination Act, 5 CFR 1320, Privacy Act, Electronic Government Act, and OMB Circular A-130 to manage the CFPB PRA program. Analyzes and work in the collection, analysis, evaluation, interpretation and dissemination of policy, legal, or program management information for CFPB. <br />&bull; Identifies PRA and other information management-related requirements contained in rulemakings and provides guidance on developing the PRA section of preambles to rulemakings and related supporting documentation. Assesses PRA implications for surveys, forms, studies, projects, usability studies, and other activities conducted by assigned CFPB divisions and assist in the preparation of any related PRA materials and managing the lifecycle of related information collection requests.<br />&bull; Provides day-to-day guidance for the development of PRA information collection procedures and guidance materials for CFPB-wide use. Takes a proactive role in analyzing paperwork reduction and duplicative reporting initiatives and develops recommendations for their implementation. Assist program office and project teams in preparing information collections and all relevant documentation for submission review by the CFPB's PRA officer.<br />&bull; Assist in preparing issue/position papers or summary reports with analysis and recommendations on reporting and information management program issues and initiatives, and developing guidelines or instructions for implementing approved initiatives.<br />&bull; Review all new statutes and regulations pertaining to CFPB and the PRA to ensure that information collection requests are properly reported and cleared.<br />&bull; Prepares PRA-related Federal Register notices, monitors for comments, and assists CFPB business units in preparing response to comments received on PRA matters.<br />&bull; Conducts research to determine novel approaches to PRA clearance needs and identify best practices with respect to PRA implantation in other Federal agencies.<br />&bull; Participates in meetings, on teams, or otherwise representing Technology and Innovation (T&amp;I) as a subject matter expert in a variety of forums requiring formal presentations and in-depth technical knowledge of program requirements in order to serve as a subject-matter expert. Manage relationships with other CFPB information governance functions including the CFPB's Privacy Office, Data Team, Cybersecurity team, FOIA Office, and Office of Records Management, and Section 508 Officer. Leverage those teams to develop and communicate best practices in information governance.<br />&bull; Provides status reports to the PRA Officer no less than weekly.</p>
<p><br />Deliverables<br />Weekly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit Weekly Status Reports to the COR each Friday by 5:00 pm EST throughout the life of the order. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain the below required information for the week ending on the submission Friday. The Weekly Status Reports shall contain, at a minimum, the following information:<br />&bull; Work Accomplishments<br />&bull; Hours Worked<br />&bull; Issues and Resolutions<br />&bull; Planned activities for the following week<br />&bull; Any issues/risks that may impact the quality or planned milestones</p>
<p>Monthly Status Reports - The Contractor shall electronically submit a Monthly Status Report on the last Friday of each month by 5:00 pm EST that summarizes the activities performed and deliverables submitted during that reporting period. Additionally, the Monthly Status Report shall contain a financial overview of the subsequent calls including invoiced and remaining amounts to date.</p>
<p>3.0 REQUEST FOR INFORMATION (RFI) REPLY DOCUMENTATION</p>
<p>If you are interested, please reply via email. Your reply shall include the following:<br />&bull; Documentation demonstrating your capability in providing the above services (scope) and deliverables, and in meeting the above contractor qualifications. <br />&bull; A short description, to include the agency, of three (3) previous or current projects in which you have or are providing these or similar services. <br />&bull; Describe your ability to maintain an ongoing pipeline of capable resources that can be deployed to support this work.<br />&bull; Identify any major risks of the recommended approach<br />&bull; How much time will you need to ramp up?</p>
<p>This documentation is limited to twelve (12) pages. Additional pages included may not be reviewed.</p>
<p>In addition, responses shall include a cover page with the following (this information will not be counted within the twelve (12) page limitation):</p>
<p>1. Company Name &amp; Address<br />2. Point of Contact Name/Telephone/Email</p>
<p>3. Size/Status: (Check all that apply)</p>
<p>____Small Business<br />____Veteran-Owned Small Business<br />____Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned Small Business<br />____Small Disadvantaged Business<br />____Woman-Owned Small Business<br />____Large Business<br />____8(a) Certified<br />____HUBZone Small Business</p>
<p>4. Data Universal Numbering System (DUNS) Number and Commercial and Government Entity (CAGE) Code.</p>
<p>5. NAICS Code(s) and PSC Code(s).</p>
<p>6. Do you have a GSA or other contract vehicle that covers these services? If yes, please provide the contract number.</p>
<p>The Bureau of the Fiscal Service is required to conduct Market Research as part of acquisition planning. The information obtained from market research will help the Bureau of the Fiscal Service arrive at the most suitable approach to acquire these services. This is not an invitation for bid, request for quote/proposal or other solicitation and in no way obligates The Bureau of the Fiscal Service to award a contract. The sole intent is to obtain capabilities for procurement planning purposes.</p>
<p>Responses shall be provided via email to purchasing@fiscal.treasury.gov ATTN: BBurnworth/CG by 1400 (2:00pm ET) 13 October 2015.</p>
<p>Thank you in advance for your input.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/TREAS/BPD/DP/RFI-CFPB-15-0097/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/TREAS/BPD/DP/RFI-CFPB-15-0097/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - B--Analysis of White-nose Syndrome Data]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Interior - IGF::OT::IGF  NORTHERN LONG-EARED BAT White Nose Syndrome data and GIS analysis]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOI/FWS/CGSWO/F15PS01257/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOI/FWS/CGSWO/F15PS01257/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - Geospatial Support Services - 100% ISBEE Set-aside]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Interior - Geospatial Support Services - 100% ISBEE Set-aside
Buy Indian Act 25 USC 47]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOI/BIA/RestonVA/A15PS01332/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOI/BIA/RestonVA/A15PS01332/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - Information Technology Enterprise Management Services (ITEMS): Enterprise Management /Cyber Security Services (EM/CSS)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Other Defense Agencies - The Office of Contract Services - IT Infrastructure &amp; Data Storage Division (OCSI) intends to competitively award a contract under the&nbsp;Information Technology Enterprise Management Services (ITEMS) Program for&nbsp;Enterprise Management /Cyber Security&nbsp;Services (EM/CSS) located at various NGA facilities. The solicitation is for full and open competition. NAICS Code: 541513. This requirement encompasses: 1) an Enterprise Service Desk (ESD), providing self-service and operator-assisted IT support across NGA; 2) a Command and Control Operations Management function serving as the central point for Information Technology Infrastructure (ITI) and Production Systems situational awareness on all domains; 3) a Cyber Security Operations Cell (CSOC) serving as the central point for security incident detection, cyber intelligence collection and analysis, response, investigation, and reporting through the use of firewalls, intrusion detection/prevention system, malware detection, forensics, auditing, and other capabilities and 4) the development and collection of business intelligence information to support enterprise management process and product improvement. Estimated start date is on or about 13 May 16. RELEASE of solicitation, HM0476-16-R-0003, is scheduled on or about 02 Oct 15. Inquiries about the solicitation will not be responded to until the solicitation has been released. The point of contact is Rose M. Schultz, email: <a href="mailto:rose.m.schultz@nga.mil">rose.m.schultz@nga.mil</a>. Interested offerors must follow the instructions below for any further announcements to this requirement. No hard copies will be provided.
<p>In order to view this effort you must have a TS/SCI clearance as this effort is being posted on the classified ARC website. Access to this effort will require a classified ARC account by visiting <a href="https://acq.westfields.net">https://acq.westfields.net</a> and clicking on the "Register" link at the top right of the page. Be sure to include your classified email address as you will not be able to access your classified account without it. Once you have finished the registration process on the unclassified system and validated your account by clicking the link you were sent via email, you need to wait 2 business days for your classified ARC account to be automatically created.</p>
<p>Once you have waited 2 business days, you will be able to log into your classified account using the same email and password you used on the unclassified system. This will bring you to a page where you can click a button to send yourself a verification email to the classified email account you listed when creating your unclassified account. To log into the classified ARC, visit <a href="https://acq.nro.ic.gov/">https://acq.nro.ic.gov/</a>&nbsp;from a TS network such as NMIS, NSAnet, CWE, AWAN, CWAN, JWICS, etc. If you do not have access to a TS network but possess TS/SCI clearance, you can arrange a visit to our reading room by calling 703-230-6100.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/00b79442ce7f8bc92a590d8495cf2a16</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/00b79442ce7f8bc92a590d8495cf2a16</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - 70--InterAct Computer Aided Dispatch License Renewals]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - This Sources Sought notice is for informational and planning purposes only.  The information from this market research is for planning purposes only and will assist the Government in planning its acquisition strategy. <br>  <br> This is not a Request for Proposal (RFP) or a Request for Quotation (RFQ); it is strictly a Request for Information (RFI) as defined in Federal Acquisition Regulation (FAR) 15.201(e). NO SOLICITATION DOCUMENT EXISTS. This RFI is for planning purposes only and shall not be construed as a RFP or as an obligation on the part of the Government for follow-on acquisition. Responses to this notice are not offers and will not be accepted by the Government to form a binding contract. Responders are solely responsible for all expenses associated with responding to this RFI. All information received in response to this RFI that is marked as proprietary will be handled accordingly. <br>  <br> This is strictly market research and the Government will not entertain questions concerning this market research. The NAICS Code for this requirement is 511210 software publishers.  The intent of this notice is determine the availability of qualified sources technically capable of providing the following Commercial Off the Shelf software.   <br>  <br>  <br> The Government requires renewal of InterAct Computer Aided Dispatch (CAD) software licenses. <br>  <br> Specifically, the Government requires renewal of: <br>  <br>  	CAD-CLNT-DISP <br>  	Annual Support/Maintenance for InterAct CAD Software <br>  <br>  	CAD-CLNT-RPRT <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterActCAD Report Module <br>  <br>  	GEO-CLNT-SL <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterAct GIS Client Licenses in Dispatch <br>  <br>  	CAD-SRVR-LIC <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterCAD Server Software License <br>  <br>  	GIS-SVR <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterActGIS Servers Software License <br>  <br>  	CAD-SVR-WBCAD <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterAct WebCAD Server Module (10 Clients) <br>  <br>  	CAD-MDC <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterAct Mobile CAD User Access License - CAD access for MDTs <br>  <br>  	CAD-CLNT-NCIC <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterAct CAD NCIC access software Query Only Client License <br>  <br>  	CAD-SRVR-NCIC <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for InterAct CAD NCIC Query Only Server software Module <br>  <br>  	GEO-MDC <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for GIS Software for MDT's/ InterAct GEO 911 MDC Software License <br>  <br>  	CAD-SVR-WBCAD-INCID-M <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for WEB CAD Software/ InterAct CAD web Server Module Incident Entry - allows for incident entry from WEB CAD <br>  <br>  	MC-CLNT-M <br>  	InterAct Mobile Client for Fire Units <br>  <br>  	GIS-SVR-AVL <br>  	Annual Support Maintenance for AVL Software <br>  <br>  	MC-SERVER (up to 20 units) <br>  	MC-SERVER (up to 20 units) <br>  <br>  	MC-CLNT-AVL-M <br>  	InterActMobile AVL Mobile Client License <br>  <br>  	GEO-CLNT-REV-M <br>  	InterActGIS Reverse GEO Coding - converts phase ii locations to physical address <br>  <br>  	CAD-RMS-INT-M <br>  	InterAct Server to Server Interface to communicate with County for NCIC <br>  <br>  	IA-HDM <br>  	Annual Hardware Help Desk Support <br>  <br>  <br> The Government is seeking vendors who may be able to perform this requirement in order to support a competitive procurement.   <br> The Government is seeking responses to this sources sought synopsis from all interested businesses capable of providing the requirement, ensure your response indicates if you are an authorized reseller/distributor of the required software licenses and support renewals. <br>   <br> Small businesses, in all socioeconomic categories (including, 8(a) Business Development Program, Historically Underutilized Business Zone, Service Disabled Veteran-Owned, Women-Owned Small Business, etc.) are highly encouraged to identify capabilities in meeting the requirements at fair market prices. Please indicate your business size (Small, Large etc...) in your responses.  Furthermore, indicate in response if you are able to provide the proposed requirement under an existing GSA, DOD ESI, CHESS, NASA SEWP, et al contract mechanism. <br>  <br> All responsible sources may submit a capability statement, proposal, or quotation, which shall be considered by the agency. All responsible parties that feel they can provide this product should forward their capabilities in writing to the designated contracting points of contact - EMAILS ONLY. <br>  <br> Contracting Point of Contact:  Cori Duford at email  cori.j.duford.mil@mail.mil <br> Again, please note that this is not a solicitation but a sources sought only.  <br>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/b42b07149d18137c19d706a9f8a46968</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/b42b07149d18137c19d706a9f8a46968</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - DATAVIEWER PROGRAMMING]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - PROGRAMMING SERVICES TO ADD ADDITIONAL FUNCTIONALITY TO THE EXISTING GIS DATAVIEWER MODULE IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE SOW.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/00183a9a5495ab838d14b8b492c928b8</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/00183a9a5495ab838d14b8b492c928b8</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - EV Market Ops, EV Power, EV Energy Map]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of Justice - The Department of Justice, Justice Management Division, Library Staff, intends to procure from ABB Enterprise Software access to EV Market Ops, EV Power with New Entrants, and EV Energy Map for the Antitrust Division Library. The requirements of the Antitrust Division Library include the ability to visualize LMP market data; access to integrated market data that is updated daily with aerial imagery and the most accurate geospatial data; Data coverage should include multiple layers for the natural gas industry, coal industry, electric industry, environmental issues, and should include the ability to map the countries, major cities, states, zip codes, urbanized areas, cities, major roads, rivers, lakes, aquifers, stream gauging stations, and census tracks. They also require a comprehensive view of North America power markets. Data coverage should include electric company overviews, plant operations statistics, utility operations statistics, daily power prices, forward power prices, short term price forecasts, wholesale transaction details, wholesale power sales, Canadian imports &amp; exports, retail transaction details, utility regulatory financials, statement of income &amp; cash flow and daily stock prices for the SEC 10k &amp; 10Q, monthly capabilities at peak demand, and net energy for load &amp; peak demand. The Antitrust Library also requires hourly data for generation (US and parts of Canada), heat rates, emissions (EPA CEMS), loads and prices (FERC and ISO). Data coverage should include ISO real-time and day ahead LMP pricing, ISO ancillary pricing, ISO zonal load data, ISO total load data, control area actual peak load data, historical demand by zone, market marginal costs, ISO hub and zone definitions, ISO zonal load forecasts, control area forecast peak load data, forecast demand by zone, annual &amp; monthly unit operations summary, hourly unit generation, unit capacity blocks, unit ramp rates, GADS availability report, GADS outage cause report, unit emission control installations, unit level NOx, S02 and C02 total emissions for the US and Canada, and the unit level emission allowance holdings. Market research shows that ABB is the only company that can provide all of the required information. The statutory authority for the proposed procurement is 41 U.S.C. 253(c) (1), only one responsible source. The solicitation will not be distributed on the General Services Administration website (www.fbo.gov ). This is not a formal solicitation, however, interested concerns must respond within ten (10) days from the date of this synopsis with written documentation, detailed data and pricing information that clearly demonstrates their ability to perform the requirement. Responses received as a result of this notice of intent shall be considered solely for the purpose of determining whether to conduct a competitive procurement. Responses will not be considered as either bids or proposals. A determination by the Government not to open this requirement to competition based upon the written responses to this notice is solely within the discretion of the Government. Responses to this notice must be submitted to marla.chesler@usdoj.gov.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOJ/JMD/LIBSTAFF/DJJ-LIB-16-2/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOJ/JMD/LIBSTAFF/DJJ-LIB-16-2/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - EV Market Ops, EV Power, EV Energy Map]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of Justice - The Department of Justice, Justice Management Division, Library Staff, intends to procure from ABB Enterprise Software access to EV Market Ops, EV Power with New Entrants, and EV Energy Map for the Antitrust Division Competition and Policy Section. The requirements of the Antitrust Division&nbsp;include the ability to visualize LMP market data; access to integrated market data that is updated daily with aerial imagery and the most accurate geospatial data; Data coverage should include multiple layers for the natural gas industry, coal industry, electric industry, environmental issues, and should include the ability to map the countries, major cities, states, zip codes, urbanized areas, cities, major roads, rivers, lakes, aquifers, stream gauging stations, and census tracks. They also require a comprehensive view of North America power markets. Data coverage should include electric company overviews, plant operations statistics, utility operations statistics, daily power prices, forward power prices, short term price forecasts, wholesale transaction details, wholesale power sales, Canadian imports &amp; exports, retail transaction details, utility regulatory financials, statement of income &amp; cash flow and daily stock prices for the SEC 10k &amp; 10Q, monthly capabilities at peak demand, and net energy for load &amp; peak demand. The Antitrust Library also requires hourly data for generation (US and parts of Canada), heat rates, emissions (EPA CEMS), loads and prices (FERC and ISO). Data coverage should include ISO real-time and day ahead LMP pricing, ISO ancillary pricing, ISO zonal load data, ISO total load data, control area actual peak load data, historical demand by zone, market marginal costs, ISO hub and zone definitions, ISO zonal load forecasts, control area forecast peak load data, forecast demand by zone, annual &amp; monthly unit operations summary, hourly unit generation, unit capacity blocks, unit ramp rates, GADS availability report, GADS outage cause report, unit emission control installations, unit level NOx, S02 and C02 total emissions for the US and Canada, and the unit level emission allowance holdings. Market research shows that ABB is the only company that can provide all of the required information. The statutory authority for the proposed procurement is 41 U.S.C. 253(c) (1), only one responsible source. The solicitation will not be distributed on the General Services Administration website (www.fbo.gov ). This is not a formal solicitation, however, interested concerns must respond within ten (10) days from the date of this synopsis with written documentation, detailed data and pricing information that clearly demonstrates their ability to perform the requirement. Responses received as a result of this notice of intent shall be considered solely for the purpose of determining whether to conduct a competitive procurement. Responses will not be considered as either bids or proposals. A determination by the Government not to open this requirement to competition based upon the written responses to this notice is solely within the discretion of the Government. Responses to this notice must be submitted to marla.chesler@usdoj.gov.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOJ/JMD/LIBSTAFF/DOJ-LIB-16-2/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOJ/JMD/LIBSTAFF/DOJ-LIB-16-2/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - A&E Services, Mapping and Surveying IDIQ Contract]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - INDEFINITE DELIVERY INDEFINTE QUANTITY (IDIQ) TYPE ARCHITECT-ENGINEER<br />CONTRACT(S) FOR SURVEY ENGINEERING, MAPPING, AND RELATED SERVICES WITHIN THE MEMPHIS AND VICKSBURG DISTRICTS OF THE MISSISSIPPI VALLEY DIVISION OF THE U.S. ARMY CORPS OF ENGINEERS; BUT MAY ALSO BE USED ANYWHERE WITHIN THE GEOGRPAHICAL BOUNDARIES OR OTHER MISSIONS OF THE 6 DISTRICTS INCLUDED IN THE MISSISSIPPI VALLEY DIVISION.
<p><br />1. CONTRACT INFORMATION: This pre-solicitation notice is for interested firms to<br />submit their SF330 by 19 Oct 2015, 1330 hours. Firms will be selected for negotiations based on demonstrated competence and qualifications for the required work. <strong>This is not a Request for Proposal (RFP).</strong> The proposed procurement listed herein will be set aside for small business concerns and submittals from only small businesses will be considered. A firm is considered to be a small business concern if the firm's average annual receipts from the preceding three fiscal years do not exceed $15.0 Million. The services to be procured under this announcement are classified in North American Industry Classification System Code 541370. This contract is being procured in accordance with the Brooks A-E Act as implemented in FAR Subpart 36.6.</p>
<p>More than one contract may be awarded as a result of this announcement. It is the district's intent to award at least two <strong>(2) IDIQ contracts to two (2) small businesses.</strong> Contracts may be awarded by Memphis and/or Vicksburg Districts. Work will be accomplished under separate Indefinite Delivery Indefinite Delivery Type Contracts NTE $5,000,000 with a performance period of not to exceed five (5) years for each contract. Work will be issued by negotiated firm-fixed price task orders. Allocation of task orders will be based on the following factors: specialized knowledge or expertise which would enhance execution, past experience or knowledge of the locality, availability of appropriate staff, performance on previous task orders, magnitude of task order relative to remaining contract capacity and equitable workload distribution.</p>
<p>2. PROJECT INFORMATION: A-E service capabilities are required for various civil works projects and support for other agencies. Work may be comprised of topographic surveys, hydrographic surveys, dredge material measurement surveys, monitoring surveys, construction layout surveys, geodetic control surveys, mobile laser scanning, boundary and cadastral surveys, GPS surveying and mapping. Firms with demonstrated specialized experience, competence and qualifications pertinent to survey engineering, geodetic surveying, land and boundary surveying, hydrographic surveying, mapping (Microstation and InRoads capability required) and related services are desired for consideration. The contract services performed under this contract may support the Government revetment construction project along the Mississippi River located in the Memphis, Vicksburg, and New Orleans Districts. Work areas will normally be within the boundaries of the Memphis District (which includes portions of AR, IL, KY, MO, MS, and TN) but work assignments may be made in other Corps of Engineers Districts. The first contract is anticipated to be awarded on/about January 2016, with the contract period of service not to exceed five years from the contract award date, or expenditure of the contract amount, whichever occurs first. Award of any subsequent contracts will be based on projected District workload. Work to be performed is subject to satisfactory negotiation of individual task orders with no one task order to exceed neither $1,000,000 nor the accumulated total of task orders to exceed $5,000,000 during the five year term of the contract.</p>
<p>3. SELECTION CRITERIA: Selection criteria will be based on the following<br />considerations and are listed in descending order of importance (first by major criterion and then by each sub-criterion). <strong>Criteria A through E are primary. Criteria F through H are secondary and will only be used as a quote mark tie-breaker, quote mark if necessary, in ranking the most highly qualified firms. (A) Specialized Experience:</strong> The selected firm shall have the capability to provide digital surveying and mapping data in readable and fully operational format on the District's Computer Aided Design and Drafting (CADD) or GIS Systems. Data submission shall be required in native Microstation design files (.DGN), InRoads digital terrain model files (.DTM), InRoads alignment files (.ALG), and occasionally in GIS (.SHP and Personal Geodatabases) formats. Firms with demonstrated specialized experience, competence and qualifications pertinent to surveying are desired for consideration. Firms considered to be highly qualified will be required to furnish at least five fully equipped survey crews with four-wheel drive vehicles and approved electronic total station surveying instruments and related equipment. Additional crews may be required. Highly qualified firms shall be required to have both code and carrier phase L1/L2 GPS receivers. A firm will be considered if it can demonstrate the capability to provide these personnel and equipment by such means as an increase in staffing, subcontracting, or joint venture. At least two, with a possibility of four, fully automated hydrographic survey systems (single fathometer) operational on a boat not less than 21 feet in length equipped with Coast Guard Radio Beacon DGPS shall be required in addition to ground based crews. Each hydrographic and topographic party provided shall have the capability to collect and process each survey performed at the work site (plot cross sections, compute volumes, revetment re-designs, etc.). One electronic hydrographic sweep system (no booms) on a boat with a length no greater than 30 feet (trailerable) with Coast Guard Radio Beacon DGPS will be required either through in-house capabilities or subcontracting. Additional conventional hydrographic systems may also be required where GPS is unavailable. Firms considered to be highly qualified shall be required to show specialized experience in performing all types of surveys as stated above and subsequent data reduction and plotting utilizing state-of-the-art computer technology. <strong>(B) Professional qualifications:</strong> The prime firm and/or its subcontractor(s) (hereinafter referred to collectively as "firm") must have registered Professional Civil Engineers and Land Surveyors on staff. The firm should indicate professional recognition, professional associations, advanced training, certification, and specific work experience of key personnel. The firm should emphasize the qualifications and experience of its management personnel in survey engineering, hydrographic, topographic and geodetic surveying. <strong>(C) Capacity:</strong> Firms must demonstrate sufficient personnel in the disciplines necessary to conduct the required work in an efficient manner. <strong>(D) Past Performance:</strong> Performance evaluations on previous contracts with Government agencies, including DOD, and private industry in terms of cost control, quality of work, and compliance with performance schedules will be considered. Additional consideration will also be given to firms that have above average performance evaluations in the type of work described in (A) above. <strong>(E) Knowledge of locality:</strong> A firm's knowledge of the locality will be given consideration. The firm should demonstrate its knowledge of the geographical and topographical features of the area within the boundaries of the Memphis District, and its familiarity with the major rivers and tributaries of the area all as related to survey engineering, mapping, and related services. <strong>(F) Geographic proximity</strong> to Memphis, Tennessee, and/or Vicksburg, Mississippi. <strong>(G) Small Business Considerations:</strong>Extent of participation of Small Business and Small Disadvantaged Business, in the proposed contract will be given consideration. Firms should list the total amount of the contract anticipated to be subcontracted, name and amount anticipated for small business, name and amount anticipated for small disadvantaged business and name and amount anticipated for women-owned small business. <strong>(H) Volume of DOD Work:</strong> DoD contract awards in the past 12 months. The greater the awards the lesser the consideration. In the final selection process, the most highly qualified firms will be interviewed. The contract will be awarded on or about December 2015.</p>
<p>4. SUBMISSION REQUIREMENTS: Interested firms having the capabilities for this work must submit one paper copy and one electronic copy (in PDF format submitted on a CD) of SF 330 along with a copy of part II of each sub-consultant's SF 330 to U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Memphis District, ATTN: Thomas E Mercer, CECT-MVM, Memphis District, Corps of Engineers, Room 669, 167 North Main Street, Memphis, TN 38103-1894, no later than 13:30 PM (Central) 19 Oct 15. Include both the solicitation number and the company's DUNS number on all submittals.</p>
<p>Note the following restrictions on submittal - Resumes of key persons, specialists and individual consultants (Section E) anticipated for this contract will be limited to a maximum of 20 typed pages. Pages in excess of the maximum of 20 will be discarded and not used in the evaluations. Additional information (Section H) will be limited to a maximum of 20 pages. All telephone calls should be directed to Mr. William Snapp, (901) 544-3237 or email at william.b.snapp@usace.army.mil . <br /><br />*** APPOINTMENTS WILL NOT BE SCHEDULED FOR THE PURPOSE OF<br />DISCUSSING THIS ANNOUNCEMENT *** This is not a Request for Proposal. A fee<br />proposal will be requested at a later date. **** NOTE: Contractors must be registered with the appropriate SBA Office.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA66/W912EQ-15-R-0008/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA66/W912EQ-15-R-0008/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - ArcGIS software licenses and support.]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of Transportation - In accordance with the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) Acquisition Management System (AMS) paragraph 3.2.2.4, the purpose of this announcement is to inform industry of the basis for the FAA's decision to contract with AVL – North America, via single source procedures.

This procurement is in support of the FAA’s IT Business Office. The award will be for the procurement of ArcGIS software licenses and support.  
The Esri technology provides the FAA the ability to fulfill the FAA’s airspace mission in ways that were not previously possible and its enablement and standardization are also an important component of overarching DOT-wide goals. The Esri ELA grants the FAA the capacity to harmoniously combine numerous similarly oriented initiatives which can be leveraged by many FAA programs as well as outside government organizations to meet mission requirements. This Geographic Information System (GIS) or geospatial technology is not offered by other software that is compatible with FAA Systems.
Esri, Inc. developed this software and the Government has no rights in design or development of this source code. In 2008, an Enterprise License Agreement was established between the FAA and Esri. Esri does have authorized resellers and business partners. 
Accordingly, a competitive solicitation is not available for this procurement. The FAA is not seeking or accepting unsolicited proposals. The FAA is not liable for any costs associated with the preparing of a response to this announcement.  Any questions or comments about this announcement must be directed to Stephanie Taylor at stephanie.a.taylor@faa.gov, no later than 12 p.m. (local time) on September 25, 2015.   All inquiries must be submitted in writing.  Phone calls will not be entertained.


										
										If you're viewing this announcement from a source other than Federal Aviation Administration Contract Opportunities (FAACO), visit https://faaco.faa.gov/index.cfm/announcement/view/22576 to view the original announcement.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOT/FAA/WJHTC/22576/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DOT/FAA/WJHTC/22576/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - Repair BLDG 36, 2B East]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Other Defense Agencies - REPAIR AREA, BLDG 36, SECTION 2B EAST, ST. LOUIS SITE<br /><br />Work consists of furnishing all plant, labor, materials, equipment and performing all work in strict accordance with those specifications, schedules and drawings forming parts thereof, for the interior repair and alterations.<br /><br />The total affected area is approximately 7,660 square feet. The work includes minor demolition of walls, ceilings, floor finishes, mechanical and electrical demolition. New work includes but is not limited to new walls, doors, ceilings, finishes, office furniture, conference room furniture, break room furniture, system furniture, fire protection, mechanical and electrical.<br /><br />The work shall be performed by a general contractor. All work shall be accomplished in strict accordance with applicable NGA, EPA, NFPA, and OSHA requirements.<br /><br />The performance period for this project is 154 calendar days from the date of the Notice to Proceed. The contractor will not be allowed to start on-site performance before the 30th day after the Notice to Proceed is issued.<br /><br />The approximate cost of this project is between $500,000 and $1,000,000.<br /><br />The project is 100 percent set-aside for small business. The NAICS code for this project is 236220, size standard $36.5M. This work is located at the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency facilities at 3200 South Second Street, St. Louis, Missouri 63118-3399.<br /><br />All sources interested in acquiring this solicitation shall register on fbo.gov as an interested vendor. Drawings and Specifications will be available for purchase from ARC Document Solutions, 2665 Scott Ave, St. Louis, MO 63103, PHONE: 314-231-5025 AND FAX: 816-326-0946. <br /><br />All responsible sources may submit a bid, which shall be considered by the agency. All contractors must have a current registration on www.sam.gov (formerly known as the CCR) under the applicable NAICS Code to be eligible for an award.<br /><br />An IFB will be posted on or about 07/29/2015 with bids being due on or about 08/31/2015. A site visit will be scheduled around the middle of August.<br />]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/ODA/NIMA/PCSL-13/HM157515B0004/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/ODA/NIMA/PCSL-13/HM157515B0004/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - ESMARTS Follow-On RFI]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Other Defense Agencies - The National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA), in support of the Enterprise Technical Services Office, is seeking information in the form of a capability statement on the level of interest, capabilities and qualifications of small and large businesses to provide support for the follow-on effort to the Enterprise Support to Management and Resources for Technical Services (ESMARTS) Contract.&nbsp;<br /><br />
<p>The details pertaining to this requirement and the request for information (RFI) have been posted to the Classified ARC, which is only accessible to those with a Top Secret/SCI (TS/SCI) clearance. &nbsp;If you have a TS/SCI email address and network, but have not previously registered for the Classified ARC, you can do so by following the steps below:<br /><br /><br />1. On an unclassified system, go to https://acq.westfields.net.<br />2. Click 'Register' on the top right corner of the page, which will provide you first with an unclassified ARC account.<br />3. When you register, use your classified email address as you will not be able to access your classified account without it.<br />4. Validate your account by clicking on the link you will be sent via email.<br />5. Your classified ARC account will be created and accessible after two (2) business days.<br />6. After two (2) business days have passed, you will be able to log into your classified account using the same email and password you used to register on the unclassified system. &nbsp;<br />7. Access the classified IC ARC via https://acq.nro.ic.gov only using a classified system up to TS/SCI (NMIS, NSAnet, CWE, AWAN, CWAN, JWICS, etc).<br />8. You can find this announcement under 'NGA Announcements', listed as ESMARTS Follow-On. &nbsp;The same RFI#, HM028516R0001, is also referenced.<br /> 9. If you do not have access to a TS network, but possess a TS/SCI clearance, you can arrange a visit to our reading room by calling 703-230-6100.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/45ad50d4bbdc132f6655e2b59b9239b2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/45ad50d4bbdc132f6655e2b59b9239b2</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - Command, Control, Communications & Protection, Ashore, Public Safety Network (PSNet) Information Technology (IT) Solutions and Services.]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Defense Information Systems Agency - &nbsp;
<p style="TEXT-ALIGN: center" align="center">SOURCES SOUGHT ANNOUNCEMENT</p>
<p style="TEXT-ALIGN: center" align="center">MAC 0110 <br style="mso-special-character: line-break" /><br style="mso-special-character: line-break" /></p>
<p><br />The<span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold"> </span>COMMANDER, NAVY INSTALLATIONS COMMAND (CNIC), <span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold">is seeking sources for </span>Command, Control, Communications &amp; Protection (C3P) Ashore (N61) Public Safety Network (PSNet) Information Technology (IT) Solutions and Services.<strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal"></strong></p>
<p style="TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ">&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal"><br />CONTRACTING OFFICE ADDRESS: </strong></p>
<p><br />DISA/DITCO-SCOTT-PL83</p>
<p>2300 EAST DRIVE</p>
<p>SCOTT AFB IL 62225-5406</p>
<p><span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold"><br />Questions regarding this announcement shall be submitted in writing by e-mail to </span></p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal">John Schiffhauer</strong>, Contract Specialist, <a href="mailto:John.P.Schiffhauer.civ@mail.mil">John.P.Schiffhauer.civ@mail.mil</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;">,</span> phone: 618-229-9481<span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold">.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>Verbal questions will NOT be accepted.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>Questions will be answered by posting answers to </span>Federal Business Opportunities <span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold">website; accordingly, questions shall NOT contain proprietary or classified information. The Government does not guarantee that questions received after 4:00 PM </span>Eastern Daylight Time (EDT)<span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold"> October 8, 2015 will be answered.</span></p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal">&nbsp;<br /></strong><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal">INTRODUCTION:</strong></p>
<p><br />This is a SOURCES SOUGHT TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION to determine the availability and technical capability of small businesses (including the following subsets, Small Disadvantaged Businesses, HUB Zone Firms; Certified 8(a), Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned Small Businesses and Woman Owned Small Business) to provide the required products and/or services.</p>
<p><br />The Commander, <span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp;</span>Navy Installations Command is seeking information for potential sources to provide technical, analytical and equipment-related IT support services required to achieve CNIC's mission critical Protection Ashore, Public Safety/Anti-Terrorism (ATFP), and Emergency Management missions, functions, and requirements <span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold">(both NIPR and SIPR)</span>.</p>
<p><span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold"><br />This includes the management of CNIC's enterprise network environment, which is the Public Safety Network (PSNet), a Global Information Grid-compliant network built upon Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) technology.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>PSNet is a specific network dedicated to providing end-to-end support of Life and Safety Command Control (C2) applications and systems for Navy installation first responders including:</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="tab-stops: 22.5pt"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><br />Real-time delivery </span>of radio voice Enterprise Land Mobile Radio (ELMR), surveillance video Virtual Perimeter Monitoring Systems (VPMS), sensor and alarm data (Navy Emergency Response Management Systems (NERMS), Consolidated Emergency Response System (CERS), Base Telecommunications Infrastructure (BTI), and Wide Area Communications Network (WACN);</p>
<p style="tab-stops: 22.5pt"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><br />Smart Grid transport</span> including delivery of advanced meter data Advanced Metering Infrastructure (AMI), Supervisory Control and Data Acquisition (SCADA) data, and Industrial Control Systems (ICS);</p>
<p style="tab-stops: 22.5pt"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><br />Disaster Recovery</span> and Continuity of Operations (COOP);</p>
<p style="tab-stops: 22.5pt"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><br />Connectivity to entry control points</span>, Pass &amp; ID, Local Dispatch Center (LDC), Regional Dispatch Center (RDC), Regional Operation Center (ROC), and Emergency Operation Center (EOC) in support of Automated Vehicle Gates (AVG) programs;</p>
<p style="tab-stops: 22.5pt"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><br />Command, Control, Communications, Computers &amp; Intelligence (C4I Suite)</span>, allowing regional commanders to gather information, gain situational awareness and exercise control over forces across the entirety of the Force Protection and Emergency Management timelines;</p>
<p style="tab-stops: 22.5pt"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><br />Giant Voice, mass warning and notification system at Navy installation</span>s. Giant Voice consists of exterior and interior speakers and sirens to broadcast emergency communications to the Navy community within its jurisdiction; and for the integration of physical security and Chemical, Biological, Radiological, Nuclear and Enhanced Conventional Weapons (CBRNE) into a single interoperable network.</p>
<p><span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold"><br />This support provides for IT solutions and support services, including technical, analytical and equipment procurement/installation (e.g., Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) circuits to provide base-to-base connectivity) in support of the mission-critical Protection Ashore, Public Safety/ATFP, and Emergency Management Operations/Programs cited above.</span></p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal"><br />DISCLAIMER:</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><br />THIS SOURCES SOUGHT IS FOR INFORMATIONAL PURPOSES ONLY. THIS IS NOT A REQUEST FOR PROPOSAL.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>IT DOES NOT CONSTITUTE A SOLICITATION AND SHALL NOT BE CONSTRUED AS A COMMITMENT BY THE GOVERNMENT.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>RESPONSES IN ANY FORM ARE NOT OFFERS AND THE GOVERNMENT IS UNDER NO OBLIGATION TO AWARD A CONTRACT AS A RESULT OF THIS ANNOUNCEMENT.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>NO FUNDS ARE AVAILABLE TO PAY FOR PREPARATION OF RESPONSES TO THIS ANNOUNCEMENT.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>ANY INFORMATION SUBMITTED BY RESPONDENTS TO THIS TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION IS STRICTLY VOLUNTARY.</p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal"><br />CONTRACT/PROGRAM BACKGROUND: </strong></p>
<p>Contract Number:<strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal"> </strong>GS-06F-0621Z/HC1028-13-F-0245<br /><br />Contract Type: (FFP)</p>
<p style="MARGIN-TOP: 12pt"><span style="FONT-FAMILY: 'Times New Roman', 'serif'; FONT-SIZE: 12pt"><br />Incumbent and their size: (ECS Federal, Large Business)(initially the tasking was solicited and awarded as a small business, that company was later absorbed by ECS Federal, which is a large business).<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; <br /></span></span><br /><br />Method of previous acquisition: (Total Small Business Set Aside)</p>
<p><br />Description of the current program/effort.</p>
<p><br />The mission of the CNIC Chief Information Officer (CIO), Code N6, is to execute Department of Navy and Navy Chief Information Officer policies and programs and to provide IT services required to support the mission of the Command.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>The CNIC N6 organization is tasked to provide an integrated framework of technology aimed at efficiently performing the business of CNIC.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>The CNIC N6 organization manages all aspects of the systems, and the supporting infrastructure, providing critical systems and infrastructure support enterprise wide.</p>
<p><br />CNIC N61 is responsible for C3P Ashore and headquarters (HQ) activities with significant participation or impact.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>These mission critical activities include, but are not limited to, the Defense Readiness Reporting System, Joint Basing, Public Safety related initiatives (e.g., Crisis Action Teams, ROCs, and EOCs.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>CNIC N61 ensures HQ IT priorities and directives are communicated and managed across the enterprise.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>CNIC N61 engages all regional chief information officers to provide quarterly performance reviews on their priorities, as well as coordinates projects across regions, commands, and services to effectively share information and deploy standard technology solutions.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span><span style="LAYOUT-GRID-MODE: line">To ensure that CNIC remains in the forefront of technology without interruption of services, IT services and solutions are required by CNIC N61 to support the needs of CNIC, regional CIOs, and external Program Owners (e.g., Naval Facilities Engineering Command (NAVFAC), U.S. Marine Corps (USMC), U. S Air Force (USAF), U. S. Army Corp of Engineers (USACE), and Missile Defense Agency (MDA)).</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Anticipated Time Frame:</p>
<p>October 2016 (base year plus 2 optional option years)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Place of Performance.</p>
<p>CNIC's C3P Ashore services are distributed across approximately 167 locations of which approximately 45 are OCONUS locations to include remote locations such as Diego Garcia, Iwakuni, Okinawa, Yokosuka, Sasebo, Atsugi and other locations in Japan, Korea, Guam (Marianas), Singapore, ISA Air Base (Bahrain), Camp Lemonier Djibouti (Horn of Africa), Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, Poland and NSF Deveselu (Romania). The vendor must support all locations as part of this solicitation. There is a primary Network Operations Center (NOC) at the Washington Navy Yard.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal">REQUIRED CAPABILITIES:</strong></p>
<p>Experience supporting global Department of Defense network installations with the same size and scope of operations as the C3P Ashore Public Safety Network. Detect, identify and provide Tier I triage within two hours, provide Tier II/III issue resolution to location in 24 hours.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Experience and knowledge supporting and integrating Land Mobile Radio Systems from major commercial vendors (e.g., Motorola and Harris) on a global level.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Experience deploying staff to perform technical subject matter expert network services both CONUS and OCONUS with multiple teams deployed concurrently.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Demonstrate successful knowledge in integrated logistics and asset management both CONUS and OCONUS for service-life management of network and server equipment including the Defense Logistics Agency (DLA) Disposition process.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Demonstrate knowledge with inter-service, multi-agency collaboration for the stand-up of new installations in OCONUS locations involving critical infrastructure installation and configuration as it relates to the core enterprise services.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Demonstrate Software Development incorporating geospatial data utilizing a Capability Maturity Model (CMM) Level 3 development process in a classified computing environment specifically Secret Internet Protocol Router Network (SIPRNet).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Demonstrate knowledge and ability with successful outcomes of the Cyber Security Inspection process conducted by FLTCYBERCOM (FCC) Office of Compliance &amp; Assessment (OCA) on behalf or by DISA under the direction and authority of USCYBERCOM as it relates to compliance for DoD networks of similar size and complexity as CNIC's PSNet.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Demonstrate 24/7/365 global NOC support to include Continuity of Operations Planning (COOP) and stand up of alternative NOC at a contractor furnished location.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Demonstrate knowledge and ability in running a detailed configuration management process for a global enterprise network environment to include Architecture Review Board, Configuration Change Board and full configuration management process components.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal">SPECIAL REQUIREMENTS </strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>All staff must hold a secret clearance to perform on contract.</p>
<p>DoD 8570 certified workforce supporting operating environments at a minimum of Mission Assurance Category (MAC) level 2Navy Risk Management Framework Experience</p>
<p>The following certifications must be maintained:</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; mso-list: l2 level1 lfo2"><span style="FONT-FAMILY: Symbol; mso-fareast-font-family: Symbol; mso-bidi-font-family: Symbol"><span>&bull;&middot;<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span></span>Technical:<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>Information Assurance Technician (IAT) Level 3 certification.</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; mso-list: l2 level1 lfo2"><span style="FONT-FAMILY: Symbol; mso-fareast-font-family: Symbol; mso-bidi-font-family: Symbol"><span>&bull;&middot;<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span></span>IA Management: Information Assurance Management (IAM) Level 3 certification.</p>
<p>Must hold a Program Management Professional (PMP) certification for program management office representatives.</p>
<p>Must be ISO 9001 and 20000 certified.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>ISO 27000 certification is also preferred.</p>
<p>Must be at least a <span style="mso-ansi-language: EN">Capability Maturity Model Integration (</span>CMMI) Level 3 certified software development organization.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Managers, Engineers, Technicians, Administrators/Privileged Users</p>
<p>The following certifications must be maintained:</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; mso-list: l0 level1 lfo3"><span style="FONT-FAMILY: Symbol; mso-fareast-font-family: Symbol; mso-bidi-font-family: Symbol"><span>&bull;&middot;<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span></span>Enterprise IAT Level 3 certification</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; mso-list: l0 level1 lfo3"><span style="FONT-FAMILY: Symbol; mso-fareast-font-family: Symbol; mso-bidi-font-family: Symbol"><span>&bull;&middot;<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span></span>Network IAT Level 2</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; mso-list: l0 level1 lfo3"><span style="FONT-FAMILY: Symbol; mso-fareast-font-family: Symbol; mso-bidi-font-family: Symbol"><span>&bull;&middot;<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span></span>Systems IAT Level 1</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal">SOURCES SOUGHT: </strong></p>
<p style="MARGIN-TOP: 12pt; mso-margin-bottom-alt: auto">The anticipated North American Industry Classification System Code (NAICS) for this requirement is 541512, with the corresponding size standard of $27.5 million.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>This Sources Sought Synopsis is requesting responses to the following criteria from small businesses that can provide the required services under the NAICS Code.</p>
<p><span style="FONT-FAMILY: 'Times New Roman', 'serif'; FONT-SIZE: 12pt">To assist CNIC in making a determination regarding the level of participation by small business in any subsequent procurement that may result from this Sources Sought, you are also encouraged to provide information regarding your plans to use joint venturing (JV) or partnering to meet each of the requirements areas contained herein. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp;</span>This includes responses from qualified and capable Small Businesses, Small Disadvantaged Businesses, Service Disabled-Veteran Owned Small Businesses, Women-owned Small Businesses, HUB Zone Small Businesses, and 8(a) companies.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>You should provide information on how you would envision your company's areas of expertise and those of any proposed JV/partner would be combined to meet the specific requirements contained in this announcement.</span></p>
<p><span style="FONT-FAMILY: 'Times New Roman', 'serif'; FONT-SIZE: 12pt">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p style="mso-margin-bottom-alt: auto">In order to make a determination for a small business set-aside, two or more qualified and capable small businesses must submit responses that demonstrate their qualifications.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>Responses must demonstrate the company's ability to perform in accordance with the Limitations on subcontracting clause (FAR 52.219-14). <span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal">SUBMISSION DETAILS:</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; mso-layout-grid-align: none">Responses should include:</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; MARGIN-LEFT: 0.5in; mso-list: l1 level1 lfo1; mso-layout-grid-align: none"><span>&bull;1)<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span>Business name and address;</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; MARGIN-LEFT: 0.5in; mso-list: l1 level1 lfo1; mso-layout-grid-align: none"><span>&bull;2)<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span>Name of company representative and their business title;</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; MARGIN-LEFT: 0.5in; mso-list: l1 level1 lfo1; mso-layout-grid-align: none"><span>&bull;3)<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span>Type of Small Business;</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; MARGIN-LEFT: 0.5in; mso-list: l1 level1 lfo1; mso-layout-grid-align: none"><span>&bull;4)<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span>Cage Code;</p>
<p style="TEXT-INDENT: -0.25in; TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; MARGIN-LEFT: 0.5in; mso-list: l1 level1 lfo1; mso-layout-grid-align: none"><span>&bull;5)<span style="FONT: 7pt 'Times New Roman'">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span>Contract vehicles that would be available to the Government for the procurement of the product and service, to include ENCORE II, General Service Administration (GSA), GSA MOBIS, NIH, NASA SEWP, Federal Supply Schedules (FSS), or any other Government Agency contract vehicle.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>(This information is for market research only and does not preclude your company from responding to this notice.)</p>
<p style="TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; mso-layout-grid-align: none">&nbsp;</p>
<p style="TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; mso-layout-grid-align: none">Vendors who wish to respond to this should send responses via email NLT 4:00 PM Eastern Daylight Time (EDT) October 22, 2015 to <a href="mailto:gil.ward@navy.mil">gil.ward@navy.mil</a>, <a href="mailto:allison.grills@navy.mil">allison.grills@navy.mil</a>, and <a href="mailto:John.P.Schiffhauer.civ@mail.mil">John.P.Schiffhauer.civ@mail.mil</a>.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>Interested businesses should submit a brief capabilities statement package (no more than five (5) pages) demonstrating the ability to perform the services listed in this Technical Description.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>Documentation should be in bullet format.</p>
<p style="TEXT-AUTOSPACE: ; mso-layout-grid-align: none">&nbsp;</p>
<p>Proprietary information and trade secrets, if any, must be clearly marked on all materials.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>All information received that is marked Proprietary will be handled accordingly.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>Please be advised that all submissions become Government property and will not be returned.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>All government and contractor personal reviewing RFI responses will have signed non-disclosure agreements and understand their responsibility for proper use and protection from unauthorized disclosure of proprietary information as described 41 USC 423.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes">&nbsp; </span>The Government shall not be held liable for any damages incurred if proprietary information is not properly identified.</p>
<p style="PAGE-BREAK-AFTER: avoid; MARGIN: 12pt 0in 3pt; mso-outline-level: 1">&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DISA/D4AD/DITCO/MAC0110/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DISA/D4AD/DITCO/MAC0110/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SRCSGT - Scheduling Contract for the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency Next NGA West Campus (N2W)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - The following is a Sources Sought announcement to seek market research information on businesses with capability of providing the services described in the below scope of work. This is not a Request for Quote (RFQ) or Request for Proposal (RFP). THIS IS NOT A SOLICITATION FOR PROPOSALS AND NO CONTRACT SHALL BE AWARDED FROM THIS SOURCES SOUGHT. No reimbursement will be made for any costs associated with providing information in response to this sources sought or any follow up information requests. This notice is a market research tool used for planning purposes only to determine the availability of capable contractors able to do the following:
<p>A new indefinite delivery indefinite quantity (IDIQ/IDC) contract is being contemplated for third party scheduling subject matter expert (SME) with knowledge, skills and abilities to perform independent schedule development, analysis and assessment to assist in the administration of U.S Army Corps of Engineers construction contracts. The primary scheduling SME efforts would be associated with a new $1B design and construction project for the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency West campus located in St. Louis, Missouri. Scheduling SME efforts would occur during both the design and construction phases of the project. Task orders may be issued on other projects as needed by the district. The following is a listing of potential tasks based on current need. These tasks would be further developed and issued to the successful offeror as subsequent task orders. These are preliminary and may be modified based on coordination with the Contracting Officer.</p>
<p>a. Participate in Pre-Construction review efforts by analyzing a construction contractor's construction schedule submittals at various identified milestones during the design phase. Provide a written report on the completed analysis. This could include but is not limited to:<br /><br />i. Verifying compliance with Project Schedule Specification 01 32 01.00 10<br />ii. Overall feasibility analysis. Ensure constructability based on, reasonable and realistic sequence of activities as it relates to construction methods, proposed durations, and activity relationships.</p>
<p>b. Develop an independent government construction schedule based on interpreting provided plans and specifications in accordance with Project Schedule Specification 01 32 01.00 10. The independent government construction schedule shall be created in Primavera P6 software. The submittal shall include a written narrative identifying all assumptions and the ".xer" export file from P6 for Government review.</p>
<p>c. Provide independent third party evaluation of an AE developed schedule and a Construction Contractor developed schedule. Submit a written report documenting the comparative analysis. The analysis should ensure constructability based on, reasonable and realistic sequence of activities as it relates to construction methods, proposed durations, and activity relationships. Brief the on-site USACE staff of your findings.</p>
<p>d. During the construction phase of a project, review and evaluate the contractor's monthly schedule update submission. Analyze the schedule for variance from the previous month submission. Verify the contractor's schedule against actual site conditions. For each monthly update, provide a written narrative describing the analysis and conduct an on-site briefing to senior USACE construction staff. Participate in periodic schedule update meetings and weekly progress meetings as requested by on-site USACE personnel.</p>
<p>e. During the construction phase of a project, complete forensic schedule analysis on an as needed basis. Conduct analysis and provide recommendations on responsibilities for impacts of submitted modifications, RFIs, claims, and other changes which have impacted the schedule. Provide recommendations to the Government on merits of the contractor's assertions that these have adversely impacted contractor performance and that the contractor is due compensable time extension(s). Provide written analysis and onsite presentations as needed.</p>
<p>f. At the beginning of the construction phase of a project, review the construction contractor's Initial Project Schedule submittal. Review schedule for constructible, reasonable and realistic sequence of activities as it relates to construction methods chosen and overall compliance with Project Schedule Specification 01 32 01.00 10. Provide written narrative highlighting items of non-compliance. Conduct additional reviews as applicable until the schedule is approved.</p>
<p>g. During the construction phase of a project, review recovery schedule submittals which would occur should a contractor fall behind the approved construction schedule. The recovery schedule must demonstrate how the rate of progress will be regained. Review the recovery schedule for constructible, reasonable and realistic sequence of activities and overall compliance with Project Schedule Specification 01 32 01.00 10. Provide written narrative highlighting items of non-compliance. Conduct additional reviews as applicable until the recovery schedule is approved.</p>
<p><br />The North American Industrial Classification System (NAICS) code for this procurement is 541330 (Engineering Services), which has a small business size standard of $15,000,000.00 in average annual receipts. The Small Business size standard for this code is $15,000,000.00. To be considered a Small Business under this NAICS code, the respondent's average revenue for the last three fiscal years cannot be more than $15,000,000.00. If the respondent's average revenue for the last three fiscal years is over $15,000,000.00 the respondent is not considered a Small Business.</p>
<p>If the contract is set-aside for Small Business, FAR 52.219-14, Limitation on Subcontracting, will be included in the contract. This clause requires that at least 50 percent of the cost of contract performance incurred for personnel shall be expended for employees of the concern.</p>
<p>ADDITIONAL PROJECT INFORMATION</p>
<p>Prior experience in the following areas is required:</p>
<p>1) Reviewing and verifying schedule submittals comply with UFGS Project Schedule Specification 01 32 01.00 10 and ensure constructability based on, reasonable and realistic sequence of activities as it relates to construction methods, proposed durations, and activity relationships.</p>
<p>2) Developing construction schedules based on interpreting provided plans and specifications in accordance with UFGS Project Schedule Specification 01 32 01.00 10 utilizing P6 software.</p>
<p>3) Reviewing and evaluating the contractor's monthly schedule update submission for accuracy and matches field conditions.</p>
<p>4) Completing forensic schedule analysis and provide recommendations on responsibilities for impacts of submitted modifications, RFIs, claims, and other changes which have impacted the schedule.</p>
<p>5) Reviewing recovery schedule submittals which would occur should a contractor fall behind the approved construction schedule.</p>
<p>How to Respond to this Sources Sought Notice:</p>
<p>If your company has recent experience similar to that mentioned in the above scope of work, please respond to the information below by email to:</p>
<p>hilary.m.winans@usace.army.mil by 2:00 pm Central Standard Time (CST) Friday, November 6, 2015.</p>
<p>1. Description of up to five (5) five similar projects completed by your company within the past seven (7) years, including as much of the following information as possible: <br />(a) dollar amount of the overall construction effort and dollar amount of the contract; <br />(b) brief description of the technical requirements of that scheduling effort; <br />(c) a description of the work that was self-performed; <br />(d) description of the final output that your firm provided to support the project and the benefits that this provided for the designer, constructor, and owner, <br />(e) a description of role on the contract (prime, sub, etc). <br />(f) name, address, point of contact, and phone number of customer organization for which the work was done.<br /><br />If possible at least one example should highlight experience in developing a full construction schedule, one should highlight experience with forensic schedule analysis, and one should highlight experience completing a full schedule review of another's work product. One existing sample of each of the three efforts listed is allowed to be submitted. When submitting an example of a project schedule, it should be a simple P6 Activity/Gantt chart view with the accompanying schedule log file.</p>
<p>2. Firm's business size and, if applicable, small business category: Large Business, Small Business, (Section 8(a), Historically Underutilized Business Zones (Hub-Zone), Women Owned, Service Disabled Veteran Owned (SDVOSB), etc.</p>
<p>3. Firm's Joint Venture information, if applicable - existing and potential. <br /><br />The response must be specific to the qualifications listed above to show that the respondent meets the requirements and possesses the necessary skills and experience. If a response does not show that the respondent meets the qualifications and/or does not possess the necessary skills and experience, the respondent will not be considered by the Government. Again this is not a request for proposal or quotation; there is no solicitation available at this time. A determination by the Government to proceed with the acquisition as a set-aside for 8(a) program, HUBZone, Small Business, etc. or unrestricted is within the discretion of the Government.<br /><br />Contracting Office Address: <br />US Army Engineer District, Kansas City, ATTN: CENWK-CT, 647Federal Building, 60l East 12th Street, Kansas City, MO 64106-2896</p>
<p>Place of Performance: <br />TBD</p>
<p>Point of Contact(s): <br />Jay.b.denker@usace.army.mil Jay B. Denker, 816-389-3934<br />Hilary.m.winans@usace.army.mil Hilary Winans, 816-389-3500</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA41/W912DQ-16-R-4004/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA41/W912DQ-16-R-4004/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - Secure Web Based Project Information System Contract for the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency Next NGA West Campus (N2W)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - The following is a Sources Sought announcement to seek market research information on businesses with capability of providing the services described in the below scope of work. This is not a Request for Quote (RFQ) or Request for Proposal (RFP). THIS IS NOT A SOLICITATION FOR PROPOSALS AND NO CONTRACT SHALL BE AWARDED FROM THIS SOURCES SOUGHT. No reimbursement will be made for any costs associated with providing information in response to this sources sought or any follow up information requests. This notice is a market research tool used for planning purposes only to determine the availability of capable contractors able to do the following:
<p>A Secure Web Based Project Information System (SWBPIS) contract is required to support the planning, design, construction, and operation of a replacement campus for the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency's (NGA) 2nd Street St. Louis facilities. The project has been designated Next NGA West (N2W). One contract may be awarded, with a base for design phase effort and one or more options for construction phase effort. This will be a firm-fixed-price contract. Award of the contract is anticipated in FY16. <br /><br />Firms must be capable of performing project information documentation work to support the planning, design, construction and operation of facilities for the N2W program in the St. Louis Area. This project will include a replacement campus for the 2nd Street facilities known as the Next NGA West (N2W) program. The project is tentatively planned for construction to occur in the FY18 through FY22 timeframe. Efforts under this contract are expected to begin in FY16. The campus complex would consist of the following facilities/improvements:</p>
<p>a. Secure Analytics Facility (SCIF) (approx 800,000 sf) <br />b. Central Utilities Plant (approx 40,000 sf) <br />c. Structured Parking (approx 1,000,000 sf) <br />d. Visitor Control Center (VCC) (approx 7,300 sf) <br />e. Remote Vehicle/Truck Inspection Facility (approx 6,500 sf) <br />f. Associated Site improvements (roads, utilities, landscaping, etc)</p>
<p>The selected firm will provide secure web based information management through the life cycle of the N2W project. Documents/information that may be handled include, but are not limited to, design analyses, plans, specifications, meeting minutes, programming documents, planning documents, conformed documents, bidding documents, schedule documents, construction submittals, modifications, requests for information, reports, closeout documents, photos, LEED submissions, test reports, etc.</p>
<p><br />The North American Industrial Classification System (NAICS) code for this procurement will be 541511 (Custom Computer Programming Services) or 518210 (Data processing, hosting, and other related services). The Small Business size standard for this NAICS code (541511) is $27, 500,000.00. To be considered a Small Business under this NAICS code, the respondent's average annual revenue for the last three fiscal years cannot be more than $27,500,000.00. If the respondent's average annual revenue for the last three fiscal years is over $27,500,000.00 the respondent is not considered a Small Business.</p>
<p>If the contract is set-aside for Small Business, FAR 52.219-14, Limitation on Subcontracting, will be included in the contract. This clause requires that at least 50 percent of the cost of contract performance incurred for personnel shall be expended for employees of the concern.</p>
<p>ADDITIONAL PROJECT INFORMATION</p>
<p>Prior experience in the following areas is required:</p>
<p>(1) Providing a secure web based project information system capable of providing the following:</p>
<p>&bull; Host a secure web-based electronic media site that provides for electronic&nbsp;exchange of information between government users, design firms, construction firms and others as called for.<br />&bull; Handling a large volume of files (multiple volumes of specifications and several thousand plan sheets for multiple buildings and contracts at one time)<br />&bull; Be capable of providing multiple levels of access depending on user authorizations and privileges<br />&bull; Provide collaborative mode so multiple users can access the same file concurrently<br />&bull; Plan reviews, to include capability to comment directly on document being reviewed and providing reports documenting comments made, actions taken, current status, etc. System should be capable of uploading design review comments to the USACE Dr. Checks system. <br />&bull; Webcam hosting and storage services.<br />&bull; Notification to users when new documents are available<br />&bull; Supports use of multiple web browsers for access<br />&bull; System should be capable of responding/loading documents/drawings/plans, rapidly to meet multiple user's needs. Capable of supporting both native file formats (such as Word, AutoCAD, Microstation) as well as Adobe Portable Document Format (PDF). Color shall be supported for documents that are in color.<br />&bull; Capable of providing multiple folders for segregation of information as needed.<br />&bull; Linking details on plans to where they apply<br />&bull; Ability to download documents to individual computers<br />&bull; Ability to tie photo documentation to floor plans or site plans</p>
<p>(2) Experience working on projects requiring Secret or TS/SCI clearance.</p>
<p>How to respond to this sources sought notice.</p>
<p>If your company has recent experience similar to that mentioned in the above scope of work please respond to the information below by email to:</p>
<p>Jay.b.denker@usace.army.mil by 2:00 pm Central Standard Time (CST) Thursday, November 4, 2015.</p>
<p>1. Provide a description of up to five (5) five similar projects completed by your company as a prime contractor within the past seven (7) years, including as much of the following information as possible: (a) dollar amount of the contract; (b) brief description of the technical requirements of that project; (c) a description of the size, complexity, square footage of the similar project; (d) describe the work that was self-performed; (e) description of the system that your firm provided to support the project and the benefits that this system provided for the designer, constructor, and owner, (f) name, address, point of contact and phone number of customer organization for which the work was done. (g) provide a link, if available, to the company website and any available demonstration of the product used by your firm.</p>
<p>2. Firm's business size and, if applicable, small business category: Large Business, Small Business, (Section 8(a), Historically Underutilized Business Zones (Hub-Zone), Women Owned, Service Disabled Veteran Owned (SDVOSB), etc.</p>
<p>3. Firm's Joint Venture information, if applicable - existing and potential. <br /><br />The response must be specific to the qualifications listed above to show that the respondent meets the requirements and possesses the necessary skills and experience. If a response does not show that the respondent meets the qualifications and/or does not possess the necessary skills and experience, the respondent will not be considered by the Government. Again this is not a request for proposal or quotation; there is no solicitation available at this time. A determination by the Government to proceed with the acquisition as a set-aside for 8(a) program, HUBZone, Small Business, etc. or unrestricted is within the discretion of the Government.</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA41/W912DQ-16-R-4005/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA41/W912DQ-16-R-4005/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 08:45:05 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>