<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Geospatial Sources Sought and Presolicitation notices]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[FBO extract of early stage geospatial opportunities]]></description>
        <link>http://example.com</link>
        <image>
            <url>http://example.com/icon.png</url>
            <title>Geospatial Sources Sought and Presolicitation notices</title>
            <link>http://example.com</link>
        </image>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 12:28:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="http://example.com/geospatial.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 12:28:03 GMT</pubDate>
        <copyright><![CDATA[2015 Bill Dollins]]></copyright>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <managingEditor><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></managingEditor>
        <webMaster><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></webMaster>
        <docs>http://example.com/rss/docs.html</docs>
        <ttl>60</ttl>
        <category><![CDATA[GIS]]></category>
        <category><![CDATA[geospatial]]></category>
        <category><![CDATA[FBO]]></category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - R--A-E Studies, Geotechnical Engineering Services IDIQ Contract (Unrestricted)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - Solicitation No. W9128F-14-R-0027 (Unrestricted) <br>  <br> 1. CONTRACT INFORMATION <br>  <br> This contract(s) is being procured in accordance with the Brooks A-E Act as implemented in FAR Subpart 36.6.  Firm(s) will be selected for negotiation based on demonstrated competence and qualifications for the required work.  A-E services will consist primarily of preparation of investigations, studies, analyses, designs, and engineering construction support services for dams, levees, military facility construction, and military airfields.  A-E Services may include, but are not limited to: Geotechnical Engineering and Engineering Geology investigations, studies, designs, and engineering construction support; drilling and subsurface investigations; laboratory testing of soil, rock, aggregate, and concrete/asphalt materials; computer analysis/modeling; geophysics; land-based surveying; computer-aided drafting and design (CADD); and geographical information systems (GIS).  These services will be provided for the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers (USACE) districts of Northwestern Division and their respective customers.  One (1) indefinite delivery indefinite quantity (IDIQ) contract will be negotiated and awarded with a five-year ordering period (three (3) year base with a two (2) year option period) and $4,950,000 in capacity.  There is no specific task order limit except the limit of the contract.  Work will be issued by negotiated firm-fixed-price task orders. North American Industrial Classification System code is 541330, which has a size standard of $15,000,000 in annual average gross receipts over the past three years. This announcement is open to all businesses regardless of size.  If an other-than-small (i.e.  quote mark large quote mark ) business firm is selected for this contract, it will be required to submit a detailed subcontracting plan (reference FAR Subpart 19.7 and FAR Clause 52.219-9) during contract negotiation.  The subcontracting goals that will be considered in the negotiation of this contract are as follows: a minimum of 40.0% of the contractor's intended subcontract amount be placed with Small Businesses (SB), 3.0% be placed with Small Disadvantaged Businesses (SDB), to include Historically Black Colleges and Universities or Minority Institutions (HBCU/MIs), 7.0% be placed with Women-Owned Small Businesses (WOSB), 1.0% be placed with HUBZone Small Businesses, 2.0% be placed with Veteran Owned Small Businesses (VOSB), and 3.0% be placed with Service-Disabled Veteran-Owned Small Businesses (SDVOSB).  The subcontracting plan is not required with this submittal, but will be required with the proposal of the firm selected for negotiations. quote mark  Selected and successful firm will be required to comply with the subcontracting limitations as set forth by the FAR Clause 52.219-14 LIMITATIONS ON SUBCONTRACTING, wherein stated in pertinent part,  quote mark Services (except construction).  At least 50% of the cost of contract performance incurred for personnel must be expended for employees of the concern. quote mark   When two or more indefinite delivery contracts (IDCs) available to the procuring agency contain the same or overlapping scopes of work so that a particular task order might be issued under more than one IDC, the contracting officer will consider the following factors in deciding which contractor will be selected to negotiate an order: performance and quality of deliverables under the current contract, current capacity to accomplish the order in the required time, uniquely specialized experience, and equitable distribution of work among the contractors.  The minimum guarantee amount for this contract is $2,500.00.  To be eligible for contract award, the Contractor must be registered in the System for Award Management (SAM).  Registration is free and can be accessed at: http://www.sam.gov.  <br>      <br> 2. PROJECT INFORMATION <br>  <br> Geotechnical Engineering and Engineering Geology investigations, studies, designs, and engineering construction support work may include literature search/existing data compilation; field reconnaissance; determining design and study parameters; site characterization/exploration planning; producing project work plans; design and study data acquisition; obtaining work permits; soil and rock mechanics analyses; ground water characterization including field permeability testing; in situ concrete/asphalt testing; design computations; developing technical input to contract documents; developing project plans and specifications; project cost estimates; technical oversight of construction activities; project progress and completion reporting; and expert services. <br>  <br> Drilling and subsurface investigations work may include geotechnical drilling utilizing auger, fluid rotary, percussion, rotosonic, and direct push techniques; cone penetrometer testing; excavated test pits; subsurface instrumentation placement such as monitoring wells, piezometers, inclinometers, remote sensing instruments, etc.;  in-situ soil and rock testing; disturbed and undisturbed soil sampling; rock/concrete/asphalt coring; and field logging subsurface materials. <br>  <br> Laboratory work will be performed by a USACE certified laboratory and may include typical geotechnical testing of soil, rock, aggregate, concrete, asphalt, etc., materials in accordance USACE guidelines, standards, and regulations or other appropriate industry standards. <br>  <br> Computer analysis/modeling will be performed utilizing commercially available software and work may include analyses for slope stability, ground water, dewatering, seepage, consolidation/settlement, foundation design (pile, pier, footing, excavation, etc.), retaining walls, drains, material strengths, and site optimization. <br>  <br> Geophysics work may include borehole/downhole, surface, and airborne surveys employing nuclear, electrical resistivity, electromagnetic, ground conductivity, seismic, magnetometer, gravity, thermal, and radar techniques. <br>  <br> Land-based surveying work may include determining geospatial reference data (coordinates and elevation) for key project features with both traditional land surveying equipment and techniques as well as Global Positioning Satellite (GPS) techniques. <br>  <br> Computer-aided drafting and design (CADD) work may include developing design drawings, site plans, interpretive subsurface logs and cross-sections, and figures for reports and presentations.  CADD work products will be produced utilizing the most recent version Microstation, AutoCAD, gINT, or other commercially available software as specified in each task order.   <br>  <br> Geographical information systems (GIS) work may include integrating project information on to GIS platforms for comprehensive data interpretation, analysis, manipulation, and archiving. <br>  <br> All specifications shall be developed and edited using the SpecsIntact automated specifications processing system.   <br>  <br> All work will comply with USACE standards, guidelines, regulations or industry standards as appropriate. <br>  <br> Offerors are advised that there could be requirements for performance of work on U.S. Government Federal Properties or Military Installations requiring proper identification and appropriate clearances for personnel to gain access.  <br>  <br>  <br> 3. SELECTION CRITERIA <br>  <br> The selection criteria for this particular project are listed below in descending order of importance.  Criteria a-e are primary.  Criterion f is secondary and will only be used as  quote mark tie-breakers quote mark  among firms that are essentially technically equal.  Page restrictions are outlined per criterion.  A page is defined as a single side of an 8 -inch by 11-inch sheet with print font no smaller than 10. <br> (a) Specialized Experience and Technical Competence (SF 330, Part I, Section F & G):   Section F will provide examples of not more than 10 projects completed within the last 5 years that best demonstrate experience and competency in the areas outlined below.  All projects cited will identify start/completion dates as well as the project size (cost and scope).  Project examples will not exceed 1 page per example.   <br>  <br> Demonstrated experience and competency to complete: <br>  	Geotechnical Engineering and Engineering Geology services <br>  	Drilling and subsurface investigations <br>  	Geotechnical laboratory testing <br>  	Computer analysis/modeling <br>  	Geophysics <br>  	Land-based land surveying <br>  	CADD <br>  	GIS <br>  	Quality Assurance/Quality Control (QA/QC) for engineering support during construction <br>  <br> Section G will list key personnel proposed for this contract and their respective roles in example projects cited in Section F.  Section G will not exceed 2 pages. <br>  <br> (b) Capacity (SF 330, Part I, Section H): Capacity is the ability to effectively complete task orders.   Firms shall demonstrate the capacity to accomplish at least two (2) $250,000 simultaneous individual task orders within a one-year period.   Evaluation will consider resources, team organization, coordination of in house disciplines and consultants, and prior experience of the prime firm and any of their significant consultants on similar projects.  The evaluation will consider the key persons identified in Sections D, E, and G of the SF330, as well as other available staff and information provided in Section H. <br>    <br> A proposed Management Plan shall be presented that includes an organization chart (reference SF330, Part I, Section D) and addresses team organization (reference SF330, Part I, Section C), any anticipated sub-contractors or entities to supplement the in-house team, quality control procedures, cost control, coordination of in-house disciplines and consultants required to meet work capacity, and interaction with USACE. The SF 330 shall clearly indicate the primary office where the work will be performed and the staffing at that office.  Additionally, key equipment assets (e.g. drill rig(s), laboratory testing facilities/equipment, geophysical instruments, etc.) will be acknowledged and respective locations identified. <br>  <br> If necessary, the organization chart may be presented on a single side of an 11-inch by 17 inch sheet neatly fold to an 8 -inch by 11-inch format. <br>  <br> (c) Knowledge of Locality Knowledge of locality will mean knowledge of regional or local geology, hydrology, soils, topography, climatic conditions, local methods that are unusual or unique, etc.  The firm's office location(s) is not necessarily indicative of knowledge of locality.  The location of Engineering Services will include USACE districts of Northwestern Division and their respective customers.   <br>  <br> (d) Professional Qualifications (SF 330, Part I, Section E):  Evaluation of education, training, registration, certifications, overall and relevant experience, and longevity with the firm of key management and technical personnel.  This criterion is primarily concerned with the qualifications of key personnel, not the number of personnel. Certifications and/or licensing are required for the following: Professional Engineer (Geotechnical/Civil), Professional Geologist, Driller, Professional Land Surveyor/Registered Land Surveyor, and Project Management Professional (PMP).  Other key personnel that will be identified include:  laboratory manager, laboratory technician, GIS professional, geophysicist, CADD professional, and technical editor.  If after submission of the proposal or after award of a contract, the proposed individuals are unable to fulfill the obligation of the solicitation, any proposed replacements will have similar or greater education and experience credentials.  Those credentials shall be provided in writing to the Contracting Officer for review and approval.  Professional qualification information will not exceed 1 page per key personnel position and will not exceed 20 pages cumulatively. <br>  <br> (e) Past Performance: Past Performance on DoD and other contracts with respect to cost control, quality of work, and compliance with performance schedules, as determined from ACASS and other sources. (May be evaluated from ACASS information obtained by the Omaha District Office)  <br>  <br> Past Performance Questionnaires (PPQ) may be used to provide or supplement a firm's past performance with other than U.S. Governmental clients.  Firms which choose to use the PPQ may obtain a PPQ standard form by submitting a request to the below referenced POC to the Contract Specialist. <br>    <br> Secondary Selection Criteria:  Secondary criteria will only be used by a selection board as a  quote mark tie-breaker quote mark , if necessary, in ranking the most highly qualified firms.   <br>  <br> (f) Equitable Distribution of Department of Defense (DoD) Contracts (SF 330, Part I, Section H): Volume of DoD A-E contract awards in the last 12 months, with the objective of effecting an equitable distribution of DoD A-E contracts among qualified firms, including SB and SDB.  DoD contract information shall not exceed 2 pages. <br>  <br>  <br> Evaluation Ratings <br>  <br> The following ratings will be used to evaluate the submitted information: <br>  <br> Exceptional. All or almost all of the significant disciplines and attributes are <br> rated  quote mark exceptional. quote mark   No discipline or attribute should be  quote mark marginal quote mark  or  quote mark unsatisfactory quote mark  in an  quote mark exceptional quote mark  performance evaluation. <br>  <br> Very Good.  A majority of the significant disciplines and attributes are rated  quote mark exceptional quote mark  or  quote mark very good. quote mark   No significant discipline or attribute should be  quote mark marginal quote mark  or  quote mark unsatisfactory quote mark  in a  quote mark very good quote mark  performance evaluation. <br>  <br> Satisfactory.  No significant discipline or attribute should be  quote mark unsatisfactory. quote mark  Quality of final work is acceptable in an overall sense; however, it may have been necessary to get the firm to correct some unacceptable work. <br>  <br> Marginal.  One or two significant disciplines or attributes are rated  quote mark unsatisfactory, quote mark  or all or almost all disciplines or attributes are rated  quote mark marginal. quote mark   An unusual amount of extra effort and follow-up on the part of the Government was required in order to get an acceptable product. <br>  <br> Unsatisfactory.  Several significant disciplines and attributes are rated <br>  quote mark unsatisfactory. quote mark   This rating is appropriate for a firm that does not produce acceptable work despite extensive effort by <br>  <br>  <br> 4. SUBMISSION REQUIREMENTS: <br> Interested firms having the capabilities to perform this work must submit five (5) copies of SF 330 Part I, and five (5) copies of SF 330 Part II for the prime firm and all consultants/subcontractors, to US Army Corps of Engineers, Omaha District, ATTN: Tyler Hegge (CENWO-CT-M), 1616 Capitol Ave., Omaha, NE, 68102, not later than 2:00pm Central time on the 6th of October, 2014.  SUBMITTAL PACKAGES MUST ALSO INCLUDE A CD CONTAINING A COMPLETE COPY OF THE SUBMITTAL (AN SF 330 PART 1 + SF 330 PART II FOR THE PRIME FIRM AND ALL CONSULTANTS/SUBCONTRACTORS), AS A SINGLE PDF FILE. Regulation requires that the Selection Board not consider any submittals received after the specified time and date.  Late proposal rules in FAR 15.208 will be followed for submittals received after 2:00pm Central time on the closing date specified in this announcement.  The SF 330, 03/2013 edition, must be used, and may be obtained from the following web site: http://www.gsa.gov/portal/forms/download/116486.  Include DUNS number and CAGE code in SF330 Part I, Section B, Block 5.  Additionally, the DUNS number and CAGE code should be identified in SF 330 Part I, Section C, Block 9, for EACH TEAM MEMBER.  The submittal shall have a page limit of 100 pages.  A page is one side of a sheet.  Blank sheets/Tabs separating the sections within the SF 330 will not count against the maximum page count. All fonts shall be at least 10 pitch or larger.  Pages shall be 8-1/2 inches by 11 inches.  Organizational charts may be presented on a sheet up to 11 inches by 17 inches. If an 11 inch by 17 inch sheet is used it shall be neatly folded to 8-1/2 inches by 11 inches, bound in the SF 330 at the proper location, and counted as one page.  A Part II is required for each branch office of the prime firm and any consultants/subcontractors that will have a key role in the proposed contract (i.e. a Part II is required for all entities identified in SF 330 Part I, Section C of the submittal).  Cover letters, company literature and extraneous materials are not desired and will not be considered.  Sections E and G of SF 330 Part I must include only individuals proposed to perform the anticipated work, including all consultants/subcontractors.  In SF 330 Part I, Section G, Block 26, along with the name, include the firm with which the person is associated.  A maximum of ten (10) projects including the prime and consultants/subcontractors will be reviewed for SF 330 Part I, Section F.  Use no more than one page per project.  When listing projects in SF 330 Part 1, Section F, an Indefinite Delivery Contract (IDC) with multiple Task Orders as examples is not considered a project. A task order executed under an IDC contract is a project.   For all types of contracts, do not include for consideration options that have not been exercised.  Joint ventures shall submit the following additional documentation of the evidence of a joint venture entity: 1) Firms shall provide a copy of a legally binding joint venture agreement, and 2) Identification of the party who can legally bind the joint venture.  FACSIMILE AND EMAIL SUBMISSIONS WILL NOT BE ACCEPTED.  Solicitation packages are not provided and no additional project information will be given to firms during the announcement period.  This is not a request for proposal.]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA45/W9128F-14-R-0027/listing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/spg/USA/COE/DACA45/W9128F-14-R-0027/listing.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 12:28:03 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PRESOL - R--Geospatial Information System Support Services]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Department of the Army - Mission & Installation Contracting Command Center (MICC) - Fort Bragg, North Carolina will issue solicitation W91247-15-T-0045 for a requirement to provide services for Geospatial Information System Support Services at Fort Bragg, North Carolina. The Contractor shall support the oversight on the creation, maintenance, and management of Installation geospatial data as defined in this Performance Work Statement (PWS). The Contractor shall perform to the standards in this contract. The requirement will be set-aside for HubZone, under NAICS Code 561110, with a size standard of $7.5M. A Firm-Fixed Price (FFP) contract is anticipated under solicitation number W91247-15-T-0045 and will be available for downloading at the Army Single Face to Industry website https://acquisition.army.mil/asfi.   <br>  <br> Potential Responders are responsible for monitoring this site for release of the solicitation package and any amendments.   <br>  <br> All offerors must be registered with the System for Award Management (SAM) per FAR Clause 52.212-4(t) - Contract Terms and Conditions - Commercial Items (May 2015). Offerors must also complete Offeror Representations and Certifications on-line at www.sam.gov prior to submitting an offer.  No paper copies of the solicitation will be mailed and telephone requests will not be honored.  The Government anticipates posting of the Request for Quote (RFQ) on or about 09 September 2015. <br>   <br> The point of contact is Contract Specialist, Nicole Jones at email: nicole.m.jones2.civ@mail.mil. Phone Number 910-643-7221. <br>  <br> The alternate point of contact is the Contracting Officer, Heather Clifton at email: heather.d.clifton.civ@mail.mil. Phone Number 910-908-1964. <br>  <br> Contracting Office Address: <br> Mission & Installation Contracting Command (MICC) Center - Fort Bragg, North Carolina, ATTN: CCMI-CBR-BR, Building 2-1105 C-Stack, Macomb Street, Fort Bragg, North Carolina 28310-5000. <br>  <br>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.fbo.gov/notices/bc79a868a193ce35a88ea10f42323aef</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fbo.gov/notices/bc79a868a193ce35a88ea10f42323aef</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 12:28:03 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>