<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Arc2Earth | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/arc2earth/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-26T15:36:36-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Biggest News You May Have Missed...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/19/the-biggest-news-you-may-have-missed/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/19/the-biggest-news-you-may-have-missed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you missed it, this tweet floated across the Twitters last week:</p>

<p>{% tweet http://twitter.com/Arc2Earth/status/269194049230102528 %}</p>

<p>Yes, the team at <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> is apparently working on a new feature in <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/services/sync/">Arc2Earth Sync,</a> called TileMill Connect, that will link <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcMap</a> MXDs with <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/">TileMill</a>. This will allow users to migrate their ArcMap cartography into TileMill to take advantage of the rich tools there as well as the potential for version control and cut/paste sharing of techniques and best practices enabled by <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/">CartoCSS</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/bFlood">Brian Flood</a> followed that up today with a short video showing it in action.</p>

<p>{% tweet http://twitter.com/Arc2Earth/status/270631991110692865 %}</p>

<p>No word on a timetable for this feature, but I can't wait to kick the tires. I am especially intrigued by the pseudo <a href="http://www.postgis.org">PostGIS</a> proxy service that enables connections to ArcGIS data sources.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Geospatial Workflows]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've had a couple of people ask me recently about the geospatial tools I use. Year-over-year, that answer changes but here's how I answer that right now:</p>

<p>As a Federal contractor, I spend a lot of time working with the <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> stack during my work day. A few years ago, I added a few open-source geospatial tools into my tool set and, since then, have also done a respectable amount to consulting work them as well. The balance between the two varies over time, depending on the requirements of individual customers and projects. Lately, commercial customers have seemed much more interested in open-source tools while my government customers are sticking with Esri. Since those observations are based on the the extremely heavy filter of my own recent experience, I'd be hesitant to draw any larger conclusions from them.</p>

<p><img alt="" height="264" src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/duct-tape.jpg" title="Duct Tape" width="300" /></p>

<p>I've always believed that proficiency with a wide range of tools makes me a better consultant and integrator, so I am always exploring and trying new things. With those commercial customers, and in my own personal side projects, my recent workflows have gelled around a core set of tools, both commercial and open-source: <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> - I am very comfortable with SQL and tend to use <a href="http://www.postgresql.org" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> and PostGIS for a lot of my vector data processing. Lately, this has mainly involved joining up geometries with attributes and doing aggregations and similar things. For example, the vector data in this <a href="http://geobabbler.github.com/mdq62012.html" target="_blank">map of the county-level Maryland Question 6 results</a> was processed in PostGIS. Very simply, I have a baseline table of the counties of Maryland which I will use to create new data sets. In this case, I imported a CSV of the election results, created a view that joined up the data and then selected the view into a new table. This is workflow is much easier with PostGIS 2.x thanks to the <a href="http://blog.opengeo.org/2012/03/06/postgis-2-0-new-features-typmod/" target="_blank">use of typmod</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a> - In the case of the map mentioned above, the data set is ultimately going to be static so it makes sense to serve it as static content, rather than bringing a heavyweight geospatial server such as <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgisserver/" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> or <a href="http://geoserver.org/display/GEOS/Welcome" target="_blank">GeoServer</a> into the mix. In these cases, I lean toward <a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>. QGIS makes it very easy to export any vector layer out to GeoJSON so it's become my go-to tool for that. QGIS also has great analytical tools and I consider it a complete functional match for ArcMap but, having said that, I'm actually very comfortable with the spatial SQL functions in PostGIS so I end up doing most of my analytical work there.</p>

<p><a href="http://leafletjs.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a>/<a href="http://www.openlayers.org/" target="_blank">OpenLayers</a> - Most of the web maps I'm doing are single-use and pretty straightforward. When that's the case, I prefer to use Leaflet as it's a pretty lightweight library. That said, I keep OpenLayers in the mix if the GIS-like requirements get a little more complex. OpenLayers does more "out of the box" than Leaflet but Leaflet is trimmer so it really depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/" target="_blank">Arc2Earth</a>/<a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill </a>- Arc2Earth is a commercial extension to ArcGIS and I lean on it to make tiles, although it does a lot more than that. I also use TileMill for this purpose but it really depends on where my cartography resides. There's a lot of good cartography locked up in MXDs and Arc2Earth is just a great way to capitalize on that. It's also nice that Arc2Earth works in ArcMap, eliminating the need for a license of Server.  If I'm building my cartography from scratch, which is not really my strong suit, I'll lean toward TileMill because it more easily connects directly to PostGIS, which is where my data tends to reside if I have my druthers. Again, it depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.python.org/" target="_blank">Python</a>/Javascript - I'm doing a lot more work in Python these days. It's become the <em>lingua franca</em> of GIS development in my book. Additionally, the capabilities of Javascript for web maps is evolving at a stunning pace. I can't see being productive in the long term in the geospatial field without proficiency in these two languages.</p>

<p>So these are the tools that I'm using most often these days as part of my personal workflows. The stable of tools that I use evolves over time, as should be evident if you peruse this blog. In general, I'm finding it very easy to be productive with these tools right now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cutting Tiles for ArcGIS Server Using TileMill]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/03/cutting-tiles-for-arcgis-server-using-tilemill/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/03/cutting-tiles-for-arcgis-server-using-tilemill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There's been a lot of talk about <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill</a> and <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/" target="_blank">CartoCSS</a> lately, with good cause. TileMill makes it very easy generate beautiful map tiles using the <a href="http://mapnik.org/" target="_blank">Mapnik</a> engine and CartoCSS provides a familiar method to author the cartographic representation of spatial data. <a href="http://mapbrief.com/2012/09/27/gis-cartography-the-latest-best-opportunity-to-bridge-the-chasm/" target="_blank">As Brian Timoney points out</a>, CartoCSS has the added bonus of making best practices shareable via copy-and-paste.</p>




<p>Naturally, the best way to take advantage of TileMill is to export your tiles to <a href="https://github.com/mapbox/mbtiles-spec" target="_blank">MBTiles</a> and use <a href="http://mapbox.com/" target="_blank">MapBox</a> hosting. If that's not an option, you can pretty easily self-host with <a href="https://github.com/mapbox/tilestream" target="_blank">TileStream</a>. That said, there are some organizations that, due to larger GIS workflows, IT policies, and a host of other legitimate reasons, need or choose to use <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">ArcGIS Server</a> to do map hosting. For those organizations, TileMill is still an option to create attractive basemaps, within certain constraints.</p>


<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2911" height="295" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/tilemill_screen.png" title="tilemill_screen" width="640" /></p>

<p>So I set out to see if I could bridge the gap between the two. Two blog posts pointed the way. A while back, <a href="http://www.weogeo.com/blog/Create_WeoGeo_Tilepack_from_MBTiles_SQLite_database_with_mbutil.html" target="_blank">Dan Dye blogged about how he had forked mb-util</a> and added support for exporting WeoGeo tilepacks from MBTiles. Also, a co-worker of mine, Eric Mahaffey, had blogged some time ago about <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2011/08/03/using-arc2earth-tile-caching-across-air-gapped-networks" target="_blank">how to use Arc2Earth to manage tile caches across air-gapped networks</a>. Using these posts for guidance, I was pretty sure I had all the pieces I needed. <!--more--></p>

<p>First, I decided to fork Dan's code (I love GitHub) and add support for exporting ArcGIS tiles. Essentially, I followed Dan's pattern and added a choice for an ArcGIS schema as a command-line option. My forked version <a href="https://github.com/geobabbler/mbutil" target="_blank">can be found on GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>I then fired up TileMill (0.10.0 for Windows) and created some tiles at zoom levels 4 through 8 using the "Control Room" sample that comes with TileMill. I chose this for two reasons: First, I am not very good at cartography and this sample looks attractive and distinct from the generic ArcGIS sample I used. Second, it's very well-known to TileMill users so it worked well for this demo. I won't go into how I created the tiles as this post is not intended to be a TileMill tutorial.</p>

<p>Once I had exported the tiles to an MBTiles file, I ran the updated mb-util Python utility to export the tiles in an ArcGIS structure. The command-line usage is shown below. One note: I did not generate the "level" folders in accordance with ArcGIS convention. If you are familiar with ArcGIS, you know that the level numbers are relative so that, if your service only contains levels 3, 4 , and 5, the will be levels L00, L01, L02 respectively. Instead, the utility names them according to their original TMS levels (L03, L04, L05 in this case). So, you may need to rename your level folders when you rehost to ArcGIS Server but this should entail a maximum of 19 manual edits, which seemed like a reasonable compromise.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/mbutil_cmd.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2897" height="311" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/mbutil_cmd.png" title="mb-util usage" width="640" /></a></p>

<p>So mb-util created the "_alllayers" folder and its child file system for us. Because I'm not creating a conf.xml yet, I can create it by hand or use ArcGIS to create some dummy tiles with a configuration. Once that's done, we are simply engaged in a file copy  operation (picking up at step 4 of Eric's post). For this demo, I created an actual map using one of the ArcGIS samples so that it would be apparent that the operation worked. In practice, I wouldn't go to that much trouble up front. The image below shows the map service using the original tiles.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill1.png"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-2901" height="370" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill1.png" title="ArcGIS map service before TileMill tiles" width="640" /></a> <div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">ArcGIS map service as created from the original MXD.</div></div>


<p>After I copied the tiles from TileMill into the correct location, I was able to refresh the window and see the boundary between the original tiles and the those from TileMill. Again, this was just for demo purposes. In practice, the whole cache would be from TileMill. The image below shows the updated cache, displayed using the ArcGIS Javascript API.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill2.png"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-2902" height="370" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/arc_tilemill2.png" title="ArcGIS map service after TileMill tiles" width="640" /></a> <div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">ArcGIS map service showing tiles from TileMill.</div></div>


<p>I apologize for screenshots but my EDN license precludes making my ArcGIS Server public for a live demo.</p>

<p>So, it's perfectly possible to create nice basemaps using TileMill for use in ArcGIS server, provided you adhere to two constraints: 1) You use Web Mercator for your spatial reference and 2) You make sure your ArcGIS cache is the "exploded" variety.</p>

<p>Why would you do this? It is certainly possible to build great cartographic representations in ArcGIS but those representations are locked away in ArcGIS map documents, styles, layer packages and such; all of which are some proprietary binary format such as persisted COM objects. While this may not be the worst thing in the world, CartoCSS, being a text format, more easily lends itself to configuration control. Organizations that want to maintain configuration control over map templates and such can take advantage of standard tools such as git or SVN to do so. I have found that organizations with strict IT policies are also exactly the same kinds of organizations that to maintain control over content and styling so this is actually a surprisingly important factor.</p>

<p>I'll probably play with this more as time and customer demand allow, but it's good to know this option is available for providing flexibility with ArcGIS Server.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc2Earth Focusing On Google Earth Builder]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/08/03/arc2earth-focusing-on-google-earth-builder/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/08/03/arc2earth-focusing-on-google-earth-builder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> (disclaimer: <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">my company</a> is an Arc2Earth reseller) has focused a lot on extending their integration with the Google cloud infrastructure. This started with Cloud Services, which provided the ability to push data into Google <a href="http://code.google.com/appengine/">AppEngine</a> and serve it through emulation of the <a href="http://help.arcgis.com/en/arcgisserver/10.0/apis/rest/index.html">Esri REST API</a> (among other options). This was expanded to include live editing of data hosted on AppEngine. More recently, Arc2Earth added support for <a href="http://www.google.com/fusiontables/public/tour/index.html">Google Fusion Tables</a>.</p>

<p><img alt="arc2earth logo" src="http://www.arc2earth.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/10/logo_Arc2Earth_h.png" /></p>

<p>Late last year, they announced their <a href="http://beta.arc2cloud.com/">Arc2Cloud</a> initiative to expose Google's spatial data services to ArcGIS users. This has seemed to fall of the radar a bit lately but, as we know, there have been <a href="http://www.google.com/enterprise/earthmaps/builder.html">changes brewing on the on the Google end of things</a> so some delays from Arc2Earth are understandable.<!--more--></p>

<p>Yesterday's newsletter from Arc2Earth confirmed suspicions with the following:</p>

<blockquote>
Many of you have also been asking about Arc2Cloud and when it will be available. All we can say is it has changed into something more powerful and we are really excited about where it will lead us. If you want to use Google Fusion Tables or Google Earth Builder from within ArcGIS, this is the product for you. Arc2Cloud is still used to provide online compatibility with ArcGIS but the real benefit is the automatic synchronization of your data. 

It runs in the task tray and keeps everything up to date (data, live edits, tiles, published maps etc) without you having to do anything. In fact, I think it's the culmination of all the different parts of Arc2Earth into a single, automated package. Arc2Earth Sync will be coming this fall as part of Arc2Earth Desktop.
</blockquote>


<p>So there you have it, Arc2Earth will be your interface between ArcGIS Desktop and Google Earth Builder. The state of offerings in the "cloud" for geospatial users will be changing a lot over the next year or so. Arc2Earth looks like it will be a nice way to keep your options open.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Day At the 2011 FedUC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/21/my-day-at-the-2011-feduc/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/01/21/my-day-at-the-2011-feduc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a variety of reasons, I only spent one day at the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/feduc/index.html">FedUC</a> this year. I chose Thursday because that was the day of the DevGeo session, as well as the National Security Session and a SIG in which I was interested. As a result, I did not see the plenary or any of the big-screen demos. With a few meetings crammed in, my day was a whirlwind. What follows is my view of the FedUC but it is by no means comprehensive. To get a more complete picture, I suggest checking out <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9273-Update-3-Wed-Morning-Plenary-FedUC.html">Adena's</a> <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9275-Update-Wed-Afternoon-Plenary-FedUC.html">updates</a> <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9282-Hottest-Thing-on-FedUC-Floor-Zebra-Imagings-Holograms.html">over</a> at <a href="http://apb.directionsmag.com/archives/9278-FedUC-Session-on-Geospatial-Platform-and-Geodata.gov.html">Directions</a>.</p>

<p><img alt="#FedUC" src="http://www.esri.com/news/graphics/feduc.jpg" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I started out in the National Security Session where I saw demos of some mobile apps done for warfighter use and some web-based common operational picture apps targeted at the homeland security community. Perhaps it was the use case that was discussed, combined with my background doing similar work but the Android app, as it was shown, rang a little hollow for me. I thought homeland security demos were on more solid ground. The use cases were familiar, being similar to those shown in previous years, but the tools are now more advanced and the applications more effective. I have worked with most of the tools discussed (ArcGIS Server, the web APIs, geoprocessing tools, etc.) in similar contexts so I thought the technical content was on target. I am a little concerned that multiple agencies seem to be building similar systems under the guise of addressing their own unique requirements. The proliferation of operating pictures and services and such is quickly creating a hydra that may bog down under the weight of its own redundancy. This is not strictly a technology or GIS problem but all of the nice mapping apps put a very visible face on the issue of lack of coordination.</p>

<p>My next stop was the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/feduc/agenda/dev-geo.html">DevGeo</a> session. Because of overlap with the National Security session, I missed the first part on the iOS API but arrived in time for discussion of the Microsoft APIs. The session was technically an all-day thing but I like the way <a href="http://twitter.com/jimbarry">Jim Barry</a> and team broke it up by technology (with specific time slots for each). This made it easy to drop in for the APIs which interested you but also cut out for other sessions during times when other APIs were being discussed.</p>

<p>Before I get too far into the meat of the DevGeo, I want to point out that this is a case where <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> listened to feedback regarding the FedUC. Back in the fall, I suggested to <a href="http://twitter.com/jsteffenson">John Steffenson</a> that some flavor of the DevGeo session they did in Silicon Valley would be a great thing to add to the FedUC. Much to my surprise, John took the idea forward and it happened. I think the addition of DevGeo, which is much more technically focused than the FedUC content tends to normally be, was a good way to round out the conference.</p>

<p>Jim Barry also told me that they are planning five more dev meetups in the DC area in 2011. I'm not sure about other regions, but developers in this area tend to spend a lot of time in cubicles in windowless rooms behind cipher locks so I think these meetups are a good way to foster more collaboration. I know I won't make all five but I'll hit what I can.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img alt="" height="274" src="http://youcube.us/wp-content/uploads/2008/08/officespace.jpg" title="This guy could stand to get out more." width="412" /><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">This guy could stand to get out more.<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>As for the session itself, I saw the various Microsoft APIs and then also the Android API. I work a lot with the Silverlight API so I'm familiar with it but I did see the Sharepoint tools. It's no secret that I'm not a Sharepoint fan but Esri has done a lot of work to provide web parts that make it pretty easy to insert maps and GIS tools without a lot of code. These parts seem to be targeted at Sharepoint administrators and they make it very easy to map data contained in Sharepoint lists and such. I think Esri succeeded in creating tools that integrate well with workflows with which a Sharepoint administrator is comfortable.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing is the upcoming Silverlight App Builder. This is a wizard-like tool that allows you to build a baseline application framework by choosing a basemap, components such as the navigator, various toolbars and tools, behaviors, actions and the like. What it does is roll up a lot of the tools that the Silverlight API team has been putting out for a while now so you can pick what you want to start with for your application.</p>

<p>I have not actually touched the app builder yet but it seems to create a baseline solution which will build a functioning app with the components you chose. From there, you can deploy the app as-is or begin extending it with your own code. To be perfectly honest, it's probably not something I would use (out of personal preference, not a commentary on the app builder) but I can see its value. I have worked in settings where developers start a Silverlight API app by taking the Silverlight Showcase and stripping out what they don't need. That's a good way to create a mess and I think the app builder provides the opportunity for building a cleaner baseline by adding in only what you do need. It's supposed to be in beta by the the time of the Dev Summit.</p>

<p>The Windows Phone API looked as effective as any other API. Esri is getting pretty good at turning out APIs for various platforms now so it's no surprise that they are on top of Windows Phone. Really, I have nothing to say about the API itself as I was fascinated by the room as the topic transitioned to Windows Phone. The room was filled to capacity (between 150 and 200 people) and only one person had a Windows Phone. As the discussion of the API progressed, people started to leave. I found the lack of interest in the platform almost palpable.</p>

<p>From there, I went to lunch and ditched my backpack. I never once opened my laptop but had my iPad all day. Tablets rule. The days of the laptop are numbered.</p>

<p>I took a swing through the exhibit hall to specifically catch up with the Brian and Jack Flood of <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> and also Brian and Ryan at <a href="http://voyagergis.com/">VoyagerGIS</a>. Arc2Earth is really expanding its cloud support. Upcoming changes are going to greatly simplify pushing data to Google AppEngine. The current version of Arc2Earth Cloud Services is a little cumbersome in that regard and they have been working on streamlining the process. Additionally, they are adding support for the full range of Google geospatial services, including Fusion Tables. This will bring these services right into ArcMap where they can augment existing workflows and data sources. (Disclaimer: <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">My company</a> is an Arc2Earth reseller.)</p>

<p><img alt="Arc2Cloud" src="http://www.arc2earth.com/images/slide1.png" /></p>

<p>I hadn't really seen VoyagerGIS since GIS in the Rockies but they continue to expand their product. At first glance, it looks like a search tool (which it is) but I've always been more impressed by the insights it can give you into your own data use. One of the earliest features that impressed me was the ability to easily identify duplicate data sets, not only by content but by schema (structure). These two things alone can go a long way to helping reduce data redundancy. Additionally the tool indexes ArcMap documents. With this information, you can begin to get insight into what data sets are actually being used in your organization. Basically, the act of indexing your data for search provides the potential for a lot more insight. VoyagerGIS seems to have really hooked into this concept. But don't take my word for it, <a href="http://voyagergis.com/account/signin">download it and try it</a>.</p>

<p>After that, I sat in on a SIG related to infrastructure protection. It gave me a lot of flashbacks and I could probably write an entire (very boring) post on just that. Let's just say there needs to be a lot more thought put into understanding infrastructure interdependence and that federal efforts to engage states on this issue still have a long way to go.</p>

<p>I then swung back through DevGeo for the Android API before my brain was full and my feet hurt. In general, DevGeo was pretty high-level. I would call it a topical overview of the various developer tools provided by Esri but seeing some live demos (Of code...yes, I am a geek because I'd rather see live coding than a PowerPoint any day.) and being able ask some questions is much more valuable than browsing the resource center (at least for me).</p>

<p>I did not go to the Esri shindig at the Natural History Museum as I instead went to the #geoglobaldomination at RFD. Quite a few people from the DC geo scene were there (such as a large crew from <a href="http://www.fortiusone.com">FortiusOne</a>). One of the great things about Esri's conferences is that they act as something of a center of gravity for geo types of all stripes. So there was a great mingling of ideas and catching up with some people that I hadn't seen in a long time. Then, it was time to head for home.</p>

<p>So that closes the books for me on this year's FedUC. Due to scheduling, this will be the only one of the big Esri conferences I'll hit this year so I'll be looking for another backchannel from the <a href="http://www.dtsagile.com/">DTS</a> guys to keep up with the Dev Summit and the International User Conference. :-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
