<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: no fixed address | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/no-fixed-address/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-19T14:13:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How long until the ads stop?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/How-long-until-the-ads-stop/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/How-long-until-the-ads-stop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In celebration of this day when the non-stop political ads, robo-calls, junk mail, and social media posts <em>should</em> finally come to an end. I threw together a little map to show the latest time at which polls close in each state. This should represent, state-by-state, the time (EST) at which you can safely go back to answering your phones. Click the image below to go there (the data takes a couple of seconds to load).</p>

<p><a href="http://demo.zekiah.com/polls"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2947" height="331" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/pollmap.png" title="pollmap" width="640" /></a></p>

<p>Democracy is a wonderful thing, but it will be nice to have this campaign season behind us.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/K1vaEweJUUk?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Still Jonesing for zigGIS? Try this OGR Plug-In for ArcGIS.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/Still-Jonesing-for-zigGIS-Try-this-OGR-Plug-In-for-ArcGIS./"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/Still-Jonesing-for-zigGIS-Try-this-OGR-Plug-In-for-ArcGIS.</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I've actually noticed a surprising uptick in traffic related to <a href="https://code.google.com/p/ziggis/" target="_blank">zigGIS</a> lately? We also had someone asking about <a href="http://www.st-links.com/Pages/default.aspx" target="_blank">ST-Links</a> on the zigGIS mailing list last week. Clearly, there's still a level of interest out there for the problem that zigGIS was designed for.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank"><img alt="ArcGIS and SpatiaLite" height="65%" src="https://a248.e.akamai.net/camo.github.com/c1c86347c63522cb0f5f449b7b9df4209923c3ed/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f53767a6a702e706e67" width="65%" /></a></p>

<div style="font-size: 70%;"><strong>ArcGIS reading SpatiaLite natively, thanks to OGR and Ragi Burhum</strong></div>


<br />


<p>Along those lines, <a href="http://twitter.com/rburhum" target="_blank">Ragi Burhum</a> posted an <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank">OGR Workspace plug-in for ArcGIS</a> up on GitHub. Using OGR is really the magic ticket and the project is available under a BSD license (which Ragi explains very well). The only word to the wise is that pre-built binaries and installers aren't available yet so you Windows/<a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> users will need to get your hands dirty.</p>

<p>I haven't used it yet but I plan to within the next week or so. Stay tuned for a follow up post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Today Is World Diabetes Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/11/14/Today-Is-World-Diabetes-Day/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/11/14/Today-Is-World-Diabetes-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.idf.org/worlddiabetesday/"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2225" height="383" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/wdd.png" title="World Diabetes Day" width="590" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/">Learn More...</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Have Fun In San Diego]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/07/01/Have-Fun-In-San-Diego/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/07/01/Have-Fun-In-San-Diego</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As everyone gears up for the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/user-conference/index.html">exodus to San Diego</a>, I wish everyone a good, enjoyable and fruitful time. There's something to be said for the energy of 12,000+ geonerds in one place. As for me, I'll be <a href="http://www.childrenwithdiabetes.com/activities/orlando2011/">here</a>, hanging with a couple hundred of the bravest, most inspiring young people you could ever meet. After that, it's family time and and little R&amp;R.</p>

<p>And be sure to use the <a href="http://uc.dtsagile.com/">Unofficial Esri UC BackChannel</a> by the guys at <a href="http://dtsagile.com/">DTS Agile</a>. It's a great way to enrich your experience.</p>

<p><img alt="Back soon." class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1879" height="302" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/07/back_soon.jpg" title="Back soon." width="400" /></p>

<p>Have fun and, hopefully, I'll catch up with many of you at <a href="http://2011.foss4g.org/">FOSS4G</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Government, Open Data and Some Lessons from Arkansas]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/29/Open-Government-Open-Data-and-Some-Lessons-from-Arkansas/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/06/29/Open-Government-Open-Data-and-Some-Lessons-from-Arkansas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was reading Brian Timoney's excellent post "<a href="http://mapbrief.com/2011/06/29/open-government-is-a-slammed-door-at-the-blm/">Open Government is a Slammed Door at the BLM</a>," when I encountered this line:</p>

<blockquote>
Top-down, large scale spatial-data-integration-by-directive simply doesn?t have the track record of success to justify the costs...
</blockquote>


<p>This resonates well with observations that I have made during the course of my recent work with the <a href="http://www.gis.arkansas.gov/">Arkansas GIO</a> office. The immediate focus of that work was to help AGIO assess the current state of their <a href="http://www.geostor.arkansas.gov/G6/Home.html">GeoStor</a> platform and gather data about current and emerging capabilities in order to support decision-making about whether to migrate to a hosted (cloud) environment. In the course of doing that work, I learned about the collaborative approach AGIO has taken with the cities and counties of Arkansas, which also informs some of the functional requirements of GeoStor.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>AGIO, among many other functions, offers state-wide, seamless data sets for streets, parcels and addresses. These data sets are assembled from county/city data and allow GeoStor to feature a highly accurate geocoding service, which serves as a resource to support requirements such as <a href="http://www.streamlinedsalestax.org/">streamlined sales tax</a> and others. AGIO feels that commercial geocoding engines do not provide enough accuracy to support these types of requirements so they use detailed data from local jurisdictions to build one for the State.</p>

<p>What I came to understand is that AGIO integrates these data sets in the absence of any top-down requirement of the kind Brian mentions in his post. In general, they take the data as it comes (format, schema, etc.) and use automated/manual processes to transform the data and build/update the data sets. Using this "light touch" approach, AGIO receives data from all 75 counties in the State.</p>

<p>This arrangement works because AGIO views GeoStor as a state-wide asset that must be able to provide value back to the localities as well as to individual citizens. Local jurisdictions can store/host their data on GeoStor. They can also make use of the platform to host map viewers and applications. For instance, the <a href="http://bit.ly/k4f4Ae">Saline County Assessor's Viewer</a> is hosted on the GeoStor platform. So that geocoder can be used by the localities for their own needs without needing to build and maintain their own. Another example is the <a href="http://www.geostor.arkansas.gov/G6/Home.html">GeoStor search tool</a>, which can be used to expose any asset registered with GeoStor (local or linked). This search engine becomes a single point of entry that counties can use to expose their own products and services.</p>

<p>And, again, all of this works without a top-down approach of "integration-by-directive," as Brian puts it. When I asked <a href="http://twitter.com/learondalby">Learon Dalby</a> about this approach, he cited minimal impact on counties and value-add, among others, as two important core values that inform the work AGIO does. This approach requires a lot of leg work. Staff visit the counties and AGIO seems to be remarkably in touch with the needs at that level. Basically, all participants get something of value out of the arrangement and the citizens of Arkansas benefit from the collaboration.</p>

<p>This approach stands in stark contrast to much-less-successful efforts I have witnessed at the Federal level. Through my participation in various working groups over the years I have seen numerous top-down efforts fail. Commonly, this is because they offer a data standard that legislates both content and structure. Oftentimes, these standards to do not mesh well with data that is already in place at lower echelons so additional collection/validation/conversion procedures are required, leading to increased complexity and "discussions" over who will fund/execute that additional complexity. Since complexity usually translates into dollars, the stream of vendors and integrators with solutions to mitigate that complexity soon follows.</p>

<p>Another situation I have commonly observed in such efforts, especially those that attempt to get data from the state level up to the Federal level, is a lack of perceived value by the state-level data providers. Often, they feel they do not see value flow back down. They see high-quality data go in and little, if anything, come back out. This is often obscured by nebulous policy or security requirements but almost universally leads to frustration.</p>

<p>Which brings me back to the Arkansas model. The minimization of top-down requirements and the focus on providing clear value (which doesn't always need to be realized in dollars) to all participants are key reasons why it works. A straw-man that is often tossed out in working groups is "Will it scale?" That's a non-factor here. With 75 counties participating, it is already operating at scale. Here, I am not referring to data. Scaling data is easy. Scaling relationships and participation is harder. Processes that impose little overhead scale better. AGIO succeeds by knowing their mission and pushing down as few requirements and as much value as possible.</p>

<p>If the Federal government (including the defense and homeland security sectors) ever gets serious about "open government," "open data," data sharing and other such efforts, it might be worth a trip to Arkansas.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
