<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: no fixed address | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/no-fixed-address/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-27T14:00:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How long until the ads stop?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/how-long-until-the-ads-stop/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/how-long-until-the-ads-stop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In celebration of this day when the non-stop political ads, robo-calls, junk mail, and social media posts <em>should</em> finally come to an end. I threw together a little map to show the latest time at which polls close in each state. This should represent, state-by-state, the time (EST) at which you can safely go back to answering your phones. Click the image below to go there (the data takes a couple of seconds to load).</p>

<p><a href="http://demo.zekiah.com/polls"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2947" height="331" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/pollmap.png" title="pollmap" width="640" /></a></p>

<p>Democracy is a wonderful thing, but it will be nice to have this campaign season behind us.</p>

<p>{% youtube K1vaEweJUUk %}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Still Jonesing for zigGIS? Try this OGR Plug-In for ArcGIS.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I've actually noticed a surprising uptick in traffic related to <a href="https://code.google.com/p/ziggis/" target="_blank">zigGIS</a> lately? We also had someone asking about <a href="http://www.st-links.com/Pages/default.aspx" target="_blank">ST-Links</a> on the zigGIS mailing list last week. Clearly, there's still a level of interest out there for the problem that zigGIS was designed for.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank"><img alt="ArcGIS and SpatiaLite" height="65%" src="https://a248.e.akamai.net/camo.github.com/c1c86347c63522cb0f5f449b7b9df4209923c3ed/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f53767a6a702e706e67" width="65%" /></a></p>

<div style="font-size: 70%;"><strong>ArcGIS reading SpatiaLite natively, thanks to OGR and Ragi Burhum</strong></div>


<br />


<p>Along those lines, <a href="http://twitter.com/rburhum" target="_blank">Ragi Burhum</a> posted an <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/" target="_blank">OGR Workspace plug-in for ArcGIS</a> up on GitHub. Using OGR is really the magic ticket and the project is available under a BSD license (which Ragi explains very well). The only word to the wise is that pre-built binaries and installers aren't available yet so you Windows/<a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> users will need to get your hands dirty.</p>

<p>I haven't used it yet but I plan to within the next week or so. Stay tuned for a follow up post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Create a WeoGeo Tilepack from ArcGIS Tiles]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/14/create-a-weogeo-tilepack-from-arcgis-tiles/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/14/create-a-weogeo-tilepack-from-arcgis-tiles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of months ago, <a href="http://twitter.com/dandye" target="_blank">Dan Dye</a> at WeoGeo <a href="http://www.weogeo.com/blog/Create_WeoGeo_Tilepack_from_MBTiles_SQLite_database_with_mbutil.html" target="_blank">posted about work he had done</a> to facilitate creating <a href="http://www.weogeo.com" target="_blank">WeoGeo</a> tile packs from <a href="http://mapbox.com/developers/mbtiles/" target="_blank">MBTiles</a> databases. Recently, I had the need to do the same with <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> tiles. As Dan explained, WeoGeo uses a ZYX structure in their tile packs. This matched up nicely with the Level/Row/Column structure <a href="http://blogs.esri.com/esri/arcgis/2010/08/20/checking-your-local-cache-folders/" target="_blank">used by ArcGIS</a>. WeoGeo supports either WGS84 (EPSG:4326) or Spherical Mercator (EPSG:3857) as spatial references for tile packs. In my case, I used the latter. My preferred way of creating tiles from ArcGIS products is to use <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/" target="_blank">Arc2Earth</a>. While Arc2Earth does directly export to the WeoGeo structure, the tiles are watermarked with a WeoGeo logo, which was not needed in this case. Arc2Earth also exports to the ArcGIS structure, so a simple script to convert to the WeoGeo structure is all that was needed.</p>

<p><img alt="Arc2Earth settings to create ArcGIS Tiles" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2815" height="243" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/a2e_ags.png?w=300" title="Arc2Earth settings to create ArcGIS Tiles" width="300" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>So I wrote a Python script to migrate from the ArcGIS structure to the WeoGeo structure. It primarily uses file system operations with a little bit of logic to unroll the hex-based file naming convention used by Esri. That script can be found <a href="https://github.com/geobabbler/ags2weo" target="_blank">here on GitHub</a>. Be sure to check out the README for the current state of the script. The biggest potential gotcha is that it doesn't current use the ArcGIS conf.xml file so, if your ArcGIS cache contains non-consecutive zoom levels (0-2 and 4, for example), it will throw this script off. This has to do with the peculiarities in how Esri names the levels (Z) in their format. I'll be making this more robust in subsequent versions, along with with some work to provide a more complete workflow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Today Is World Diabetes Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/11/14/today-is-world-diabetes-day/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/11/14/today-is-world-diabetes-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.idf.org/worlddiabetesday/"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2225" height="383" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/wdd.png" title="World Diabetes Day" width="590" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/">Learn More...</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Have Fun In San Diego]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/07/01/have-fun-in-san-diego/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/07/01/have-fun-in-san-diego</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As everyone gears up for the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/user-conference/index.html">exodus to San Diego</a>, I wish everyone a good, enjoyable and fruitful time. There's something to be said for the energy of 12,000+ geonerds in one place. As for me, I'll be <a href="http://www.childrenwithdiabetes.com/activities/orlando2011/">here</a>, hanging with a couple hundred of the bravest, most inspiring young people you could ever meet. After that, it's family time and and little R&amp;R.</p>

<p>And be sure to use the <a href="http://uc.dtsagile.com/">Unofficial Esri UC BackChannel</a> by the guys at <a href="http://dtsagile.com/">DTS Agile</a>. It's a great way to enrich your experience.</p>

<p><img alt="Back soon." class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1879" height="302" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/07/back_soon.jpg" title="Back soon." width="400" /></p>

<p>Have fun and, hopefully, I'll catch up with many of you at <a href="http://2011.foss4g.org/">FOSS4G</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
