<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: GeoPackage | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/geopackage/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-11T22:38:23-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comment Period Open for GeoPackage Specification Draft]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/09/comment-period-open-for-geopackage-specification-draft/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-09T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/09/comment-period-open-for-geopackage-specification-draft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) has <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/pressroom/pressreleases/1756">published a draft GeoPackage specification for comment</a>. The GeoPackage specification attempts to create a non-proprietary means for packaging and exchanging all geospatial data in all its forms (vector, raster, and tiles). A couple of things that jump out at me:</p>

<ul>
<li>It calls out <a href="https://sqlite.org/">SQLite</a> as the reference implementation of a GeoPackage container</li>
<li>It calls out <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/">SpatiaLite</a> 4 as the reference implementation of a vector feature store</li>
<li>It does not call out a reference implementation for rasters or tiles</li>
<li>It does not mention exchange of cartography.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Although the draft references the <a href="http://mapbox.com/developers/mbtiles/">MBTiles</a> specification and uses it as an example of a pure SQL method of storing tiles, it does not call out MBTiles as the chosen storage approach nor does it mention MBTiles as a reference implementation. The draft should not be read as "SpatiaLite + MBTiles."</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://www.publicdomainpictures.net/view-image.php?image=9097&picture=empty-cardboard-boxes"><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/boxes.png" /></a></div>


<p>I think, in 2013, anything that attempts to do what GeoPackage sets out to do should have some provision for cartography. I would prefer CSS-like approach (such as <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/">CartoCSS</a>) and will say so when I submit comments but I would suspect that future discussion of cartography, if any, will probably start with SLD. For now, tiles can fill the gap.</p>

<p>So comments are open, give it a look and tell OGC what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
