<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: GIS | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/gis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-08T23:55:40-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Thoughts On the AppGeo Announcement]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/09/11/personal-thoughts-on-the-appgeo-announcement/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T20:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/09/11/personal-thoughts-on-the-appgeo-announcement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I read with great interest <a href="http://www.appgeo.com/blog/breaking-up-is-hard-to-do/">today's announcement that AppGeo is no longer an Esri Business Partner</a>. I find the announcement significant for a number of reasons, which I will explore shortly. I have always respected <a href="http://www.appgeo.com/">AppGeo's</a> work. As a small business that does geospatial consulting, they have foregone the "grow at all costs" approach that is seen all too often in the consulting world. They generally stuck to what they do well and branched out conservatively in ways that tie logically back to their core business.</p>

<p>I first met the President of AppGeo, Rich Grady, at an early <a href="https://www.hifldwg.org/">HIFLD</a> meeting many years ago. (It may have even been before the group was called "HIFLD.") The work they were doing then was very relevant to critical infrastructure protection efforts and, had some of their concepts for sharing data between state, local, and Federal agencies been adopted, we'd probably be better off today. I have always considered Rich one of the good guys in the geospatial industry and the company he has built reflects his integrity.</p>

<p>Over the years, our companies haven't quite found the right vehicle to work together and we sometimes even compete against each other. That's the nature of the consulting business. You will often compete against friends and still be able to have dinner together later.</p>

<p>So I was happy for Rich and AppGeo when I read their announcement. As I said above, I found it significant in a few ways...</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Professionalism</h2>

<p>The announcement was a textbook example of the professionalism with which such matters should be handled. AppGeo did not burn down the house in announcing they were no longer a business partner. There were no declarations that "Esri sucks" or any other such unnecessary hyperbole. They discussed real, significant differences that had evolved over time with Esri that lead to an agreement that their business interests had diverged to the point that a Business Partner status no longer made sense. While Esri initiated the final break, AppGeo handled it well, stated their case professionally, and gave no ground. Well done. This announcement should be required reading for the various factions and camps in our industry.</p>

<h2>A Sign of Maturity</h2>

<p>I found the announcement significant because I see it as evidence that AppGeo, as a geospatial business, has evolved to a point of maturity that most businesses never reach. They have built a diverse portfolio and realize they can go it alone without the safety net of Redlands under them. I will note that my company is an Esri Business Partner so I guess we haven't gotten there yet. I have worked as a consultant for my entire career and I believe to my bones that my primary job is to recommend the most appropriate solution to my customers. That is quite often an Esri solution for a lot of valid reasons, but not always. Right now, I am working on a project for a Federal agency based entirely on open-source geospatial tools. Often, a hybrid solution is really the best fit. The point is that, as a consultant, my job is to first gather data, analyze it, and determine the best solution. My job is not to walk in with a pre-conceived notion. If you call yourself a consultant and never look outside the Esri stable of tools (or whomever your preferred vendor may be), then you are not a consultant but a salesman. Just own it.</p>

<p>AppGeo recognizes this and has built a consulting practice that can proceed forward with less influence from large vendors. I commend them for that.</p>

<h2>Maturity of Open-Source Geospatial</h2>

<p>This next observation is statistically spurious as it is based only on this particular case, but I see this announcement as a sign of the increased maturity of the open-source geospatial segment. AppGeo is still a fairly small business, and many small consulting shops tend to be very conservative in their business moves. The fact that they are willing to decouple themselves from Esri indicates that they are not only confident in their capabilities with a diverse tool set, but that they are also confident in the stability and reliability of the tools in terms of being able to stake their business on them. Those of us who work with open-source geospatial tools are not surprised by this but it is important to note that AppGeo is as deeply proficient with the Esri tool suite as any company I've seen. I am not privy to their internal decision-making process but, at some point, a comparison must have yielded the conclusion that open-source tools (and Google) were sufficient to stand on equal footing in their capability portfolio. When a once-marquee partner like AppGeo reaches that conclusion, I find it significant.</p>

<p>Those represent some of my thoughts after reading the announcement. I recognized a lot in it but I can't say I've had all of the experiences they describe. I can't say that I've ever received any poor treatment from Esri as a Business Partner. I have heard enough stories from others that I don't doubt that it happens but I have never personally experienced it. Esri has always been exceedingly professional with me and my company. I don't feel like I've ever felt undue pressure to push their products to the front of the line but I recognize that my experience may be atypical.</p>

<p>In many ways, I expect all vendors to be partisan about their products, be it Esri or Microsoft or Oracle or Boundless or whomever. I would be suspicious if they weren't. Perhaps, because of that expectation, I've developed a bit of a filter for it but it doesn't bother me. My job as a consultant is to stand between my customers and the vendors and use my experience to sort through the market blather, find the real data, help my customers make an informed decision, and then help them implement. I have always felt that proficiency with a broad set of technologies makes me a better consultant, even for my strictly-Esri customers. AppGeo clearly understands this better than most and I commend them on reaching this significant and positive milestone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maryland Council on Open Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/08/26/maryland-council-on-open-data/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-26T17:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/08/26/maryland-council-on-open-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in May, I had the honor of being appointed to the newly established Maryland Council on Open Data. The Council had its inaugural meeting in Baltimore yesterday and was heavily attended, including attendance by Governor Martin O'Malley. I'll discuss his remarks to the group later.</p>

<p>As the first meeting of a new group, it went off largely as I expected. The agenda consisted primarily of an overview of the establishing legislation, a review of ethics requirements, demos of the existing open data portals, discussion of the history of open data in Maryland, and remarks from the Governor.</p>

<p>I won't go into details about the make-up of the Council, but they can be found here <a href="http://msa.maryland.gov/msa/mdmanual/25ind/html/53opendata.html">http://msa.maryland.gov/msa/mdmanual/25ind/html/53opendata.html</a>. Nor will I do a deep dive into the legislation, but it can be found here: <a href="http://mgaleg.maryland.gov/2014RS/chapters_noln/Ch_69_sb0644T.pdf">http://mgaleg.maryland.gov/2014RS/chapters_noln/Ch_69_sb0644T.pdf</a> (PDF). I will instead focus on my take-aways from the meeting itself.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>First, the establishing legislation makes data in Maryland open by default, unless it falls under certain criteria (personally identifiable information, law enforcement sensitive, etc.). Second, it is in fact legislation. Previous open data initiatives (MSGIC Executive Committee and the Maryland Open Data Working Group), were established by executive order. As a result, they were vulnerable to reversal by subsequent administrations and they had no real effect on other branches of government. Because of the new legislation, the open data has greater durability and active, enthusiastic participation from the state legislature.</p>

<p>So the new Council unifies the previous efforts and has top cover from the legislation. That can only be a good thing. The state currently has two open data portals: an <a href="http://data.imap.maryland.gov/">Esri Open Data portal</a> for geospatial data and a <a href="https://data.maryland.gov/">Socrata portal</a> for everything else. In practice, the lines between them may not be so distinct, but that's the stated role of each.</p>

<p>It is clear that open data is important to the Governor. Since his days as the Mayor of Baltimore, he has been known as a data-driven executive. The "CityStat" concept in Baltimore evolved into "StateStat" when he moved to Annapolis. It is widely known that data and metrics back everything his administration does. Open data is the other side of the coin. It is the mechanism by which the supporting data and metrics of the state government are made public.</p>

<p>In his remarks, the Governor highlighted Maryland's top ranking (shared by six states) in the <a href="http://www.datainnovation.org/2014/08/state-open-data-policies-and-portals/">Center for Data Innovation report of August 18, 2014</a> but then quickly addressed the remaining weaknesses identified. Specifically, he discussed:</p>

<ul>
<li>Reporting on spending data</li>
<li>The need for a more complete picture of all data sets</li>
<li>The need for better minimum metadata standards</li>
<li>The need for a uniform standard for giving citizens access to public information</li>
</ul>


<p>These are all fairly easy to address on the surface. In the open discussion that followed, the theme that I took away was "culture." Maryland has the policy framework and a good start on a technical framework to more fully open its data. The hard work, as it always is, is transforming the culture. As the requirements for opening data begin to trickle down into the daily lives of the people handling information, I think a lot of workflows will change. I also suspect some of the standards chosen for achieving compliance with open data requirements will facilitate significant changes to technical architectures in individual departments. In short, the proverbial onion will part to get peeled.</p>

<p>It's a lot of work and it won't happen quickly. I am excited for the opportunity to participate. I have worked in the private sector for my entire career (although in professional services to the government), so this is my first foray into anything resembling being on the public sector side of things. I expect I'll have a lot to learn.</p>

<p>My interest in open data has been somewhat spurred by the infrastructure data contraction that occurred in the mid-2000s in reaction to domestic security concerns. I felt it was the wrong direction to go then and I don't think making data harder to acquire really helped anyone. I'm looking forward to seeing what we can do on the Council to achieve the benefits other states, like Arkansas, have achieved through opening data rather than closing it off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JS.GEO 2014 Locked In Solid]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/31/js-dot-geo-2014-locked-in-solid/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-31T16:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/31/js-dot-geo-2014-locked-in-solid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back, <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/12/27/js-dot-geo-2014-announced/">I posted about about the 2014 edition of JS.GEO</a>. After that post, things got a little fluid, but I'm happy to finally be able to provide an update.</p>

<p>According to JS.GEO Organizer <a href="http://twitter.com/cwhelm">Chris Helm</a>, the event is <a href="https://twitter.com/cwhelm/status/494919297144066048">"locked in solid."</a></p>

<p>The event has a <a href="http://jsgeo.com">web site</a>, a location, and a date. <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/jsgeo-2014-tickets-12450450633">Tickets and sponsorships are available.</a> Agenda is to be announced and they are actively seeking speakers.</p>

<p>The first event was one of those serendipitous things that turned out to be pretty awesome. It was personally very influential on me and changed the focus of a lot of what I was doing with geospatial and with programming. It's probably the best single geospatial event I've attended in the last five years. The fact that FOSS4G will have already drawn a like-minded crowd to Portland should bode well for JS.GEO. My own attendance is still in question due to a number of factors but I highly recommend adding this to your schedule if you can.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ArcWhat? I Just Want My Map.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/30/arcwhat-i-just-want-my-map/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T15:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/30/arcwhat-i-just-want-my-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>TL;DR:</h3>

<p>What follows is probably my last post related to the Esri User Conference and is highly Esri-centric. Open-source readers may want to jump off here, or exercise a willing suspension of disbelief.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/16/the-esri-uc-so-far/">A couple of posts ago</a>, I did something that I generally try to avoid. I took <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> to task for its confusing product names without really offering any thoughts on how to make things better. I don't really like it when people do that to me so I'll try to correct that here. It bears noting that I was not the only person feeling this way at the UC. I was happy to see <a href="http://www.directionsmag.com/articles/making-sense-of-the-2014-esri-international-user-conference/410201">Adena's post over at Directions</a> touch on this and it also came up in a number of conversations I had while I was in San Diego.</p>

<p>Here are some things that I think may help. They represent most of the stumbling blocks I typically encounter when doing consulting/integration with Esri-centric users, especially new ones.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/93/Spaghetti.jpg" /> <br/>
 <sub>"<a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Spaghetti.jpg#mediaviewer/File:Spaghetti.jpg">Spaghetti</a>". Licensed under <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" title="Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0<p></p>">CC BY-SA 3.0</a> via <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/">Wikimedia Commons</a>.<sub></p>

<!--more-->


<ol>
<li><p>Retire the "Arc" prefix - It's confusing to have a relatively meaningless and seemingly random (to new users) prefix attached to everying. If you are moving to a platform concept, shouldn't that platform just bear your name? The company is Esri, the platform should be "Esri GIS" or something. Don't hide from your own product line. "Arc" is a verbal stumbling block. Try telling a user how to publish a map online and see how many times you say "Arc." Is it any wonder they get confused? It's like the old dog food commercial, except all they hear is "Blah blah Arc blah Arc blah blah Arc."</p></li>
<li><p>Acknowledge four environments for the platform - Mobile, Desktop, Server, Online. Period. "Esri GIS Desktop" or "Esri GIS Server" for example. Clean up spurious products that just clutter the menu. The current Explorer? Esri GIS Mobile (resist the urge to tack on "for iOS"). The current Portal? Esri GIS Online (Online can offer a hosted or on-premise version). What's the distinction between Esri GIS Server and an on-premise instance of Esri GIS Online? I don't know. Those are your waters to unmuddy.</p></li>
<li><p>One Desktop - Basic? Standard? Advanced? How about just Desktop? After 15 or so years of selling the three tiers, you should have enough data on the sales mix to set one normalized price for a fully-functional desktop product and be done with it. I suspect that price would hover somewhere between the current prices of Basic and Standard, perhaps closer to Standard. Everybody pays one price, everybody gets the current Advanced product. If nothing else, that code base should have long since paid for itself. Then you'll be better positioned for the inevitable transition to Esri GIS Pro (which could really just be the next Esri GIS Desktop) that everyone sees coming. Need more? Buy extensions.</p></li>
<li><p>Speaking of Extensions - You can have too much of a good thing. Roll some of them into core products (like Spatial Analyst). Doing so will assure users that a common set of tools will be available as they move between the environments (see item number 2). Furthermore, stop calling everything an "extension," which exacerbates the need for cumbersome qualifiers like "for Desktop" and "for Server." Choose a standard nomenclature for each environment and stick with it. Desktop can have "extensions" and server can have "adapters," for example. Then I know that a discussion about the Network Analyst Adapter is focused on Server.</p></li>
<li><p>Stop changing product names - Take any of the suggestions above, or do something else entirely. But, whatever you do, leave it alone once you're done. At least for a couple of dot releases, anyway.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Slow Food]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/29/slow-food/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T09:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/29/slow-food</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 1985, I was a junior in high school and I got my first job at a local chain steakhouse. I ended up staying there for a few years and did everything, including management. This particular location happened to be the busiest store in the chain, which had a couple hundred locations at the time. Basically, we just unlocked the doors and people came in. We often had a line and managers from all over the country came to see how we did business.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://s3-media3.fl.yelpcdn.com/bphoto/NhIU66uSYbsi9LPzBpSgwA/l.jpg" /></p>

<p>Eventually, I transferred to another store that happened to be much slower. I expected this to be a something of a cakewalk compared to the store I had just left. Sometime during my first day, the long-time manager made a point to remind me to close the back dining room after lunch and turn the lights out. The dark room looked uninviting to me so I asked if we could leave the lights on. He replied that doing so would raise the electric bill and affect the store's profits. Over the next few weeks, I learned so many new techniques for managing food inventory, staffing levels, and equipment that I realized my initial impression was wrong. So I told the manager this. He was not surprised.</p>

<p>He said to me: "It takes more skill to run a slow store than a busy one."</p>

<!--more-->


<p>He was absolutely right. At the first location, we would simply order enough food to fill the walk-ins and did enough prep every day to fill the racks. We quickly ramped our staffing up to max levels every day and just waited for the customers to roll in. There was a myriad of issues we simply never had to worry about because sales volume masked them.</p>

<p>It's been many years since I've had to work in a restaurant but I have found this observation applicable throughout my career, during which I have worked primarily in the defense industry, designing and building various forms of geospatial tools and systems. Two weeks ago, I attended the Esri International User Conference. The Esri UC is full of opportunities to see more of these types of applications, from the Defense Showcase to the National Security Summit to many defense/intel/homeland security related paper sessions.</p>

<p>I attended almost none of them.</p>

<p>Over the past few years, I have developed the habit of attending sessions related to local governments, non-profits and other small organizations. These organizations tend to have budgets that are essentially rounding error in the defense world and I have become much more intrigued by the solutions they build to meet their missions with so few resources.</p>

<p>Of course, I was at an Esri conference, so everyone I saw was an Esri user. It's no secret that Esri tools tend to be expensive and every dollar counts for small governments, so I am intrigued how these organizations arrive at the choice of Esri tools in light of so many other capable options. Too often, there is a misconception that these small governments simply choose Esri-based solutions out of a lack of understanding of alternatives. What I have discovered is, like the manager of the slow restaurant, some of the best business understanding and most cogent and well-reasoned justifications come from these small users.</p>

<p>They seem to take a much more holistic approach to evaluating their solutions; including the availability of support from the technology provider as well as the existence of a robust third-party community that enables them to effectively compete for value-added services, customizations, and consulting. What I found interesting has been the most consistent attraction of local governments and small organizations to Esri-based solutions: the seamless integration of the entire ArcGIS platform. From mobile to desktop to web, they find that Esri tools make it easier to move through the product lifecycle. This exposes a very business-centric way of thinking that is larger than any individual technology or its licensing cost.</p>

<p>As I indicated above, an Esri conference places a huge filter on the users whom you meet. As I attend less vendor-centric events in the months ahead, I'd like to continue this line of inquiry. While landing the giant white whales of large Federal agencies might be more satisfying for the short-term bottom line, it is important to remember that all levels of government are facing downward budget pressure. Learning the thought processes of organizations that have always had to tightly manage limited resources may be more valuable in the long run.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
