<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Federal Government | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/federal-government/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-17T11:43:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilson Center to Discuss FCC National Broadband Map]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/09/wilson-center-to-discuss-fcc-national-broadband-map/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/09/wilson-center-to-discuss-fcc-national-broadband-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most compelling recent success stories for open-source geospatial tools in the Federal Government has been the <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/" target="_blank">Federal Communications Commission</a> (FCC) <a href="http://broadbandmap.gov/" target="_blank">National Broadband Map</a> initiative. It has been a very visible example of the stability, scalability, flexibility, and power of open-source geospatial tools.</p>

<p>The Woodrow Wilson Center will be hosting <a href="http://www.wilsoncenter.org/event/the-national-broadband-map-case-study-open-innovation-for-national-policy" target="_blank">a case study of National Broadband Map</a> on October 15th, 2012. The event's page also includes a link to the full paper (PDF), authored by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=113470334" target="_blank">Zachary Bastian</a> of the Wilson Center and <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=10690378" target="_blank">Michael Byrne</a> of the FCC.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2933" height="285" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/nbm.png" title="nbm" width="640" /></p>

<p>The full paper, in my opinion, is recommended reading for anyone working with geospatial technologies in the government space. While the Broadband Map has rightfully garnered significant attention based upon its success, especially in terms of performance and scalability, the paper does a good job of reminding us that the map is not an end goal in itself, but a step toward the larger policy goal of expanding broadband access. The paper does an excellent job of illustrating how top-level policy goals were broken down into actionable parts that resulted in a concrete product such as the Broadband Map. In so doing, it walks us through the introduction and fostering of an open culture within the FCC that resulted not only in the Broadband Map but also in the development of open APIs and the availability of FCC tools as open-source projects themselves.</p>

<p>In its conclusions, the paper also makes compelling observations about the power of focused policy goals to drive the use of technology standing in stark contrast to generic overarching technical policies, such as the National Spatial Data Infrastructure (NSDI) which are disconnected from specific policy goals and achieve little traction.</p>

<p>If you are interested not only in geospatial technologies, but also the link between policy and technology implementation, and the cultural change that can be brought about by open-source technologies, you should consider attending the event at the Wilson Center on the 15th. While not a universal blueprint, the National Broadband Map makes a compelling case study.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking Ahead to the 2009 ESRI Federal User Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/01/19/looking-ahead-to-the-2009-esri-federal-user-conference/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/01/19/looking-ahead-to-the-2009-esri-federal-user-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is time again for my annual plug for the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/feduc/index.html">ESRI Federal User Conference (FedUC)</a>. Last year, I <a href="http://wordpress.com/tag/feduc/">blogged</a> as much as could. It's no secret that I thought last year's FedUC was the best they had done. It was the first one where I felt that there was more content than I could get to. It was a good mix of technology and real-world user implementations. Additionally, I had a lot of side meetings so it has become a good place to get some business done.<!--more--></p>

<p>I am being something of a homer when I push the FedUC because it happens in my back yard and I do want to see it continue. It is a shorter conference and those who are used to the more party-like atmosphere of San Diego will find this one much more focused and businesslike but I like that.</p>

<p>Federal employees get in for free but state and local staff from around the region should consider it as well. The technical information is relevant beyond the Federal sector and many of the paper sessions will provide insights into concepts that cross-pollinate well to other areas. For example, there is a session on managing transportation systems.</p>

<p>Last year, I had the opportunity to attend the FedUC, the Dev Summit in Palm Springs and the IUC in San Diego and, as a result, I got to see the full narrative arc across the conferences. At the FedUC, 9.3 was about to enter beta and there was a lot of anticipation. At the Dev Summit, there was more technical detail about how many of the new features were implemented and could be used. By the time of the IUC, 9.3 was on the street and "real" and there was more of a focus on use cases and applications of the new features. It will be interesting to see what themes that are introduced at the FedUC this year.</p>

<p>Ultimately, I'd like to see ESRI broaden the FedUC into more of a "public sector" focus to appeal to various levels of government. I think the "Federal" title may filter some who would get benefit from the information presented at the conference.</p>

<p>Anyway, I'll be there. Hopefully I'll see some of you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
