<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: MapWindow | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/mapwindow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-27T09:20:38-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New MapWindow Beta Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/06/new-mapwindow-beta-available/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/08/06/new-mapwindow-beta-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Paul Meems announced today that a new beta version of MapWindow is available. From the announcement:</p>

<blockquote>
We've just released the Beta Version of July.

It is available at <a href="http://svn.mapwindow.org/svnroot/InstallationProjects/4.8/Releases/MapWindowx86Full-v48Beta-installer.exe">http://svn.mapwindow.org/svnroot/InstallationProjects/4.8/Releases/MapWindowx86Full-v48Beta-installer.exe</a>

The supporting libraries (like GDAL, GEOS) have been updated to their latest versions.
A lot of new enhancements have been added to the ocx, like image grouping, image overviews (pyramids), symbology (charts and coloring), use of the rotation values in world files.
Not all new features made it yet to the Desktop, but we're working on that.
The features are available to you for your plug-in or script development or when you develop a custom application using the ocx.
</blockquote>


<p>MapWindow is quite a powerful open-source (Mozilla Public License) mapping library for .NET. It's under active development and seems to be adding capability rapidly. If you're a developer looking for a library to add spatial capability to your application, you may want to check it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MapWindow to .NET]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/12/mapwindow-to-net/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/09/12/mapwindow-to-net</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.mapwindow.org/">MapWindow</a> open-source project will be holding its <a href="http://www.mapwindow.org/conference/2010/index.php">first-ever user conference</a> from March 31 to April 2, 2010 in Orlando, Florida. Aside from being a great milestone for MapWindow, it is also being billed as a "coming out party" for MapWindow  6, its first native .NET version.</p>

<p>For those of you who are not familiar with MapWindow, it is and open-source (MPL 1.1) mapping library (think SharpMap or MapObjects) for use in developing applications, managed by the Geospatial Software Lab at Idaho State University. Although its desktop application and some geoprocessing tools have been written in .NET (VB.NET and C# respectively) for some time, the main library has been a 32-bit ActiveX control written in C++. At version 6, it will finally be fully .NET.</p>

<p>I had used MapWindow a little bit some years ago but haven't recently due to its ActiveX structure. I will definitely add it to my (ever-growing) list of things to check out now that it's been ported.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MapWindow Looking for Testers and Programmers]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/09/03/mapwindow-looking-for-testers-and-programmers/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/09/03/mapwindow-looking-for-testers-and-programmers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mapwindow.org/">MapWindow</a> is has posted a message over on <a href="http://www.linkedin.com">LinkedIn</a> looking for testers and programmers. The text of the message, posted by Paul Meems, is:</p>

<blockquote>Any GIS experts available with some free time?
Here at MapWindow GIS (<a href="http://www.mapwindow.org">www.mapwindow.org</a>) we're looking for people who are willing the use MapWindow (it's Open Source, so it's free to use) and share their experiences. We also have our own LinkedIn group: <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/e/gis/122945/37A6504A848A">http://www.linkedin.com/e/gis/122945/37A6504A848A</a></blockquote>


<p>A follow-up answer to one of my LinkedIn contacts clarified that they are looking for testers and programmers. So, if you're interested in helping out an open-source project, here's your chance. Also, you may want to give LinkedIn a spin.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
