<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jobs | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/jobs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-24T14:05:01-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking for a Few Good Developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/07/25/looking-for-a-few-good-developers/"/>
    <updated>2008-07-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2008/07/25/looking-for-a-few-good-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Typically, I try not to directly mix work and blogging but here goes:</p>

<p>If you've poked around my blog enough, you know that I'm a partner at <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah Technologies</a> in <a href="http://http://maps.google.com/maps?sourceid=navclient&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;rlz=1T4GGIH_enUS258US258&amp;q=la+plata,MD&amp;um=1&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=geocode_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=title">La Plata, MD</a>. We are currently looking for up to four .Net developers to support various projects. ESRI development experience is a plus. Depending on the project, you could find yourself working with ArcGIS Server, ArcIMS, ArcSDE, Oracle, SQL Server, PostgreSQL. Some of the projects are supporting systems that have been in place for a while and require migration from older technologies. All will involve the development of new capability.</p>

<p>Once again, work location may vary depending upon the project but it will either be in <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?sourceid=navclient&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;rlz=1T4GGIH_enUS258US258&amp;q=Dahlgren+va&amp;um=1&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=geocode_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=title">Dahlgren</a>, <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?sourceid=navclient&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;rlz=1T4GGIH_enUS258US258&amp;q=norfolk+va&amp;um=1&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=geocode_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=title">Norfolk </a>or <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?sourceid=navclient&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;rlz=1T4GGIH_enUS258US258&amp;q=reston+va&amp;um=1&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=geocode_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=title">Reston</a> in Virginia (especially Dahlgren). We are a consulting company that does development and implementation for our customers. For these positions, customer requirements specify US citizenship. Foreign travel may be required.</p>

<p>I chose to blog about this because I and all of my partners will be at the ESRI User Conference in San Diego and it seemed like it might be a convenient place to talk since so many people will be there. We will be staffing booth 612 so feel free to stop by if you're interested.</p>

<p>For those who read this and may be thinking this way: we are not at liberty to sub-contract any of these positions.</p>

<p>Feel free to contact me via e-mail if you have any questions: bill@zekiah.com</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
