<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: QGIS | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/qgis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:00:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Geospatial Workflows]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/Personal-Geospatial-Workflows/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/Personal-Geospatial-Workflows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've had a couple of people ask me recently about the geospatial tools I use. Year-over-year, that answer changes but here's how I answer that right now:</p>

<p>As a Federal contractor, I spend a lot of time working with the <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> stack during my work day. A few years ago, I added a few open-source geospatial tools into my tool set and, since then, have also done a respectable amount to consulting work them as well. The balance between the two varies over time, depending on the requirements of individual customers and projects. Lately, commercial customers have seemed much more interested in open-source tools while my government customers are sticking with Esri. Since those observations are based on the the extremely heavy filter of my own recent experience, I'd be hesitant to draw any larger conclusions from them.</p>

<p><img alt="" height="264" src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/duct-tape.jpg" title="Duct Tape" width="300" /></p>

<p>I've always believed that proficiency with a wide range of tools makes me a better consultant and integrator, so I am always exploring and trying new things. With those commercial customers, and in my own personal side projects, my recent workflows have gelled around a core set of tools, both commercial and open-source: <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> - I am very comfortable with SQL and tend to use <a href="http://www.postgresql.org" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> and PostGIS for a lot of my vector data processing. Lately, this has mainly involved joining up geometries with attributes and doing aggregations and similar things. For example, the vector data in this <a href="http://geobabbler.github.com/mdq62012.html" target="_blank">map of the county-level Maryland Question 6 results</a> was processed in PostGIS. Very simply, I have a baseline table of the counties of Maryland which I will use to create new data sets. In this case, I imported a CSV of the election results, created a view that joined up the data and then selected the view into a new table. This is workflow is much easier with PostGIS 2.x thanks to the <a href="http://blog.opengeo.org/2012/03/06/postgis-2-0-new-features-typmod/" target="_blank">use of typmod</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a> - In the case of the map mentioned above, the data set is ultimately going to be static so it makes sense to serve it as static content, rather than bringing a heavyweight geospatial server such as <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgisserver/" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> or <a href="http://geoserver.org/display/GEOS/Welcome" target="_blank">GeoServer</a> into the mix. In these cases, I lean toward <a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>. QGIS makes it very easy to export any vector layer out to GeoJSON so it's become my go-to tool for that. QGIS also has great analytical tools and I consider it a complete functional match for ArcMap but, having said that, I'm actually very comfortable with the spatial SQL functions in PostGIS so I end up doing most of my analytical work there.</p>

<p><a href="http://leafletjs.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a>/<a href="http://www.openlayers.org/" target="_blank">OpenLayers</a> - Most of the web maps I'm doing are single-use and pretty straightforward. When that's the case, I prefer to use Leaflet as it's a pretty lightweight library. That said, I keep OpenLayers in the mix if the GIS-like requirements get a little more complex. OpenLayers does more "out of the box" than Leaflet but Leaflet is trimmer so it really depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/" target="_blank">Arc2Earth</a>/<a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill </a>- Arc2Earth is a commercial extension to ArcGIS and I lean on it to make tiles, although it does a lot more than that. I also use TileMill for this purpose but it really depends on where my cartography resides. There's a lot of good cartography locked up in MXDs and Arc2Earth is just a great way to capitalize on that. It's also nice that Arc2Earth works in ArcMap, eliminating the need for a license of Server.  If I'm building my cartography from scratch, which is not really my strong suit, I'll lean toward TileMill because it more easily connects directly to PostGIS, which is where my data tends to reside if I have my druthers. Again, it depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.python.org/" target="_blank">Python</a>/Javascript - I'm doing a lot more work in Python these days. It's become the <em>lingua franca</em> of GIS development in my book. Additionally, the capabilities of Javascript for web maps is evolving at a stunning pace. I can't see being productive in the long term in the geospatial field without proficiency in these two languages.</p>

<p>So these are the tools that I'm using most often these days as part of my personal workflows. The stable of tools that I use evolves over time, as should be evident if you peruse this blog. In general, I'm finding it very easy to be productive with these tools right now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How long until the ads stop?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/How-long-until-the-ads-stop/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/06/How-long-until-the-ads-stop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In celebration of this day when the non-stop political ads, robo-calls, junk mail, and social media posts <em>should</em> finally come to an end. I threw together a little map to show the latest time at which polls close in each state. This should represent, state-by-state, the time (EST) at which you can safely go back to answering your phones. Click the image below to go there (the data takes a couple of seconds to load).</p>

<p><a href="http://demo.zekiah.com/polls"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2947" height="331" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/pollmap.png" title="pollmap" width="640" /></a></p>

<p>Democracy is a wonderful thing, but it will be nice to have this campaign season behind us.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/K1vaEweJUUk?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Favorite QGIS Resources of the Moment]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/27/Favorite-QGIS-Resources-of-the-Moment/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/27/Favorite-QGIS-Resources-of-the-Moment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been dabbling more with Quantum GIS (<a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a>) lately. I'm not doing anything particularly sophisticated but it's a great viewer for some data types (<a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a>, <a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>) that aren't supported by my commercial desktop GIS so it's helping me validate outputs of some applications I'm writing.</p>

<p><img alt="" src="http://fossies.org/unix/misc/qgis-1.8.0.tar.gz:a/qgis-1.8.0/images/splash/splash.png" /></p>

<p>While I'll never be a real cartographer, I am interested in doing a little more. Here are the resources that have been helping me the most lately...</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I'll start with three blogs:</p>

<p><a href="http://underdark.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">Anita Graser</a> (<a href="http://twitter.com/underdarkgis" target="_blank">@underdarkgis</a>)</p>

<p><a href="http://woostuff.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">Nathan Woodrow</a> (<a href="http://twitter.com/madmanwoo" target="_blank">@madmanwoo</a>)</p>

<p><a href="http://mapbox.com/blog/" target="_blank">The MapBox Blog</a> (<a href="http://twitter.com/mapbox" target="_blank">@mapbox</a>)</p>

<p>The MapBox blog takes some explaining. It is primarily about how to be productive with MapBox, but some posts deal with using QGIS in your workflows. Those posts have some good information. All of these blogs have been helpful to me over the last couple of months.</p>

<p>Outside of that, I set up a Google Alert for QGIS which feeds me all kinds of things: posts from other blogs, mailing entries, StackExchange questions, and so on. To make that easy, I ran the feed from that alert through <a href="http://ifttt.com/" target="_blank">ifttt.com</a> and have it posting to a Twitter account: (<a href="http://twitter.com/QGISInfo" target="_blank">@QGISInfo</a>). Feel free to check it out. Keep in mind that it's based on a Google search so odd results may creep in from time to time. I've been running the alert for a few weeks and it's been pretty clean. The Twitter feed is new and will be sparse until a few refresh cycles happen. Think of it as a poor man's "Planet QGIS." I hope you find it useful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[QGIS 1.8.0 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/21/QGIS-1-8-0-Released/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/21/QGIS-1-8-0-Released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I caught a tweet by my friend <a href="http://www.paolocorti.net/" target="_blank">Paolo Corti</a> this morning that <a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a> 1.8.0 has been released.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>qgis 1.8.0 "Lisboa" released! <a href="http://t.co/UZWFzy0m" title="http://goo.gl/eSDYo">goo.gl/eSDYo</a></p>&mdash; Paolo Corti (@capooti) <a href="https://twitter.com/capooti/status/215767511990415360" data-datetime="2012-06-21T11:25:58+00:00">June 21, 2012</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>Upon checking out the full list of new features <a href="http://lists.osgeo.org/pipermail/qgis-developer/2012-June/020685.html" target="_blank">here</a>, a few caught my eye:</p>

<blockquote>
- QGIS Browser - a stand alone app and a new panel in QGIS. The
browser lets you easily navigate your file system and connection based
(PostGIS, WFS etc.) datasets, preview them and drag and drop items
into the canvas.

- DB Manager - the DB manager is now officially part of QGIS core. You
can drag layers from the QGIS Browser into DB Manager and it will
import your layer into your spatial database. Drag and drop tables
between spatial databases and they will get imported. You can use the
DB Manager to execute SQL queries against your spatial database and
then view the spatial output for queries by adding the results to QGIS
as a query layer.

- MSSQL Spatial Support - you can now connect to your Microsoft SQL
Server spatial databases using QGIS.

- Support for PostGIS TopoGeometry datatype

- Terrain Analysis Plugin - a new core plugin was added for doing
terrain analysis - and it can make really good looking coloured relief
maps.

- Heatmap tool - a new core plugin has been added for generating
raster heatmaps from point data. You may need to activate this plugin
using the plugin manager.
</blockquote>




<!--more-->


<p>It looks like a lot of focus has been placed on making it easier to user your data. If you are not familiar with QGIS, it's the best open-source desktop GIS out there and stands toe-to-toe with any commercial equivalent. A few years ago, desktop GIS was considered to be something of an Achilles heel for open-source GIS but that hasn't been true for a long time. I integrated QGIS into my work a while back and it figures more prominently for me with each release.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2692" height="225" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/smiley-happy-face-yellow.jpg?w=300" title="Smiley-happy-face-yellow" width="300" /></p>

<p>To get a sense of the kind of things you can do with QGIS, check out <a href="http://mapbox.com/blog/binning-alternative-point-maps/" target="_blank">this post</a> on the <a href="http://mapbox.com/" target="_blank">MapBox</a> blog and also check out <a href="http://woostuff.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">Nathan Woodrow's blog</a>. In addition, <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/dmgeo" target="_blank">Caitlyn Dempsey's</a> recent <a href="http://gislounge.com/where-are-the-gis-jobs-a-look-at-the-gis-job-market-in-the-united-states/" target="_blank">map of GIS job availability</a> was built using QGIS. These links are good examples to show that QGIS is excellent, professional GIS tool.</p>

<p>I think my download just finished...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MapWindow Open-Source Conference Coming Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/05/25/MapWindow-Open-Source-Conference-Coming-Up/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/05/25/MapWindow-Open-Source-Conference-Coming-Up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to Twitter, I see that the <a href="http://www.mapwindow.org/conference/2012/" target="_blank">3rd annual MapWindow Open-Source GIS Conference</a> is coming up at the end of June. It is being held in Velp, The Netherlands. I call this conference out because it has a strong, but not exclusive, concentration on open-source GIS tools for the .Net environment, such as <a href="http://dotspatial.codeplex.com/" target="_blank">DotSpatial</a>, <a href="http://sharpmap.codeplex.com/" target="_blank">SharpMap</a>, and <a href="https://code.google.com/p/nettopologysuite/" target="_blank">NTS</a>. Additionally, there will be content on non-.Net tools such as PostGIS, OpenLayers and others. This makes sense as any complete stack usually contains a mix of technologies. <a href="http://postgis.org/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> is almost the <em>de facto</em> standard back-end for open-source geo stacks and <a href="http://qgis.org/" target="_blank">QGIS</a> is probably the best open-source editor for it so inclusion of such tools is quite necessary.</p>

<p><img alt="MapWindow" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/mapwindow.png?w=245" /></p>

<p>For a number of reasons, I can't attend but I'll be watching the live stream with interest. It's location in Europe makes a lot of sense. I've always noticed that my early posts on SharpMap get a large portion of traffic from Europe and a majority of the user base of <a href="https://code.google.com/p/ziggis/" target="_blank">zigGIS</a> was European so I suspect there is a lot of demand there for open-source tools built on .Net. This conference could be a good one-stop shop if you are interested in such tools.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
