<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: postgresql | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/postgresql/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-28T06:40:24-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planet PostGIS Online]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/07/planet-postgis-online/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/07/07/planet-postgis-online</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://planet.postgis.net/">Planet PostGIS</a>, an aggregation of <a href="http://postgis.refractions.net/">PostGIS</a>-related blog content is now online. As the name suggests, it is built using the same technology as <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com">James Fee's</a> <a href="http://planetgs.com">Planet Geospatial</a> but is focused on content related to PostGIS.</p>

<p>If you are working with PostGIS, whether as part of an open-source stack or in conjunction with proprietary tools such as ArcGIS, you may want to check out Planet PostGIS.</p>

<p>Thanks to <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/regina-obe/7/5/200">Regina Obe</a> and everyone involved in setting this up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breaking Radio Silence]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/07/breaking-radio-silence/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/07/breaking-radio-silence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things have been kind of quiet on the blog lately due to things being busy at work. I call that a good problem to have. Since the beginning of the year, I've written a a lot of proposals for a mixture of potential customers. Interestingly, I'm seeing a lot more call for "GIS Analyst" work. One trend I've noticed, at least in the Federal sector, is that the time between proposal due dates and award announcements seems to be lengthening. That may be an indication of the ongoing flux in funding and organizations try to figure out how to fund their requirements. It will be interesting to see how it shakes out. Of course, it's good that the opportunities are there in the first place.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/microphone.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2664" height="413" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/microphone.jpg" title="microphone" width="413" /></a></p>

<p>One the technical side of things, I've been involved in a smattering of things that's made it hard to roll up one good post. I'm pretty heavily involved in the PIM efforts that my colleague, Barry Schimpf, <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim" target="_blank">has been blogging about</a> over on the <a href="http://www.zekiah.com" target="_blank">Zekiah</a> blog. <!--more--> Historically, the PIM data structures have been housed in Microsoft SQL Server, but we've been working on porting it to other platforms to provide options to end users. We've done an initial port to <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> but we've been spending most of our time on a <a href="http://www.sqlite.org/" target="_blank">SQLite</a>/<a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> version. This has taken two forms. First is the port of the PIM structure itself to SQLite to make it easier to provide some of the PIM services such as profiling, version-to-version migrations, dataset generation, and validation in remote, field-based settings. Second is the generation/validation of physical implementations in SpatiaLite. This is being done for a customer who is expecting to do field data collection using SpatiaLite and these services will be helpful in enhancing data quality at the point of collection. Additionally, the SpatiaLite aspect of this work has had me living within <a href="http://qgis.org/" target="_blank">QGIS</a> lately.</p>

<p>Another thing I've been experimenting with is the use of <a href="http://nodejs.org/" target="_blank">Node.js</a> for real-time data processing. Our long-standing work in the situational awareness realm has had us working with real-time data feeds for a long time. I'm interested in the possibility of using Node to tackle some of the feed collection tasks. I've used an event-driven approach for such tasks in the past so that aspect of Node is quite familiar to me but the use of Javascript, its ease of deployment and potential scalability are intriguing to me. I'm coming late to the party with Node, primarily due to my rustiness with Javascript, but I'm liking what I'm seeing so far.</p>

<p>Beyond those major things, I've had the opportunity to start working with <a href="http://postgis.org/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> 2.0 and play more with <a href="http://leaflet.cloudmade.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a> and <a href="http://mapbox.com/" target="_blank">MapBox</a>. On the development side of things, these efforts have had be jumping back and forth a lot between C#, Javascript and a little bit of Python, as well as between Windows and Linux, depending on the task.</p>

<p>You'll notice that I didn't mention any <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> tools. That's primarily because recent demand from my customers has led me to a different tool set. I expect that to level out somewhat in the near future since many of the outstanding proposals I mentioned have a strong Esri flavor. As always, having a broad toolbox can be an asset in consulting. I'll be skipping San Diego again this year. I'm finding that Esri's Federal Conference in DC is of such increasing quality each year that it fulfills my needs for Esri-related information. That's really okay with me because I'd rather spend as much of the summer with my family as possible. So it's not so much a down-vote of Esri as my taking advantage of options that fit into my life better.</p>

<p>I hope to be able blog in more detail about some of these efforts as I get farther along with them. Times like this make it exciting to work in the geospatial field. There's a lot of churn in the market right now with regard to tools and technologies. I'm not sure I can perceive any meaningful gap between the capabilities of open-source and proprietary geospatial tools anymore. As a result, there are a lot of options to choose from for building robust systems and applications. It looks to be a fun summer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FOSS4G North America]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/04/12/foss4g-north-america/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/04/12/foss4g-north-america</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's rather fitting that the second plenary talk on Wednesday had to do with "firehose" applications since the <a href="http://foss4g-na.org/" target="_blank">FOSS4G North America</a> (FOSS4GNA) conference was something of a firehose in itself. Despite the fact that the event was smaller than the worldwide event in Denver back in October, I came away with the same "full brain" feeling.</p>

<p><img alt="It feels like I never leave this place." src="http://www.visitingdc.com/images/washington-dc-convention-center.jpg" /></p>

<p>Of course, given the recent production release of <a href="http://blog.opengeo.org/2012/04/03/postgis-2-0-released/" target="_blank">PostGIS 2.0</a>, that was kind of the big story for this event. I attended a number of <a href="http://postgis.org/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a>/<a href="http://www.postgresql.org/" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a>-related sessions and came away with lots of new information. I especially enjoyed <a href="http://twitter.com/pwramsey" target="_blank">Paul Ramsey's</a> "what's new" talk on Wednesday. One thing I enjoy about his talks (here and in Denver) is that he's not afraid to throw sample SQL up on the screen. It's one thing to hear about a new feature but it's another thing entirely to see a concrete example. Some may find the idea of raw SQL in a presentation abhorrent but it worked for me. <!--more--></p>

<p>I've already started playing with PostGIS 2.0 but haven't gotten terribly far so these sessions helped a lot. It's already been pretty well vetted by the community during it's various pre-release stages so it seems remarkably stable. With the addition of topology and raster analysis in addition to 3D/4D indexing and new vector functions, PostGIS probably handles the majority of what most users would need for GIS analysis at the database level. I'm excited to dig deeper.</p>

<p>I also attended a few web-mapping themed talks. If there is one word that consistently and repeatedly passed the lips of most of the presenters, it was "<a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>." I've <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/?s=geojson" target="_blank">blogged about GeoJSON</a> in the past but it really is the oil that makes the modern geo-web run smoothly. The rate of adoption it is receiving rivals only one other <em>de facto</em> standard that I can recall: you may remember something called the shapefile. The fact is that anyone who's been hunting through their file system looking for the "next shapefile" has been looking in the wrong place. It lives behind that nice map in your browser. The shapefile took off because it solved a problem for what was the frontier of GIS in the 1990s; the transition from heavy workstations to desktop mapping. GeoJSON solves the problem of delivering vector spatial data for today's frontier; the transition from the desktop GIS to web mapping. It's that simple. We don't need another file format to solve an old problem that already has a solution.</p>

<p>Of course, there was a lot more. I got introduced to <a href="http://cartodb.com/" target="_blank">CartoDB</a> in Denver, have <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/10/13/cartodb-leaflet-easy/" target="_blank">experimented with it</a> since then and was able to get an update on its 1.0 release at one of the sessions. It remains a compelling option for spatial data hosting and <a href="http://vizzuality.com/" target="_blank">Vizzuality</a> are actively engaging with the open-source communities that build the tools they use. On the cartography side of things, <a href="http://stamen.com/" target="_blank">Stamen</a> continues to show how beautiful maps can be made with open-source tools. Similarly, <a href="http://mapbox.com/" target="_blank">MapBox</a> showed how they efficiently deliver high-quality maps on the web. For my money, the unsung hero of what MapBox is doing is <a href="http://mapbox.com/mbtiles-spec/utfgrid/" target="_blank">UTFGrid</a>. I hadn't delved into it deeply until I saw the announcement that <a href="http://www.openlayers.org/" target="_blank">OpenLayers</a> now supports it. UTFGrid is breathtakingly elegant in its approach to delivering richer content with tiles. I expect that, in a few years, UTFGrid will be a standard part under the hood of any web mapping experience, like tiles and slippy maps are today.</p>

<p>The only consistent criticism I heard was that most of the sessions were "too technical." I can see some validity to this, given that the event was held in Washington, DC and many higher-level government or policy types who may have been seeking to conceptually understand open-source geospatial may have been put off. Commercial vendors have addressed this problem with the establishment of "executive tracks" at their events. That said, if that's the biggest criticism that can be leveled, then FOSS4GNA was a rousing success in my book.</p>

<p>I have resolved that I will take at least one of my kids, if not both, to the next FOSS4G event that I attend. The attitude of the open-source crowd is one that I want to rub off on them. Aside from the energy that is exuded from a gathering such as this, the open-source world is full of people who see a problem and just set out to solve it. I want my kids to be exposed to that kind of initiative and understand the power that can come from harnessing it, even if they never go into a technical field.</p>

<p>My understanding is that FOSS4GNA came together very quickly. Given that, it was a very high-quality conference and the organizers should be commended. Early tongue-in-cheek commentary referred to it as the "<a href="http://opengeo.org/" target="_blank">OpenGeo </a>User Conference." I felt like there was good balance and, when I attended sessions given by OpenGeo staff, I didn't feel like I was beaten over the head with the OpenGeo brand. All-in-all, I found my day-and-a-half at FOSS4GNA to be very beneficial and I'm hoping it becomes an annual event. (<strong>Update</strong>: It looks like next year's FOSS4GNA <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/foss4gna/status/190517270928293888" target="_blank">will be in Minnesota</a>.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking of the 84%...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/08/speaking-of-the-84/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/02/08/speaking-of-the-84</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>HT to <a href="http://sproke.blogspot.com/2012/02/game-changer-open-source-mapping-in.html">Sophia Parafina for the 84%</a>.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE</strong>: The NSIS script at utility batch file discussed here is now on github at <a href="https://github.com/geobabbler/pgstandalone" target="_blank">https://github.com/geobabbler/pgstandalone</a>. I'll post a readme in the next day or so.</p>

<p>A few months ago, I asked the following question on Twitter and got this reply from Paul Ramsey:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-in-reply-to="136481537792294912"><p>@<a href="https://twitter.com/billdollins">billdollins</a> Possible yes, but might have to roll your own? You can get raw binaries in a zip file from download site...?</p>&mdash; Paul Ramsey (@pwramsey) <a href="https://twitter.com/pwramsey/status/136565522836897796" data-datetime="2011-11-15T22:05:32+00:00">November 15, 2011</a></blockquote>
<script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>We are working with a Federal Government customer that had the interesting policy that users can install software as long as it makes no changes to the Windows registry. These users are currently running a mix of Windows 7 and XP. We are working with them to help manage one of their data models. In this case, it's more about performing configuration management on the model/standard itself rather than physical databases with real data in them. It's a topic we touched on over at the Zekiah blog <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/2012/01/13/expanding-usefulness-geospatial-data-standards" target="_blank">here</a> and an approach we have used successfully for years to manage the <a href="http://www.sdsfie.org/" target="_blank">SDSFIE</a> data standard. <!--more--></p>

<p>So we've applied the technique to another data standard for another Federal organization. In this case, we need to distribute tools to help data modelers work with the platform-independent logical model (PIM) on their own desktops. Typically, this has been centrally managed and accessible via an implementation in SQL Server. (Don't get wrapped around the term "platform-independent." We use it in a different context within this work.) Since we have to distribute to desktops, and SQL Server makes a slew of registry entries, and <a href="http://www.postgresql.org" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> has no licensing issues, we decided to go the PostgreSQL route.</p>

<p>It turns out, this was pretty easy. After doing the work for our approach, I have subsequently found posts showing a similar approach (as always, it depends on the day and the search term), which was nice because they sort of validated what I had already done.</p>

<p>Paul was on the right track with using the Windows binaries from the PostgreSQL site. Natively, PostgreSQL doesn't need any registry entries, which makes sense given that it also runs on Linux and Unix. Registry entries are typically introduced by the one-click installers that do helpful things like setting PostgreSQL up as a service and a few other things that require registry entries on Windows. These are very useful things that I avail myself of when I use PostgreSQL on Windows. In this particular use case, those features were not helpful.</p>

<p>One thing that you'll notice when you use the one-click installer is that you'll end up with a batch file called "pg_env.bat" in the install folder for your version. It looks something like this:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='powershell'><span class='line'><span class="nv">@ECHO</span> <span class="n">OFF</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">REM</span> <span class="n">The</span> <span class="n">script</span> <span class="n">sets</span> <span class="n">environment</span> <span class="n">variables</span> <span class="n">helpful</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">PostgreSQL</span><span class="p">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="p">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="p">&gt;</span><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PATH</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;C:\Program Files (x86)\PostgreSQL\8.4\bin&quot;</span><span class="err">;</span><span class="k">%</span><span class="n">PATH</span><span class="p">%</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGDATA</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">C</span><span class="err">:</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">Program</span> <span class="n">Files</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x86</span><span class="p">)\</span><span class="n">PostgreSQL</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">8</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">4</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">data</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGDATABASE</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">postgres</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGUSER</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">postgres</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGPORT</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">5432</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGLOCALEDIR</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">C</span><span class="err">:</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">Program</span> <span class="n">Files</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x86</span><span class="p">)\</span><span class="n">PostgreSQL</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">8</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">4</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">share</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">locale</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>As you can see, I'm working with version 8.4 of PostgreSQL. That version is what has been blessed but I am also rolling up an implementation of this approach for 9.1 as we expect to get that approval soon.</p>

<p>With this batch file and the unzipped binaries, we have everything we need to run PostgreSQL without running an installer that makes registry entries. Now all we need to do is tell each user to unzip the binaries, edit the batch file to point to the correct paths, open a command window and run the batch file...</p>

<p>...Clearly, there was a little more work to do to make this operate smoothly.</p>

<p>First, we wanted <a href="http://www.postgis.org/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> in our build. As I mentioned before, the PIM represents a logical model that doesn't store actual data, but we wanted it to know about PostGIS data types. Additionally, we wanted to distribute the PIM with PostgreSQL. In this case, we did a little bit of prep work using a standard install of PostgreSQL to add PostGIS (and its template database) and build/populate our PIM database.</p>

<p>Once we had this done, we moved the data directory over to our "unzipped" instance of PostgreSQL. We tested by running our batch file from the command prompt and starting PosgreSQL the same way. In our case, we changed the listening port to 54325. We then attempted to connect via pgAdmin3 and had success:</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-2471" height="274" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/pgpost1.png" title="pgpost1" width="235" /><div style="text-align: center; font-size: 14px">Connection successful!<br /></div></div>


<p>This is all well and good, but probably still a bit much to ask a user to do. So we built an installer. In this case, we used the <a href="http://nsis.sourceforge.net/Main_Page" target="_blank">Nullsoft Scriptable Install System</a> (NSIS) to build our own installer and ensure that no registry entries were made. So once we had our instance/data prepped the way we wanted it, we zipped it all back up for inclusion in the installer. The NSIS script for the installer is at the end of this post.</p>

<p>For the installer to work, we also made use of the <a href="http://nsis.sourceforge.net/ZipDLL_plug-in">ZipDLL plug-in</a> for NSIS. The installer essentially prompts the user to specify the install location then unzips the PostgreSQL binaries/data, builds the driver batch file and places shortcuts on the user's desktop. It's really that simple. We have a utility (also a batch file) that builds the driver batch file as the installer runs. When it's done, the installer cleans up the zip file and the utility. The resulting driver batch file looks like this (where the user specified "C:\Program Files (x86)\PGStandalone11" as the install location):</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='powershell'><span class='line'><span class="n">REM</span> <span class="n">This</span> <span class="n">file</span> <span class="n">was</span> <span class="n">automatically</span> <span class="n">generated</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">REM</span> <span class="n">This</span> <span class="n">script</span> <span class="n">sets</span> <span class="n">environment</span> <span class="n">variables</span> <span class="n">helpful</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">PostgreSQL</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PATH</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;C:\Program Files (x86)\PGStandalone11\bin&quot;</span><span class="err">;</span><span class="k">%</span><span class="n">PATH</span><span class="p">%</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGDATA</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">C</span><span class="err">:</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">Program</span> <span class="n">Files</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x86</span><span class="p">)\</span><span class="n">PGStandalone11</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">data</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGDATABASE</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">postgres</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGUSER</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">postgres</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGPORT</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">54325</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">@SET</span> <span class="n">PGLOCALEDIR</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="n">C</span><span class="err">:</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">Program</span> <span class="n">Files</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x86</span><span class="p">)\</span><span class="n">PGStandalone11</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">share</span><span class="p">\</span><span class="n">locale</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">CALL</span> <span class="s2">&quot;C:\Program Files (x86)\PGStandalone11\bin\postgres.exe&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>We also drop two shortcuts on the desktop:</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2475" height="161" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/pgpost2.png" title="pgpost2" width="316" /></p>

<p>The shortcut labeled "Start PostGIS PIM" executes the batch file above. The shortcut labeled "Manage PostGIS PIM" starts pgAdmin3. I am currently trying to get pgAdmin3 to read the connection information from its settings.ini file instead of looking to the registry. If the user adds the connection on their own, it will write information to the HKCU hive of the registry. This may end up being acceptable but I probably still won't let it go until I solve this problem.</p>

<p>Once we get this completely finalized, I'll make the script and the utilities available. Another reason that I love PostgreSQL is that things like this seem to end up being easier than you would think. That's a sign of a well-built piece of software, in my opinion.</p>

<p>And here's the installer's NSIS script:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
<span class='line-number'>39</span>
<span class='line-number'>40</span>
<span class='line-number'>41</span>
<span class='line-number'>42</span>
<span class='line-number'>43</span>
<span class='line-number'>44</span>
<span class='line-number'>45</span>
<span class='line-number'>46</span>
<span class='line-number'>47</span>
<span class='line-number'>48</span>
<span class='line-number'>49</span>
<span class='line-number'>50</span>
<span class='line-number'>51</span>
<span class='line-number'>52</span>
<span class='line-number'>53</span>
<span class='line-number'>54</span>
<span class='line-number'>55</span>
<span class='line-number'>56</span>
<span class='line-number'>57</span>
<span class='line-number'>58</span>
<span class='line-number'>59</span>
<span class='line-number'>60</span>
<span class='line-number'>61</span>
<span class='line-number'>62</span>
<span class='line-number'>63</span>
<span class='line-number'>64</span>
<span class='line-number'>65</span>
<span class='line-number'>66</span>
<span class='line-number'>67</span>
<span class='line-number'>68</span>
<span class='line-number'>69</span>
<span class='line-number'>70</span>
<span class='line-number'>71</span>
<span class='line-number'>72</span>
<span class='line-number'>73</span>
<span class='line-number'>74</span>
<span class='line-number'>75</span>
<span class='line-number'>76</span>
<span class='line-number'>77</span>
<span class='line-number'>78</span>
<span class='line-number'>79</span>
<span class='line-number'>80</span>
<span class='line-number'>81</span>
<span class='line-number'>82</span>
<span class='line-number'>83</span>
<span class='line-number'>84</span>
<span class='line-number'>85</span>
<span class='line-number'>86</span>
<span class='line-number'>87</span>
<span class='line-number'>88</span>
<span class='line-number'>89</span>
<span class='line-number'>90</span>
<span class='line-number'>91</span>
<span class='line-number'>92</span>
<span class='line-number'>93</span>
<span class='line-number'>94</span>
<span class='line-number'>95</span>
<span class='line-number'>96</span>
<span class='line-number'>97</span>
<span class='line-number'>98</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='text'><span class='line'>!define CO_DIR &quot;Zekiah Technologies&quot;
</span><span class='line'>!define NAME &quot;Standalone PostgreSQL/PostGIS Install for Windows&quot;
</span><span class='line'>!define SHORTNAME &quot;PGStandalone&quot;
</span><span class='line'>!define UNINSTALLER &quot;uninstall.exe&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;OutFile &quot;setup_${SHORTNAME}.exe&quot;
</span><span class='line'>Name &quot;${NAME}&quot;
</span><span class='line'>Caption &quot;${NAME} Setup&quot;
</span><span class='line'>InstallDir &quot;$PROGRAMFILES\${SHORTNAME}&quot;
</span><span class='line'>CompletedText &quot;Success.&quot;
</span><span class='line'>XPStyle &quot;On&quot;
</span><span class='line'>InstallColors /windows&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;Page directory
</span><span class='line'>Page instfiles
</span><span class='line'>ShowInstDetails show&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;Section &quot;Install&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;SetOutPath $INSTDIR
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>; Create uninstaller first, so user can clean up if we barf.
</span><span class='line'>WriteUninstaller &quot;$INSTDIR\${UNINSTALLER}&quot; ;this actually does nothing right now
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>; Extract all the files.
</span><span class='line'>DetailPrint &quot;Extracting files...&quot;
</span><span class='line'>File pg.zip
</span><span class='line'>ZipDLL::extractall &quot;$INSTDIR\pg.zip&quot; &quot;$INSTDIR&quot;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>;Write batch file using INSTDIR to set correct paths
</span><span class='line'>Call WriteBatchFile
</span><span class='line'>DetailPrint &quot;OK: Batch file written&quot;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Call OutputToTemp
</span><span class='line'>GetFullPathName /short $0 $INSTDIR
</span><span class='line'>Delete &quot;$INSTDIR\pg.zip&quot;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>; Add start menu shortcuts.
</span><span class='line'>DetailPrint &quot;Adding shortcuts...&quot;
</span><span class='line'>SetShellVarContext all
</span><span class='line'>CreateDirectory &quot;$SMPROGRAMS\${NAME}&quot;
</span><span class='line'>SetOutPath &quot;$SMPROGRAMS\${NAME}&quot;
</span><span class='line'>CreateShortCut &quot;Uninstall.lnk&quot; &quot;$INSTDIR\${UNINSTALLER}&quot;
</span><span class='line'>CreateShortCut &quot;$DESKTOP\Start PostGIS PIM.lnk&quot; &quot;$INSTDIR\pg_standalone.bat&quot; &quot;&quot;
</span><span class='line'>CreateShortCut &quot;$DESKTOP\Manage PostGIS PIM.lnk&quot; &quot;$INSTDIR\bin\pgAdmin3.exe&quot; &quot;&quot;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>; Success.
</span><span class='line'>DetailPrint &quot;All Done!&quot;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;SectionEnd&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;Function OutputToTemp&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ExpandEnvStrings $5 &quot;%TEMP%&quot;
</span><span class='line'>SetOutPath $5
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;FunctionEnd&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;Function un.OutputToTemp&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ExpandEnvStrings $5 &quot;%TEMP%&quot;
</span><span class='line'>SetOutPath $5
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;FunctionEnd&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;Function WriteBatchFile&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;; execute utility to create batch file to execute PostgreSQL
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Call OutputToTemp
</span><span class='line'>File &quot;utils\make_pg_env.bat&quot;
</span><span class='line'>ExecWait &#39;&quot;$5\make_pg_env.bat&quot; &quot;$INSTDIR&quot;&#39;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;FunctionEnd&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;UninstPage uninstConfirm
</span><span class='line'>UninstPage instfiles
</span><span class='line'>ShowUninstDetails hide&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;Section &quot;Uninstall&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;; Remove all start menu shortcuts.
</span><span class='line'>DetailPrint &quot;Removing shortcuts...&quot;
</span><span class='line'>SetShellVarContext all
</span><span class='line'>Delete &quot;$SMPROGRAMS\${NAME}\*&quot;
</span><span class='line'>RmDir &quot;$SMPROGRAMS\${NAME}&quot;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>DetailPrint &quot;Removing files...&quot;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Delete &quot;$INSTDIR\${UNINSTALLER}&quot;
</span><span class='line'>RmDir &quot;$INSTDIR&quot;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;SectionEnd
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[zigGIS - The End of the Road]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/08/03/ziggis-the-end-of-the-road/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/08/03/ziggis-the-end-of-the-road</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/xanadont">Abe Gillespie</a> made it official today on the zigGIS Google Group: development on <a href="http://pub.obtusesoft.com">zigGIS</a> will cease.  <!--more--></p>

<blockquote>
I've been meaning to make an announcement that zigGIS has officially reached its end-of-life since the next version of ArcGIS should support direct read / write interoperability with PostGIS (thereby rendering zigGIS moot).  I was delaying the announcement because I was hoping we could test PgMap and, if it was any good, suggest it as an alternative during the interim.  But we haven't been able to test it yet.

In any case, PgMap is free, so why not give it a try?  I'm sure the list would appreciate any feedback you could give.
</blockquote>


<p>This is obviously a something of a bittersweet, though expected, development for me. Although <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/09/28/me-and-ziggis/">I ceased my involvement with zigGIS</a> last year, I was still rooting for it. Abe had a lot of cool plans for it but the fact that <a href="http://www.esri.com">ArcGIS</a> will <a href="http://events.esri.com/uc/QandA/index.cfm?fuseaction=Answer&amp;ConferenceID=DD02CFE7-1422-2418-7F271831F47A7A31&amp;QuestionID=3949">natively support direct read/write to its supported spatial databases</a> really renders zigGIS unnecessary. Its primary value at this point would be support for earlier versions of ArcGIS but that's not really enough to justify so much time and effort.</p>

<p><img alt="zigGIS is no more" class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-3109" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/08/ziggis_logo.jpg?w=200" /></p>

<p>In terms of ArcGIS, this is a good development. Direct read/write is a capability that always needed to be there and now it will be. When I first got involved with zigGIS, <a href="http://postgis.refractions.net">PostGIS</a> wasn't supported at all so it made a lot of sense. At the time, I was stuck in a windowless room building a personnel system, so working on zigGIS in the evenings helped be stay connected to the geospatial world. It enabled me to work with Abe and <a href="https://twitter.com/capooti">Paolo Corti</a>; a fact that I will always treasure. Abe put a lot of sweat into zigGIS over its lifetime and I am honored to have helped him in some small way. zigGIS also brought me into contact with phenomenally supportive users, such as <a href="http://www.bostongis.com/blog/">Regina Obe</a> and <a href="http://thesteve0.wordpress.com/">Steven Citron-Pousty</a>, from both of whom I learned a great deal.</p>

<p>Some of the first posts on this blog were about zigGIS. It's hard to believe I've just written my last one.</p>

<p>The PgMap product that Abe mentions can be found <a href="http://st-links.com/default.aspx">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> Later in the same discussion on the zigGIS group, Abe responded to a question about opening the latest version of the code (version 2.x) this way:</p>

<blockquote>
I'm planning on doing just that.  But I didn't want to
announce anything yet because I have very little free time right now
and don't know when I can get to it.
</blockquote>


<p>The full discussion thread is here: <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/ziggis/browse_thread/thread/14ae8a351564de9e">http://groups.google.com/group/ziggis/browse_thread/thread/14ae8a351564de9e</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
