<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Zekiah | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/zekiah/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-27T13:46:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Come Sling Code With Us]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/09/20/come-sling-code-with-us/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T09:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/09/20/come-sling-code-with-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been a pretty good week for us at <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a>. We announced two new <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=press/2013/09/16/zekiah-technologies-inc-wins-marine-corps-logistics-support-services-mclogss-contra">contract</a> <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=press/2013/09/16/zekiah-technologies-inc-awarded-contract-mission-assurance-division">wins</a> and I'm pleased to say that we're not done yet. After final paperwork is done, we should be able to announce a couple more. These are the things that make small-business ownership worthwhile: doing good work, building relationships with our customers and then leveraging our track record to be able to work with new customers. Project execution and business development help us build the foundation necessary to be a good place for our employees to work and we try hard every day to make sure that we are such a place.</p>

<p>The second contract win we announced this week, with the US Navy's Mission Assurance Division in Dahlgren, Virginia, is particularly fulfilling for us because we have worked side-by-side with that organization since the late 1990's, doing challenging work in the areas of infrastructure protection and situational awareness during that time. We have literally grown and evolved alongside them over that time.</p>

<p>I typically try not to mix my blog with the daily operational aspects of my work at Zekiah. Usually, my work comes through in abstracted form in various posts, although many posts actually reflect my own personal experimentation and side projects. I'm stepping outside of that practice today to say that our latest contract win has given us <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=careers/openings/gis-software-developer-ii">an opening for a software developer</a> to come work with us at the Mission Assurance Division.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/desk.jpg" /><div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">Can you bring this workstation to life?</div></div>


<br />




<!--more-->


<p>This is an immediate opening and you would be performing .Net development with the full range of Microsoft and Esri technologies. The work has been challenging and is mission-essential for not only our customer but their sponsors as well. The work would require you to be on-site full time but you would be working with one of the most talented teams of developers, both government and contractor, with which I have ever been associated. This is a group from which I have learned a great deal and still do. This specific position is not for someone who is particularly senior but it is also not entry-level either. It's a great opportunity to grow a career that's underway and picking up steam.</p>

<p>You can get some details by checking out the <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=careers/openings/gis-software-developer-ii">offical job posting</a>, where you can also apply online. Most of that language is pulled directly from the description in the contract. If you want to get an idea of what the day-to-day work looks like, <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/about/">you can always contact me directly</a>. I will draw your attention to one requirement, however: "Active security clearance or the ability to obtain a security clearance." What that means is that we can't entertain staffing via offshoring, nor can we consider applicants who do not hold US citizenship. I bring that up only because everyone's time is valuable and I'd hate for you to waste your time applying if we can't consider you.</p>

<p>So, if you're looking for the next challenge in your career and want to work with a great team, please send us your vitals. Some of the best and most meaningful work I've done in my career was done supporting this customer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using BruTile and MapsUI to Enable WeoGeo Previews]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/21/using-brutile-and-mapsui-to-enable-weogeo-previews/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/21/using-brutile-and-mapsui-to-enable-weogeo-previews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/">my company announced the availability</a> of the first beta version of <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=weogeo">WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS</a>. Unlike the previous version, which opened a separate browser window, this new release allows a user to order a data set from <a href="http://market.weogeo.com">WeoGeo Market</a> or a library from inside ArcMap.</p>

<p>One of the challenges was enabling data set previews. If you browse data sets using the <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">WeoGeo</a> online tool, you can get an idea of what the data set contains by using the data set preview images supplied by the data set provider.</p>

<p>When we developed the first version of WeoGeo Tools for WeoGeo, they used kamap to create preview tiles for data sets. This was accomplished by used either one of two desktop tools: the weoapp (command line) or gWeoApp (GUI). The first version of WeoGeo Tools used the weoapp in the background to create tiles when uploading data. <!--more--></p>

<p>In between the two versions, WeoGeo switched to a ZYX tile structure similar to Google Maps or <a href="http://wiki.osgeo.org/wiki/Tile_Map_Service_Specification">TMS</a> (although not always using spherical mercator). This change made the idea of integrating ordering much easier.</p>

<p>Part of the challenge was implementing support for preview tiles in a manner that provided a smooth user experience inside ArcMap. Luckily, my experience with <a href="http://sharpmap.codeplex.com/">SharpMap</a> pointed the way. It's been a while since I've blogged SharpMap but, in the intervening time, the project added support for map tiles by way of another .Net-based open-source project called <a href="http://brutile.codeplex.com/">BruTile</a>. It was through SharpMap that I was first exposed to BruTile and the two projects have developed something of a symbiotic relationship.</p>

<p>A while back, BruTile branched, with its UI aspects being spun off into another project called <a href="http://mapsui.codeplex.com/">MapsUI</a>. Between these two projects, I had what I needed to added support for WeoGeo previews. I've been building the UI elements of WeoGeo tools using Windows Presentation Foundation (WPF) from the beginning. MapsUI provided exactly what I needed in a simple WPF map control to embed tile support into my application.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/orderwindow.png"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-1574" height="491" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/orderwindow.png" title="Order window showing preview tiles for Maryland census tracts" width="590" /></a><div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px">Order window showing preview tiles for Maryland census tracts<br/></div></div>


<p>Because WeoGeo chose well-known tiling schemes for their previews, most of what I needed was already there. For data sets with preview tiles in spherical mercator, there was already a BruTile schema defined for working with Google Maps that I could leverage. For tiles in WGS84, there was also a schema defined based on the work <a href="http://www.maptiler.org/google-maps-coordinates-tile-bounds-projection/">documented at the MapTiler site</a> (which is the same schema WeoGeo uses for WGS84 tiles).</p>

<p>The primary customization that was required was to create custom request classes that formatted tile request URLs for WeoGeo. To get a tile from WeoGeo, you need to know two pieces of information in addition to the Z, Y and X positions of the tile: you also need to know the data set (identified by a GUID) for which you want tiles and the file format (JPG or PNG) of those tiles. So you end up with a URL that looks like this:</p>

<p><em>http://weodata.weogeo.com/dataset_tiles/{dataset_token}/xyz/{Z}/{Y}/{X}.{format}</em></p>

<p>Beyond the request, you can fine-tune the tile schema by using information from the data set metadata to set the tile extent and remove unused scale levels. For spherical mercator tiles, for example, I defined custom tile source, tile schema and request classes that defined these additional pieces of information. The result was the ability to very easily create a TileLayer for use by the MapsUI control:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}
//_dataSet is deserialized from JSON and contains the data set metadata</p>

<p>//Create schema based on data set format, min and max scaled and tile extent</p>

<pre><code>        var weoSchema = new WeoGeoSchema(_dataSet.TileFileFormat, _dataSet.Scales[0], _dataSet.Scales[_ds.Scales.Count - 1], new BruTile.Extent(_dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.West, _dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.South, _dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.East, _dataSet.Boundaries.Tiles.North));
        var weosource = new WeoGeoTileSource(new WeoGeoRequest("http://weodata.weogeo.com", _dataSet.Token, _dataSet.Scales[0], _dataSet.Scales[_dataSet.Scales.Count - 1], _dataSet.TileFileFormat), weoSchema);
        var tl = new TileLayer(weosource); //the layer to be added to the map control
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Using BruTile, this aspect of adding support for ordering went very quickly and smoothly. I like that they have native WPF UI components as I generally avoid using WinForms anymore when doing Windows desktop development. There's a lot of good work between BruTile and MapsUI and I'll be using these tools more in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I generally try to keep my blog separate from my daily work life in that I usually don't directly blog about the projects on which I am working. I'm going to deviate from that today to make a couple of announcements.</p>

<p>It's been a while now, but you may recall that, about a year ago, <a href="http://www.weogeo.com">WeoGeo</a> <a href="http://blog.weogeo.com/2010/02/16/introducing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/">announced the availability</a> of WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS. It was an <a href="http://www.esri.com/products/index.html#desktop_gis">ArcGIS Desktop</a> extension that integrated the ability browse data sets on WeoGeo Market or hosted libraries as well as providing the ability to upload your data directly from ArcMap.</p>

<p>My first bit of news is that my company, <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah Technologies</a>, produced that extension for WeoGeo. We did not announce it at the time because the original plan was for WeoGeo to support it after it was released. That arrangement has continued to the present.  <!--more--></p>

<p>Shortly before the <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> International User Conference last year, I delivered a preliminary build of an updated version with a better user interface. This was shown in the WeoGeo booth but never officially released, primarily because WeoGeo had a few major changes to their systems and APIs in the offing which would have had a large impact on the extension's code. So we decided to hold off on implementing a new version until after those changes were complete. That leads me to my second announcement.</p>

<p>Zekiah is happy to announce the availability of the first beta release of the new version of WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS. This release improves an existing capability (browsing Market and libraries), adds a new one (the ability customize and create a data order) and temporarily removes a previous capability (uploading data). But don't worry, uploading will be back very soon! WeoGeo introduced a new set of APIs to support uploading (the previous version used their command-line tool behind the scenes) and also implemented a new tiling scheme for preview images so the upload capability requires a complete re-write but will be better. (We also intend to leverage new the ability of <a href="http://www.arc2earth.com">Arc2Earth</a> to generate WeoGeo tile packs so you may want to check that out.)</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/02/weotools10.png"><img alt="" height="314" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2011/02/weotools10.png" title="Browsing WeoGeo Market in ArcGIS Desktop 10" width="590" /></a><div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Browsing WeoGeo Market in ArcGIS Desktop 10<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>This release is an open beta. There are versions for ArcGIS Desktop 9.3 and 10.0 which currently have the same capabilities; but this will change. You can find information about WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS (and download it) here: <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=weogeo">http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=weogeo</a>. From there, you can download the extension and also view the development roadmap. The user manual is draft and will be fleshed out with more detail with each release. When you view the roadmap, you will see that the capabilities between 9.3 and 10.0 will quickly diverge. We plan to integrate the new upload capability with 10.0 but limit 9.3 to browse and download. The final release (scheduled for mid-June) will be the only one that supports 9.3. From that point forward, we will focus solely on 10.0 and beyond. Please feel free to download the version for your platform. We have also established a <a href="http://zekiah.uservoice.com">feedback site</a> for comments.</p>

<p>One of the best parts is that we plan to keep WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS free-of-charge. Of course there are fees associated with ordering data from WeoGeo Market or from having a library subscription but users will be able to install and use the extension throughout their organization without needing to purchase a license.</p>

<p>We are excited about this release for a number of reasons. First, this is the first product that will have a Zekiah "nameplate" so it breaks new ground for us. Second, it strengthens our relationship with WeoGeo, who have been great to work with throughout this process. And, third, this release will put the power of WeoGeo's hosted data infrastructure at the fingertips of analysts working in ArcMap. This release helps streamline the WeoGeo workflow for ArcMap users, allowing them to access their hosted geospatial content without leaving their environment.</p>

<p>I won't be using my blog for announcements in the long term. We are finalizing a new company site and announcements will ultimately come from there. You can also track us on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Zekiah-Technologies-Inc/134576235629?ref=ts">Facebook</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/zekiah">Twitter</a>, and <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/company/109709">LinkedIn</a> for news related to WeoGeo Tools for ArcGIS and Zekiah in general.</p>

<p>Between project work which almost kept me from attending NCGIS and this, there have been a few long nights so I am happy to pass this milestone. There's quite a bit left to be done but it's nice to get this far.</p>

<p>In the coming weeks, I do plan to blog some aspects of building the extension. I've gotten pretty comfortable with some nice technologies like <a href="http://brutile.codeplex.com/">BruTile</a> and am excited to explore them more. Stay tuned...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
