<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Events | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-09T10:03:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JS.GEO 2014 Locked In Solid]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/31/js-dot-geo-2014-locked-in-solid/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-31T16:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2014/07/31/js-dot-geo-2014-locked-in-solid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back, <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/12/27/js-dot-geo-2014-announced/">I posted about about the 2014 edition of JS.GEO</a>. After that post, things got a little fluid, but I'm happy to finally be able to provide an update.</p>

<p>According to JS.GEO Organizer <a href="http://twitter.com/cwhelm">Chris Helm</a>, the event is <a href="https://twitter.com/cwhelm/status/494919297144066048">"locked in solid."</a></p>

<p>The event has a <a href="http://jsgeo.com">web site</a>, a location, and a date. <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/jsgeo-2014-tickets-12450450633">Tickets and sponsorships are available.</a> Agenda is to be announced and they are actively seeking speakers.</p>

<p>The first event was one of those serendipitous things that turned out to be pretty awesome. It was personally very influential on me and changed the focus of a lot of what I was doing with geospatial and with programming. It's probably the best single geospatial event I've attended in the last five years. The fact that FOSS4G will have already drawn a like-minded crowd to Portland should bode well for JS.GEO. My own attendance is still in question due to a number of factors but I highly recommend adding this to your schedule if you can.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JS.Geo 2014 Announced (Maybe)]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/12/27/js-dot-geo-2014-announced/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T08:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/12/27/js-dot-geo-2014-announced</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE (12 March 2014):</strong> The situation with JS.GEO 2014 seems to be a bit fluid and the information originally posted here is no longer accurate. As indicated by Steve Citron-Pousty, the current goal is to have the event occur with <a href="https://2014.foss4g.org">FOSS4G in Portland</a>, though that does not appear to have been finalized. In short, don't book travel yet.</p>

<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/mappingmashups">@mappingmashups</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/smathermather">@smathermather</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/billdollins">@billdollins</a> we are looking to try and combine with Foss4G <a href="https://twitter.com/cwhelm">@cwhelm</a></p>&mdash; TheSteve0 (@TheSteve0) <a href="https://twitter.com/TheSteve0/status/443553754873217024">March 11, 2014</a></blockquote>
<script async src="http://blog.geomusings.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>Information about the follow-up to last year's <a href="http://www.jsgeo.org/">JS.Geo</a> event has been percolating back-channel for a few weeks now. <del>Now some <a href="http://lanyrd.com/2014/jsgeo14/">official details have been posted</a>. This year's event will be held in April in San Francisco</del>. I attended last year's session, really liked the focused format, and got a lot of good information out of it. One thing that was nice was that, regardless of whether you are of an Esri or open-source persuasion in your development preferences, there was a lot of good information presented with a relative lack of hyperbole, which made it easy to focus on the content.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/jsgeo13.png" /></p>

<p>As <a href="http://twitter.com/geo_rube">Todd Barr</a> <a href="http://drunkengeographer.tumblr.com/post/69908102132/when-i-realize-that-no-one-who-plans-gis-spatial">eloquently points out</a>, the April 2014 calender is somewhat crowded with geo-events but, based on last year's event, I'd recommend putting JS.Geo at the top of the list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
