<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SQLite | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/sqlite/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-09T09:57:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite and ArcGIS 10.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/08/07/spatialite-and-arcgis-10-dot-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T12:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/08/07/spatialite-and-arcgis-10-dot-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the release of ArcGIS 10.2, <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> quietly added support for <a href="https://sqlite.org/">SQLite</a> as a geodatabase container. This is big news as the community has been looking for such support for some time. An open-source RDBMS originally designed for embedded systems, SQLite has a very small footprint and is <a href="https://www.sqlite.org/mostdeployed.html">arguably the most widely deployed RDBMS</a> in the world. (Thanks, in part, to the fact that it is embedded into Adobe Reader and other commonly used software.) Over the years numerous strategies for storing spatial data in SQLite have been developed, ranging from simply storing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Well-known_text">WKT or WKB</a> geometries in a column up to full extensions like <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/">SpatiaLite</a>, which adds OGC-compliant data types and methods. SQLite is also the engine that drives the popular <a href="http://www.mapbox.com/developers/mbtiles/">MBTiles</a> implementation used by <a href="http://www.mapbox.com/tilemill/">TileMill</a> and <a href="http://www.mapbox.com">MapBox</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://resources.arcgis.com/en/help/main/10.2/index.html#//019v0000001w000000">According to the documentation</a>, ArcGIS supports the use of either Esri's ST_GEOMETRY or SpatiaLite data types for geometry storage. This is consistent with Esri's approach on other RDBMS platforms such as <a href="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</a> and <a href="http://www.oracle.com">Oracle</a>. While SpatiaLite has been supported by platforms such as <a href="http://qgis.org/">QGIS</a>, I can't say I've seen a huge demand for data in SpatiaLite format. I have been using it for a while in some of <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">my company's</a> data modeling work as we have a Federal customer that has a documented requirement for generation of physical models in SpatiaLite, among other platforms. We have also taken the step of supporting SQLite as a container for our <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim">platform independent model (PIM) approach</a> for configuration management of logical geospatial data models.</p>

<p>Esri's new support of SpatiaLite, combined with my existing customer requirements, obviously sparked my interest so I was curious to kick the tires. Unfortunately, I also had the situation that my development environment for the PIM tools, due to current customer constraints, must remain at ArcGIS 10.1 for both the desktop software and the underlying ArcObjects libraries. I have not been able to carve out the time to build a 10.2 VM.</p>

<p>Luckily, others were also interested in the new SpatiaLite support so <a href="http://twitter.com/brymcbride">Bryan McBride</a>, "<a href="http://twitter.com/fathersandman">Father Sandman</a>," and I were able to crowdsource some very cursory compatibility tests via Twitter. The full tweet stream can be accessed by clicking the date in the tweet below.</p>

<p>{% tweet http://twitter.com/brymcbride/status/365103999671738369 %}</p>

<p>So, using Father Sandman's existing 10.2 install, we were able to verify the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>A SpatiaLite database created in ArcGIS 10.2 can be accessed and viewed in QGIS 1.9.0 and SpatiaLite GUI 1.7.1</li>
<li>A SpatiaLite database created in QGIS 1.9.0 can be accessed in ArcGIS 10.2</li>
</ol>


<p>Obviously, some more rigorous tests need to be performed but the initial results are promising. I'm curious to explore the boundaries, in ArcGIS terms, between a SQLite geodatabase and a file geodatabase. It remains to be seen whether this will put a dent in the use of file geodatabases. If it happens at all, I think it will take time since SQLite is not on the radar of the vast majority of ArcGIS users. I would hope, at a minimum, it puts a final stake through the heart of the personal geodatabase. It could also drive explicit accreditation of SQLite/SpatiaLite tools on government systems, which would be nice.</p>

<p>I'm happy, and somewhat pleasantly surprised, to see Esri take this step and provide another open option for data exchange.</p>

<p>Now, about GeoJSON...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breaking Radio Silence]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/07/breaking-radio-silence/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/06/07/breaking-radio-silence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things have been kind of quiet on the blog lately due to things being busy at work. I call that a good problem to have. Since the beginning of the year, I've written a a lot of proposals for a mixture of potential customers. Interestingly, I'm seeing a lot more call for "GIS Analyst" work. One trend I've noticed, at least in the Federal sector, is that the time between proposal due dates and award announcements seems to be lengthening. That may be an indication of the ongoing flux in funding and organizations try to figure out how to fund their requirements. It will be interesting to see how it shakes out. Of course, it's good that the opportunities are there in the first place.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/microphone.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2664" height="413" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/microphone.jpg" title="microphone" width="413" /></a></p>

<p>One the technical side of things, I've been involved in a smattering of things that's made it hard to roll up one good post. I'm pretty heavily involved in the PIM efforts that my colleague, Barry Schimpf, <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=blog/topics/pim" target="_blank">has been blogging about</a> over on the <a href="http://www.zekiah.com" target="_blank">Zekiah</a> blog. <!--more--> Historically, the PIM data structures have been housed in Microsoft SQL Server, but we've been working on porting it to other platforms to provide options to end users. We've done an initial port to <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> but we've been spending most of our time on a <a href="http://www.sqlite.org/" target="_blank">SQLite</a>/<a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> version. This has taken two forms. First is the port of the PIM structure itself to SQLite to make it easier to provide some of the PIM services such as profiling, version-to-version migrations, dataset generation, and validation in remote, field-based settings. Second is the generation/validation of physical implementations in SpatiaLite. This is being done for a customer who is expecting to do field data collection using SpatiaLite and these services will be helpful in enhancing data quality at the point of collection. Additionally, the SpatiaLite aspect of this work has had me living within <a href="http://qgis.org/" target="_blank">QGIS</a> lately.</p>

<p>Another thing I've been experimenting with is the use of <a href="http://nodejs.org/" target="_blank">Node.js</a> for real-time data processing. Our long-standing work in the situational awareness realm has had us working with real-time data feeds for a long time. I'm interested in the possibility of using Node to tackle some of the feed collection tasks. I've used an event-driven approach for such tasks in the past so that aspect of Node is quite familiar to me but the use of Javascript, its ease of deployment and potential scalability are intriguing to me. I'm coming late to the party with Node, primarily due to my rustiness with Javascript, but I'm liking what I'm seeing so far.</p>

<p>Beyond those major things, I've had the opportunity to start working with <a href="http://postgis.org/" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> 2.0 and play more with <a href="http://leaflet.cloudmade.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a> and <a href="http://mapbox.com/" target="_blank">MapBox</a>. On the development side of things, these efforts have had be jumping back and forth a lot between C#, Javascript and a little bit of Python, as well as between Windows and Linux, depending on the task.</p>

<p>You'll notice that I didn't mention any <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> tools. That's primarily because recent demand from my customers has led me to a different tool set. I expect that to level out somewhat in the near future since many of the outstanding proposals I mentioned have a strong Esri flavor. As always, having a broad toolbox can be an asset in consulting. I'll be skipping San Diego again this year. I'm finding that Esri's Federal Conference in DC is of such increasing quality each year that it fulfills my needs for Esri-related information. That's really okay with me because I'd rather spend as much of the summer with my family as possible. So it's not so much a down-vote of Esri as my taking advantage of options that fit into my life better.</p>

<p>I hope to be able blog in more detail about some of these efforts as I get farther along with them. Times like this make it exciting to work in the geospatial field. There's a lot of churn in the market right now with regard to tools and technologies. I'm not sure I can perceive any meaningful gap between the capabilities of open-source and proprietary geospatial tools anymore. As a result, there are a lot of options to choose from for building robust systems and applications. It looks to be a fun summer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
