<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open source | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/open-source/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-01T17:38:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Checking out the GDAL/OGR Plugin for ArcGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/22/checking-out-the-gdal-slash-ogr-plugin-for-arcgis/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-22T13:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/22/checking-out-the-gdal-slash-ogr-plugin-for-arcgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back, I <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/18/still-jonesing-for-ziggis-try-this-ogr-plug-in-for-arcgis/">blogged</a> the availability of a <a href="http://www.gdal.org/">GDAL/OGR</a> <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/">plug-in for ArcGIS</a> desktop by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=14926439&amp;locale=en_US">Ragi Burhum at AmigoCloud</a>. At the time, I was hoping to dig into it fairly quickly but that didn't happen and I'm finally getting to it. Anyone who has followed this blog for a while knows that I have had <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2006/12/17/postgis-and-arcgis-9.1/">more</a> than a <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2007/07/10/consuming-georss-in-arcmap-with-inmemoryworkspacefactory/">passing</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/10/03/cutting-tiles-for-arcgis-server-using-tilemill/">interest</a> in <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/02/importing-data-from-geocommons-into-arcmap/">integrating</a> new <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/03/02/announcing-weogeo-tools-for-arcgis/">data</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/08/24/togeojson-and-towkt-for-the-esri-fgdb-api/">sources</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/08/09/taking-a-look-at-pgmap/">with</a> <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2011/11/15/fgeojson/">ArcGIS</a> over the years. This comes from the fact that, as a technology geek, I am fascinated by all forms of technology and enjoy the process of integration and, as a consultant providing services to the Federal Government, most of my customers have standardized on Esri tools. Integrations such as GeoRSS, PostGIS, GeoCommons and GeoJSON have directly benefitted my customers for real-world applications so I continue look for ways to remove the barriers between them and the data they seek.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://images-mediawiki-sites.thefullwiki.org/07/3/6/0/1583563936968042.png" /></div>




<!--more-->


<p>The GDAL/OGR plug-in caught my attention because it purports to add support for any format supported by GDAL and OGR, similar to the way <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a> leverages them for a wide variety of format support. To get going with it, I downloaded the source and built it in Visual Studio 2010. I only ran into a couple of minor issues. First, a had previously installed the Windows build of OGR on my machine using the <a href="http://www.gisinternals.com/sdk/PackageList.aspx?file=release-1600-gdal-1-9-2-mapserver-6-2-0.zip">distribution from GIS Internals</a>. The project as it came down from GitHub couldn't find the OGR and OSR bindings for C#, so I had to resolve that trivial issue. Next, the plug-in was built for use in ArcGIS 10.1 but I was using 10.0. Because some new interfaces were introduced, the <a href="https://github.com/RBURHUM/arcgis-ogr/blob/master/src/OGRPlugin/OGRPlugin/ogrplugin_utils.cs">current code</a> contains a declaration of  type ISpatialReferenceFactory4, which is a 10.1 interface. I needed to change that to ISpatialReferenceFactory3 to make it work with 10.0. That has been the only change I have needed to make so far to account for the version differences. I plan to add a compiler directive in my fork of the project to account for that and submit it back once I can test it.</p>

<p>As I said before, I previously had installed GDAL/OGR so it was already on my machine and my GDAL_DATA environment variable was set. When I built the plug-in and attempted to use it in ArcMap, it threw an error when I tried adding a GeoJSON layer (also with SpatiaLite) that it could not find my gcs.csv file, which is in my GDAL_DATA location. With a little investigation, I found that the code was resetting that variable at runtime to point to the location of the plug-in binary. I copied the files there and it worked well from then on. I'll probably try to add a way to check for the existence of that variable before setting it. None of these issues were major and I think they were reasonable design choices up front so I am not concerned by them.</p>

<p>At that point, I was able to quickly add GeoJSON and SpatiaLite layers to my data frame in ArcMap. This is pretty exciting to me since the ability to support a wide range of data types was a long-standing goal of zigGIS and I'm glad that Ragi has conquered that with this work.</p>

<p>Because the layers are added using a plug-in workspace, they are full read-only citizens inside ArcGIS. For example, I was able to wire up a couple of models using ModelBuilder and execute clips (clipping a GeoJSON layer with a SpatiaLite layer) and buffers and simple tests. I'm really not a huge ModelBuilder user but I thought it would be a good way to test things out.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;">
<img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/buffer.png" />
<div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Model to test a simple buffer<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>The model above produced a 50-foot buffer around Amtrak rail lines from NTAD 2012 in GeoJSON format. The resultant buffer was written to a file geodatabase. As you can see from the image below, it worked like a charm.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;">
<img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/buffer_result_small.png" />
<div style="text-align:center;font-size: 14px;">Results of the buffer model.<br/><br/></div></div>


<p>I achieved similar success with a clip operation so I'm sufficiently confident in trying to package the plug-in up and put it in the hands of some of the analysts with whom I work. All-in-all, the plug-in is a nice piece of work. It's still not fully baked but it's a very solid start and deserves a closer look if you're looking to expand the reach of your ArcGIS investment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite 4.1.0 Beta Preview Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/03/spatialite-4-dot-1-0-beta-available/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T08:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/03/spatialite-4-dot-1-0-beta-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/spatialite-users">SpatiaLite Google Group</a> this morning, Sandro Furieri announced the availability of a beta preview of SpatiaLite 4.1.0. The primary focus of this preview is to get early comment on new capabilities supporting the storage, validation, and query of XML documents.</p>

<p>More information about this update <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=XmlBlob+and+VirtualXPath">can be found here</a>. Says Sandro:</p>

<blockquote>
The main goals of these recently introduced enhancements are:<br/>
- storing XML Documents directly within the DBMS <br/>
- supporting XML validation<br/>
- supporting plain SQL queries on behalf of XML Documents <br/>
  via canonical XPath expressions<br/>
<br/>
Implementing directly into the Spatial DBMS a common core of 
XML-oriented features surely is an interesting and useful option,
just considering that ISO- and INSPIRE-Metadata or SLD/SE Styles 
are fully based on XML.
</blockquote>


<p>Although I find myself working more with <a href="http://geojson.org">GeoJSON</a> and <a href="http://developmentseed.org/blog/2011/feb/09/introducing-carto-css-map-styling-language/">CartoCSS</a> these days, I think support for XML is a good step for SpatiaLite. There are some very mature use cases based on XML, as Sandro points out. While <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/sld">SLD</a> is not my favorite, this may keep it on my radar. Also, it would be interesting to see how this new capability would possibly affect the evolution of the <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/projects/groups/geopackageswg">OGC GeoPackage draft specification</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite for Android Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-for-android-available/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-for-android-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On what seems to be turning into <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> Monday, Sandro Furieri also announced on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/spatialite-users?pli=1" target="_blank">SpatiaLite Google Group</a> the availability of a stable version of SpatiaLite for Android.</p>

<p>I am happy to see that this version was developed and contributed back by the <a href="http://www.agc.army.mil/" target="_blank">US Army Geospatial Center</a>. The fact that they contributed back to the project under a standard open-source license is a nice step from a DoD organization.</p>

<p>The message is quoted below:</p>

<blockquote>
Hi List,

I'm really proud to announce you all that finally a rock solid stable and really easy-to-be-deployed binary porting of SpatiaLite for the Android platform is now available for download [1].

[1] <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=splite-android" target="_blank">https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=splite-android</a>

Many thanks to the U.S. Army Geospatial Center [2] who very generously contributed this highly appreciated and really useful resource under a genuine free software license (LGPLv3).

[2] <a href="http://www.agc.army.mil/" target="_blank">http://www.agc.army.mil/</a>

A detailed tutorial [3] explaining how-to deploy and use SpatiaLite on Android platforms has been kindly contributed by Andrea Antonello, who spent many long hours during the last week while performing a thorough testing of SpatiaLite-Android, then deciding to publicly share his experiences with the SpatiaLite community. Feel absolutely free to pay a beer to Andrea; he'll surely appreciate ;-)

[3] <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=spatialite-android-tutorial" target="_blank">https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=spatialite-android-tutorial</a>

enjoy, Sandro
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite 4.0 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-4-0-released/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-4-0-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It looks like it was a busy weekend for Sandro Furieri and the rest of the <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/index" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> team as version 4.0 was announced on Sunday. There are a number of changes, so it's best to <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=switching-to-4.0" target="_blank">catch up on them</a> before switching over.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.manningltg.com/fixture_show.php?f_id=GCQ-164&amp;f_desc=Spatialite%20(Quartz%20Halogen)"><img alt="" height="300" src="http://www.manningltg.com/product_imgs/web/GCQ-164_1.jpg" title="Not this SpatiaLite" width="490" /></a><div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">Not this SpatiaLite</div></div>


<p>I have a couple of Federal customers that are integrating SpatiaLite into their workflows so I'll need to take a day or so to assess impacts any impacts there. Looks like the perfect way to slide back into work after a long weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Geospatial Workflows]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/09/personal-geospatial-workflows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've had a couple of people ask me recently about the geospatial tools I use. Year-over-year, that answer changes but here's how I answer that right now:</p>

<p>As a Federal contractor, I spend a lot of time working with the <a href="http://www.esri.com" target="_blank">Esri</a> stack during my work day. A few years ago, I added a few open-source geospatial tools into my tool set and, since then, have also done a respectable amount to consulting work them as well. The balance between the two varies over time, depending on the requirements of individual customers and projects. Lately, commercial customers have seemed much more interested in open-source tools while my government customers are sticking with Esri. Since those observations are based on the the extremely heavy filter of my own recent experience, I'd be hesitant to draw any larger conclusions from them.</p>

<p><img alt="" height="264" src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/duct-tape.jpg" title="Duct Tape" width="300" /></p>

<p>I've always believed that proficiency with a wide range of tools makes me a better consultant and integrator, so I am always exploring and trying new things. With those commercial customers, and in my own personal side projects, my recent workflows have gelled around a core set of tools, both commercial and open-source: <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> - I am very comfortable with SQL and tend to use <a href="http://www.postgresql.org" target="_blank">PostgreSQL</a> and PostGIS for a lot of my vector data processing. Lately, this has mainly involved joining up geometries with attributes and doing aggregations and similar things. For example, the vector data in this <a href="http://geobabbler.github.com/mdq62012.html" target="_blank">map of the county-level Maryland Question 6 results</a> was processed in PostGIS. Very simply, I have a baseline table of the counties of Maryland which I will use to create new data sets. In this case, I imported a CSV of the election results, created a view that joined up the data and then selected the view into a new table. This is workflow is much easier with PostGIS 2.x thanks to the <a href="http://blog.opengeo.org/2012/03/06/postgis-2-0-new-features-typmod/" target="_blank">use of typmod</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://qgis.org" target="_blank">QGIS</a> - In the case of the map mentioned above, the data set is ultimately going to be static so it makes sense to serve it as static content, rather than bringing a heavyweight geospatial server such as <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgisserver/" target="_blank">ArcGIS</a> or <a href="http://geoserver.org/display/GEOS/Welcome" target="_blank">GeoServer</a> into the mix. In these cases, I lean toward <a href="http://geojson.org/" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>. QGIS makes it very easy to export any vector layer out to GeoJSON so it's become my go-to tool for that. QGIS also has great analytical tools and I consider it a complete functional match for ArcMap but, having said that, I'm actually very comfortable with the spatial SQL functions in PostGIS so I end up doing most of my analytical work there.</p>

<p><a href="http://leafletjs.com/" target="_blank">Leaflet</a>/<a href="http://www.openlayers.org/" target="_blank">OpenLayers</a> - Most of the web maps I'm doing are single-use and pretty straightforward. When that's the case, I prefer to use Leaflet as it's a pretty lightweight library. That said, I keep OpenLayers in the mix if the GIS-like requirements get a little more complex. OpenLayers does more "out of the box" than Leaflet but Leaflet is trimmer so it really depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.arc2earth.com/" target="_blank">Arc2Earth</a>/<a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/" target="_blank">TileMill </a>- Arc2Earth is a commercial extension to ArcGIS and I lean on it to make tiles, although it does a lot more than that. I also use TileMill for this purpose but it really depends on where my cartography resides. There's a lot of good cartography locked up in MXDs and Arc2Earth is just a great way to capitalize on that. It's also nice that Arc2Earth works in ArcMap, eliminating the need for a license of Server.  If I'm building my cartography from scratch, which is not really my strong suit, I'll lean toward TileMill because it more easily connects directly to PostGIS, which is where my data tends to reside if I have my druthers. Again, it depends on the use case.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.python.org/" target="_blank">Python</a>/Javascript - I'm doing a lot more work in Python these days. It's become the <em>lingua franca</em> of GIS development in my book. Additionally, the capabilities of Javascript for web maps is evolving at a stunning pace. I can't see being productive in the long term in the geospatial field without proficiency in these two languages.</p>

<p>So these are the tools that I'm using most often these days as part of my personal workflows. The stable of tools that I use evolves over time, as should be evident if you peruse this blog. In general, I'm finding it very easy to be productive with these tools right now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
