<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: arcobjects | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/arcobjects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-26T15:36:36-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[zigGIS Hotfix Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/18/ziggis-hotfix-available/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/18/ziggis-hotfix-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Abe announced the availability of hotfix 3 for <a href="http://pub.obtusesoft.com">zigGIS</a> 2.0.5. From the announcement:</p>

<blockquote>Hotfix 3 fixes an issue that prevented point layers from being
editable; it also includes all prior hotfixes.  The hotfix is a free
upgrade and is highly recommended for all users.  Please go to
<a href="http://pub.obtusesoft.com">http://pub.obtusesoft.com</a> &gt; My Order.  After logging in you'll see a
link to the patch.</blockquote>


<p><a href="http://abegillespie.blogspot.com">Abe</a> is working hard on <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/04/23/ziggis-3-0-to-be-open-source/">version 3.0</a> but obviously is continuing to support 2.x as well. Improvements include a new provider model which will better enable support for other data sources. A roadmap should be available soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Couple of Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/15/a-couple-of-updates/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/15/a-couple-of-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Shortly after my <a href="http://geobabble.wordpress.com/2010/06/02/importing-data-from-geocommons-into-arcmap/">previous post</a>, about browsing and downloading data from <a href="http://www.geocommons.com">GeoCommons</a>, hit the wires, I got quite a few back-channel requests for the code. I sent it out via e-mail to a number of people and then posted it via DropBox. I have finally gotten around to posting it up on Google Code, making things much more manageable. It is now available <a href="http://code.google.com/p/geocommonsbrowser/">here</a>.</p>

<p>I have made a few updates since the original post. Some were administrative but were functional. They are:</p>

<ol>
<li>The code was updated to replace SharpZipLib with <a href="http://dotnetzip.codeplex.com">DotNetZip</a> for handling zip files.</li>
<li>The code now attempts to identify the default KML handler on the user's system and pass KML directly to it for previewing.</li>
<li>The user now gets a wait cursor when the tool is processing downloads and such. This should make it a little more usable.</li>
<li>The code headers had been pasted in from <a href="http://sharpmap.codeplex.com">SharpMap</a> and I missed some references to SharpMap in the text. Those have been corrected.</li>
</ol>


<p>Anyway, thanks for all the interest. It sort of caught me off guard but at least the code is more accessible now. I've got a few more updates planned so this should streamline things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importing Data From GeoCommons Into ArcMap]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/02/importing-data-from-geocommons-into-arcmap/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/06/02/importing-data-from-geocommons-into-arcmap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> <em>The code for this post is available at the bottom of the page.</em></p>

<p>I have been doing a lot of development with the <a href="http://resources.esri.com/arcgisserver/apis/silverlight/">ESRI Silverlight API</a> recently. One of the requirements of my project is to be able to dynamically add KML data at runtime. The incorporation of <a href="http://code.google.com/apis/kml/documentation/">KML</a> was handled for us through <a href="http://resources.esri.com/arcgisserver/apis/silverlight/index.cfm?fa=codeGalleryDetails&amp;scriptID=16487">one of the ESRI samples</a> on the resource center so we pretty much just had to integrate that code and test against our use cases. For testing, I typically reached out to <a href="http://www.geocommons.com">GeoCommons</a> since any data set available there can be streamed as KML.</p>

<p>Obviously, this is not my first exposure to GeoCommons but, when discussing it, I found that many of the analysts I spoke with were not aware of it and did not use it much. So I decided to tackle developing a simple ArcMap extension to allow a user to search GeoCommons and then download/add data to ArcMap without the need to manually download, unzip and add the data themselves.<!--more--></p>

<p>GeoCommons, and the GeoIQ platform on which it is based, are produced by <a href="http://www.fortiusone.com/">FortiusOne</a> and are comprised, broadly speaking, of two main components: Finder and Maker. Finder allows you to search/browse data on GeoCommons while Maker allows you to visualize/map the data online and produce map products with nothing but a browser required. That's a gross oversimplification of what GeoCommons can do so I recommend that you kick the tires yourself if you haven't already done so.</p>

<p>Finder supports <a href="http://www.opensearch.org/Home">OpenSearch</a> (see more about this <a href="http://blog.fortiusone.com/2010/01/05/better-know-a-geocommons-feature-opensearch/">here</a>) so the basic search syntax is simple and RESTful. Results can be returned in a number of formats such as JSON, KML and Atom. For example, a query using the search term "oil" and returning results as Atom would simply be:</p>

<p><a href="http://finder.geocommons.com/search.atom?query=oil">http://finder.geocommons.com/search.atom?query=oil</a></p>

<p>We can further refine my query by added parameters such as "limit" to restrict the number of results returned (this can be a very good thing as there's quite a bit of data on GeoCommons) and "bbox", which can used to restrict your search to a specific geographic area. Once you have the search results, you can easily get at the actual data in a number of formats, KML and shapefile (zipped) for example. You specify the format in a RESTful manner by simply changing the URI. The following links point to Maryland zip code boundaries in KML and shapefile formats, respectively:</p>

<p><a href="http://finder.geocommons.com/overlays/22026.kml">http://finder.geocommons.com/overlays/22026.kml</a>
<a href="http://finder.geocommons.com/overlays/22026.zip">http://finder.geocommons.com/overlays/22026.zip</a></p>

<p>So what all of this boils down to is that Finder has a simple search syntax, returns results in a well-known format, and delivers data sets in standard formats. Integrating this into ArcMap should be fairly easy. I started by designing a simple search dialog:</p>

<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-932" height="374" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/06/geocommons_form.png" title="A simple GeoCommons query dialog" width="419" /></p>

<p>This post is not intended to be a lesson on how to extend ArcMap so I'll describe the basic components at a high level. I used C# to develop the project and the dialog is built using regular Windows Forms rather than WPF. It uses version 3.5 of the .Net framework. There is a simple toolbar button that creates an instance of the form and passes in a reference to the ArcMap application so that the form can get access to information such as the current extent as needed.</p>

<p>The workflow is fairly simple. Enter a "search term" in the text box (exactly as you would in the Finder web interface), select a "limit" (default is 20) and then click "execute" to run your search. The following is the code behind the "execute" button:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}</p>

<pre><code>        IEnvelope bounds = this._mxd.ActiveView.Extent; //current map extent
        bounds.Project(this.getWGS84()); //convert to WGS84 for use in query
        ExecuteSearch(this.txtKeyword.Text, Convert.ToInt32(this.comboBox1.SelectedItem.ToString()), bounds.YMax, bounds.YMin, bounds.XMax, bounds.XMin);
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>And the ExecuteSearch method that does the work:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}</p>

<pre><code>        WebClient request = new WebClient();
        string url = String.Format("http://finder.geocommons.com/search.atom?query={0}&amp;amp;limit={1}&amp;amp;bbox={2},{3},{4},{5}", term, limit.ToString(), west, south, east, north); //format the URI
        request.DownloadStringCompleted += new DownloadStringCompletedEventHandler(request_DownloadStringCompleted); //attach handler for async call
        request.DownloadStringAsync(new Uri(url)); 
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>These two pieces of code format the URI and make the call to the GeoCommons API. As you can see, it automatically uses the current map extent to bound the query. GeoCommons expects the bounding box to be in WGS84 so I convert the extent before building the URI. The "getWGS84" method is an ArcObjects helper function that I wrote years ago and reuse extensively.</p>

<p>The next part of the workflow is to parse the search results and display them in the "results" list box. To support that, I created the following (very simple) class:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}</p>

<pre><code>public class OverlayInfo
{
    public string title { get; set; }
    public string shapelink { get; set; }
    public string kmllink { get; set; }
    public string infolink { get; set; }
}
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Basically, I'll create an instance of OverlayInfo for each search result and add it to the results list, using the "title" property as the display member. I could have set up a data contract to bind these directly to the atom entries (and I may still do that) but, for the limited information I am handling at the moment, it was simpler to parse the atom using LINQ to XML. That work is done in the DownloadStringCompleted event handler here:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}</p>

<pre><code>        if (e.Error == null)
        {
            this.lstResults.Items.Clear();
            string s = e.Result;
            XElement root = XElement.Parse(s);
            string n = root.Name.LocalName;
            XNamespace atom = "http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom";
            IEnumerable&amp;lt;XElement&amp;gt; entries = root.Elements(atom + "entry"); //get the entry elements
            foreach (XElement entry in entries)
            {
                XElement title = entry.Elements(atom + "title").First(); //query the entry title
                IEnumerable&amp;lt;XElement&amp;gt; links =
                (from el in entry.Elements(atom + "link")
                 where (string)el.Attribute("type") == "application/vnd.google-earth.kml+xml"
                 select el).Take(1); //query the link to the KML resource

                XElement link = null;
                if (links.Count() &amp;gt; 0)
                {
                    link = links.First();
                }
                if (link != null)
                {
                    string kml = links.Attributes("href").First().Value;
                    string shp = kml.Replace("kml", "zip"); //coerce to zip (shapefile) link
                    string info = kml.Replace(".kml", ""); //coerce to general information link
                    OverlayInfo overlay = new OverlayInfo { title = title.Value, shapelink = shp, kmllink = kml, infolink = info }; //create instance of OverlayInfo
                    this.lstResults.Items.Add(overlay);
                }
            }
        }
        else
        {
            MessageBox.Show(e.Error.ToString());
        }
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>I use LINQ to query the entries out of the feed, iterate them, create an instance of OverlayInfo for each entry and add it to the list box. LINQ is nice for data structures that are known at runtime and I like it better than XPath for querying XML documents (although it's touchier about namespaces).</p>

<p>With that, the user now sees a list of search results. It's time to do something with them. For this pass, they can preview the KML for a selected result or they can download the shapefile data for it. The KML preview simply provides a means to look at the data before getting it.</p>

<p>You will recall that we attached the links to the KML and shapefile data to the OverlayInfo object for each result when we added it to the list so working with it is as simple as this:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}</p>

<pre><code>        OverlayInfo overlay = this.lstResults.SelectedItem as OverlayInfo;
        System.Diagnostics.Process.Start(overlay.kmllink);
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>For this pass, the code simply does a shell execute using the KML link so what this actually does is cause the link to be opened in the default browser which should then prompt you to open the data in Google Earth (or whatever your default KML handler is). In the near future, I will update this to go to GE directly but this worked for now.</p>

<p>The "download" button actually downloads the data and adds it to ArcMap automatically. Handling this is a little more complicated because GeoCommons delivers the shapefile data in a zip file so it needs to be uncompressed first. For handling zip files, I used the open-source <a href="http://dotnetzip.codeplex.com/">DotNetZip</a> to handle the zip files. Here's the bulk of the heavy lifting for handling the shapefiles:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}</p>

<pre><code>    private void download_Click(object sender, EventArgs e)
    {
        //TODO: move all of this out of the event handler
        string tmp = System.IO.Path.GetTempPath(); //find user's temp folder
        OverlayInfo overlay = this.lstResults.SelectedItem as OverlayInfo;
        string file = System.IO.Path.GetFileName(overlay.shapelink);
        //build all of the necessary file info
        string filebase = file.ToLower().Replace(".zip", "");
        string outfolder = tmp + filebase; //output location
        System.IO.Directory.CreateDirectory(outfolder);
        string outpath = tmp + filebase + "\\" + file;
        //download the data
        WebRequest req = WebRequest.Create(overlay.shapelink);
        WebResponse resp = req.GetResponse();
        Stream strm = resp.GetResponseStream();
        SaveStreamToFile(outpath, strm);
        //unzip the data, getting the name of the .shp file
        string shapefile = Utils.ExtractFiles(outpath, outfolder, false); 
        resp.Close();
        //there may have been an error or no actual shapefile
        if (shapefile != "")
        {
            string workspace = System.IO.Path.GetDirectoryName(shapefile);
            string dataset = System.IO.Path.GetFileName(shapefile);
            dataset = dataset.ToLower().Replace(".shp", "");
            AddShapefile(workspace, dataset, overlay.title);
        }

    }

    private void SaveStreamToFile(string fileFullPath, Stream stream)
    {
        try
        {
            using(Stream fs = File.Open(fileFullPath, FileMode.Create) )
            {
                byte []buf = new byte[1000];
                int iRead = 0;
                do
                {
                    iRead = stream.Read(buf, 0, buf.Length);
                    if (iRead &amp;gt; 0)
                        fs.Write(buf, 0, iRead);
                } while (iRead &amp;gt; 0);
            }                
        }
        catch (Exception ex)
        {
            //TODO: examine and throw
            MessageBox.Show(ex.ToString());
        }
    }

    private void AddShapefile(string folder, string dataset, string description)
    {
        try
        {
            IWorkspaceFactory wkspcfact = new ShapefileWorkspaceFactoryClass() as IWorkspaceFactory;
            //System.IO.Path.
            IFeatureWorkspace wkspc = wkspcfact.OpenFromFile(folder, 0) as IFeatureWorkspace;
            IFeatureLayer lyr = new FeatureLayerClass() as IFeatureLayer;
            IFeatureClass fc = wkspc.OpenFeatureClass(dataset);
            IGeoDataset gds = fc as IGeoDataset;
            IGeoDatasetSchemaEdit edit = gds as IGeoDatasetSchemaEdit;
            if (edit.CanAlterSpatialReference)
            {
                //GeoCommons does not deliver a .prj file with
                //shapefiles. This sets the spatial reference
                edit.AlterSpatialReference(this.getWGS84());
            }
            lyr.FeatureClass = fc;
            lyr.Name = description;
            lyr.SpatialReference = this.getWGS84();
            _mxd.FocusMap.AddLayer(lyr); //_mxd is the current document open in ArcMap
        }
        catch (Exception ex)
        {
            //TODO: put in better user notification
            MessageBox.Show(ex.ToString());
        }
    }
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Below is a screen capture of all of this in action (click to enlarge). I zoomed into the Gulf of Mexico region and searched on the term "oil." As can be seen I selected the "Projected Oil Trajectory - Forecast 052610" data set and added it to ArcMap. I manually applied the color ramp after the download.</p>

<p><a href="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/06/geocommons_example.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-934" height="178" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2010/06/geocommons_example.png?w=300" title="GeoCommons/ArcMap example" width="300" /></a></p>

<p>I was able to turn this around pretty quickly (less than a day) due to two main facts: 1) GeoCommons is well-designed and makes strong use of web standards and open interfaces to expose data in very well-known formats and 2) ArcGIS is, as it has always been, a very extensible platform. If it doesn't support a data source that you want to use, you can probably make it do so (although not always as easily as this example). <del datetime="2010-06-02T22:05:16+00:00">I plan on tidying up the code a bit more and making it available here so keep checking back.</del></p>

<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> The code for this post is available <a href="http://code.google.com/p/geocommonsbrowser/">here</a>. It includes the source code and the Visual Studio 2008 solution as well as the binary for those of you who are not programmers. It has only been run/tested against ArcGIS Desktop 9.3.1 SP1.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Thoughts on ArcGIS 10.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/01/13/first-thoughts-on-arcgis-100/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2010/01/13/first-thoughts-on-arcgis-100</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.esri.com/news/podcasts/audio/speaker/dangermond_arcgis10.mp3">announcement</a> that ArcGIS 9.4 is being re-christened as 10.0 leaves me feeling somewhat bemused. I have seen the new version of Desktop and it is nice and will finally update the current Office-97-feeling UI. The <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/whats-new/whats-coming.html">list of changes coming in 10.0</a> (published so far) is impressive but I haven?t seen any discussion of the changes coming to the ArcGIS architecture, which is of greater interest to me as a developer and integrator. Given the past history of ArcGIS, calling this release 10.0, in my mind, implies a significant architectural shift. ArcGIS 8 was a clear departure from the previous releases of ARC/INFO. Indeed, it not only came with a new version but introduced the name ?ArcGIS.?<!--more--></p>

<p>ArcGIS 9 represented a less-radical, but significant architectural update. By restructuring the underlying ArcObjects components of ArcGIS, ESRI enabled the introduction of ArcGIS Server and ArcGIS Engine and began to unify their desktop, web and mobile offerings. ArcGIS 8 would not have been able to support this.</p>

<p>Quite frankly, I think the current ArcGIS architecture has just about run its course. I think it is time to recognize that desktop, web and mobile applications are each different and need to be built differently. The current reliance on a common pool of ArcObjects, while not necessarily a bad thing for the desktop platform, is a hindrance for ArcGIS Server. To be specific, I am talking about COM here.</p>

<p>ArcGIS Server would benefit greatly from breaking its dependency on COM. I would not complain if I never had to do <a href="http://blog.davebouwman.com/index.php/2009/12/zen-and-the-art-of-serverobjectextensions/">this kind of stuff</a> anymore. This would, of course, mean replacing the capability for extending ArcGIS Server using ArcObjects with a similar capability. It would also mean choosing what to replace it with: .Net?...Java?...ROR?...something else? I think recent efforts with the REST API and its client technologies (JSAPI, Flex API, Silverlight API) speak to a way ahead. I can now pick a native approach and build ArcGIS solutions with less COM than ever before and ArcGIS Server itself is abstracted from the client code enough that replacing the technology that drives it can be relatively transparent. My hope is that these APIs continue to evolve and become more robust and are, perhaps, augmented by a server-side API to enable the development of advanced custom tools without the use of COM.</p>

<p>While ArcGIS Server is far from perfect, it does provide one of the better (quasi)REST APIs available and a consistent way to expose geo-processing and analysis in web applications. I think an official realization that Server is different and a commitment to re-engineer it top to bottom will benefit it in the long run. So the announcement of 10.0 now begs the question ?What is the roadmap for the 10.x series?? I haven?t seen anything yet that indicates 10.0 will introduce such changes but, perhaps, it could be setting the stage for them. ArcGIS 9.0 was released in May 2004. By the time of the scheduled release of 10.0, we will have been working with 9.x for six years. The 8.x series lasted about three and a half years. Given that we could be looking at a few years of 10.x, I?d be interested in knowing more about the underpinnings of 10.x and plans for the future. Could make the <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/devsummit/index.html">DevSummit</a> and <a href="http://www.esri.com/events/feduc/index.html">FedUC</a> interesting this year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[zigGIS 2.0.2 Getting Closer]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/01/01/ziggis-2-0-2-getting-closer/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2009/01/01/ziggis-2-0-2-getting-closer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://abegillespie.blogspot.com">Abe</a> announced via <a href="http://twitter.com/zigGIS">Twitter</a> today that <a href="http://pub.obtusesoft.com/">zigGIS</a> 2.0.2 will be available in about a month. This a small but significant release becuase zigGIS will now support the generic PostGIS "GEOMETRY" type. Because ArcGIS expects homogenous feaure classes, zigGIS will ask the user to choose a geometry type for the the specified GEOMETRY-typed column. So, if your table has mixed geometry types, you will need to specify one (like polygon for example) and zigGIS will present only records of that type to ArcGIS.</p>

<p>Secondly, zigGIS will no longer expect your primary key to be called "gid". This should reduce the instances where tables need to be modified for use with zigGIS.</p>

<p>In previous releases, a few enterprising users had figured out how to get zigGIS to see views as layers by manually hacking them into the geometry_columns table. This was one way to get around the "gid" and GEOMETRY limitations. In 2.0.2, views will be fully supported so that no such hacking will be necessary.</p>

<p>Abe, Paolo and I had a chat session a while back about the zigGIS roadmap and this represents the first step down that road. More information will be forthcoming as we flesh out the details of further changes.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="alignleft" height="270" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2007/08/ziggis_logo.jpg" title="zigGIS" width="270" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
