<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gis | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/gis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-27T13:46:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Look at GIS StackExchange]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/09/12/another-look-at-gis-stackexchange/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T11:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/09/12/another-look-at-gis-stackexchange</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A year ago, I used the StackExchange API to facilitate an <a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/09/13/carving-up-gis-stackexchange/">analysis of tags on GIS StackExchange</a> to see what people were talking about on one of the largest and most successful vendor-neutral discussion sites in our industry. In that post, I stated "It would probably be good to revisit this in a year to see how things have changed, if at all."</p>

<p>Well, a year has passed so I decided to do it again. I used the same scripts and approach I used last time in order to be consistent. Since this is one year later, there is one key caveat. My analysis last year looked at the top 100 tags since the start of the <a href="http://gis.stackexchange.com/">GIS StackExchange</a> site. Since I ran the same query this year, the new results are compounded so what they so are last year's results plus activity since then. Essentially, you are looking at "that plus this." The pie chart below shows the breakdown.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/stackexchange_chart_2013.png" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Compared to last year's results, there hasn't been much movement in the distribution of tags. One thing I did notice, however is that the tag "qgis" leaped to the top of the list. Last year, "arcgis" was the top tag and "qgis" was number three. That said, I wouldn't jump to too many conclusions. A quick <a href="/assets/data/stack2013/output_2013.csv">look at the data</a> shows that, in addition to "arcgis", there are version-specific tags such as "arcgis-10.0" and "arcgis-10.1" as well as product-specific tags like "arcgis-server" so there's a lot of Esri-centric discussion going on, but that is to be expected. The top ten tags, however, include major components of the <a href="http://opengeo.org/">OpenGeo</a> Suite (OpenLayers, GeoServer, PostGIS) in addition to QGIS so open-source tools seem to be every bit as active a topic of discussion as do <a href="http://www.esri.com">Esri</a> tools.</p>

<p>Speaking of the top ten tags, they were: <br /><br />
1. qgis (3910) <br />
2. arcgis (2382) <br />
3. python (2171) <br />
4. arcgis-10.0 (2142) <br />
5. openlayers (1996) <br />
6. postgis (1560) <br />
7. geoserver (1193) <br />
8. arcobjects (1184) <br />
9. raster (1174) <br />
10. arcmap (1113) <br /></p>

<p>Last year, I got some back-channel requests to do a little more with the raw data so, seeing a chance to play with <a href="http://d3js.org">D3</a>, here is a look at how things break down. Hover over a bubble to see the full name and tag count. If you follow your nose a bit, the color scheme will become apparent in relation to the pie chart's key.</p>

<p><link rel="stylesheet" href="http://blog.geomusings.com/assets/data/stack2013/style.css" /></p>

<iframe src="http://blog.geomusings.com/assets/data/stack2013/frame.html" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>


<p>All of the same limitations I pointed out last year about posts having multiple tags and dilution across related tags still apply this year. If there is any insight into the mind share of the GIS community to be derived from this exercise, it is probably in the aggregate.</p>

<p>The exact StackExchange API URL that generated these results is: <a href="https://api.stackexchange.com/2.1/tags?order=desc&amp;sort=popular&amp;site=gis&amp;pagesize=100">https://api.stackexchange.com/2.1/tags?order=desc&amp;sort=popular&amp;site=gis&amp;pagesize=100</a></p>

<p>The results were generated on 11 September 2013 and subsequent results will vary from those shown here. The Python script used to process the results into CSV <a href="/assets/data/stack2013/handle_json.zip">can be found here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite 4.1.0 Beta Preview Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/03/spatialite-4-dot-1-0-beta-available/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T08:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/01/03/spatialite-4-dot-1-0-beta-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/spatialite-users">SpatiaLite Google Group</a> this morning, Sandro Furieri announced the availability of a beta preview of SpatiaLite 4.1.0. The primary focus of this preview is to get early comment on new capabilities supporting the storage, validation, and query of XML documents.</p>

<p>More information about this update <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=XmlBlob+and+VirtualXPath">can be found here</a>. Says Sandro:</p>

<blockquote>
The main goals of these recently introduced enhancements are:<br/>
- storing XML Documents directly within the DBMS <br/>
- supporting XML validation<br/>
- supporting plain SQL queries on behalf of XML Documents <br/>
  via canonical XPath expressions<br/>
<br/>
Implementing directly into the Spatial DBMS a common core of 
XML-oriented features surely is an interesting and useful option,
just considering that ISO- and INSPIRE-Metadata or SLD/SE Styles 
are fully based on XML.
</blockquote>


<p>Although I find myself working more with <a href="http://geojson.org">GeoJSON</a> and <a href="http://developmentseed.org/blog/2011/feb/09/introducing-carto-css-map-styling-language/">CartoCSS</a> these days, I think support for XML is a good step for SpatiaLite. There are some very mature use cases based on XML, as Sandro points out. While <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/sld">SLD</a> is not my favorite, this may keep it on my radar. Also, it would be interesting to see how this new capability would possibly affect the evolution of the <a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/projects/groups/geopackageswg">OGC GeoPackage draft specification</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Put Planet Geospatial to Work for You]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/27/put-planet-geospatial-to-work-for-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm happy to see that <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2012/11/24/planet-geospatial-the-way-forward/" target="_blank">James has decided keep Planet Geospatial going</a>. It's been one of the more consistently valuable resources in the community since its inception and it's good that it will continue.</p>

<p>While I'm looking forward to seeing how <a href="http://twitter.com/cageyjames" target="_blank">James</a> evolves <a href="http://planetgs.com" target="_blank">Planet Geospatial</a>, there are ways to more efficiently extract value out of its current state right now. At its core, Planet Geospatial is an RSS feed. RSS can safely be called "venerable" nowadays, but it still does what it does very well.</p>

<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3002" height="400" src="http://geobabble.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/postgis_evernote1.png" title="PostGIS items from Planet Geospatial in Evernote" width="640" /></p>

<p>Two of my favorite tools for culling down the firehose that is Planet Geospatial are <a href="http://ifttt.com" target="_blank">IFTTT</a> (the title of this post is a riff on the IFTTT motto) and <a href="http://evernote.com/" target="_blank">Evernote</a>. If you're not familiar with IFTTT, you should be. It reminds me of a more-intuitive Yahoo Pipes and it allows you to mix channels, triggers, and actions to automate processes of your choosing. It's become by preferred method of synchronizing my blog with social media and for filtering data sources. It also drives the <a href="http://twitter.com/QGISInfo" target="_blank">Unofficial QGIS Info</a> Twitter account. <!--more--></p>

<p>Evernote is becoming a key tool for me to store and access notes and other kinds of information. The fact that it runs on every device I own in addition to browsers makes it very useful for me as I move between customer locations.</p>

<p>When James first posted that he was wondering what to do with Planet Geospatial, I shared with him an IFTTT recipe that inserts posts from Planet Geospatial about <a href="http://www.postgis.org" target="_blank">PostGIS</a> into an Evernote notebook. He kindly tweeted it.</p>

<p>{% tweet http://twitter.com/cageyjames/statuses/272025049526050816 %}</p>

<p>I usually have three to four such filters running, depending upon topics that I'm watching. Currently, I'm grabbing posts about PostGIS, <a href="http://geojson.org" target="_blank">GeoJSON</a>, and <a href="http://mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/" target="_blank">CartoCSS</a>. These filters allow me to peruse the posts at my leisure without worrying about missing them. I can delete them from my notebook or save them as I see fit. For me, it's like having a DVR for Planet Geospatial.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Planet Geospatial is an information source. It just happens to be an information source that's based on a mature, open, well-documented, and widely adopted standard. As such, there's no need to wait for James to evolve it into something else. We can take it and transform it to meet our needs and then share it back. It's been a great community resource for a long time; it will be fun to see what the community can do with it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite for Android Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-for-android-available/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-for-android-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On what seems to be turning into <a href="http://www.gaia-gis.it/gaia-sins/" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> Monday, Sandro Furieri also announced on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/spatialite-users?pli=1" target="_blank">SpatiaLite Google Group</a> the availability of a stable version of SpatiaLite for Android.</p>

<p>I am happy to see that this version was developed and contributed back by the <a href="http://www.agc.army.mil/" target="_blank">US Army Geospatial Center</a>. The fact that they contributed back to the project under a standard open-source license is a nice step from a DoD organization.</p>

<p>The message is quoted below:</p>

<blockquote>
Hi List,

I'm really proud to announce you all that finally a rock solid stable and really easy-to-be-deployed binary porting of SpatiaLite for the Android platform is now available for download [1].

[1] <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=splite-android" target="_blank">https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=splite-android</a>

Many thanks to the U.S. Army Geospatial Center [2] who very generously contributed this highly appreciated and really useful resource under a genuine free software license (LGPLv3).

[2] <a href="http://www.agc.army.mil/" target="_blank">http://www.agc.army.mil/</a>

A detailed tutorial [3] explaining how-to deploy and use SpatiaLite on Android platforms has been kindly contributed by Andrea Antonello, who spent many long hours during the last week while performing a thorough testing of SpatiaLite-Android, then deciding to publicly share his experiences with the SpatiaLite community. Feel absolutely free to pay a beer to Andrea; he'll surely appreciate ;-)

[3] <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=spatialite-android-tutorial" target="_blank">https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=spatialite-android-tutorial</a>

enjoy, Sandro
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SpatiaLite 4.0 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-4-0-released/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/11/26/spatialite-4-0-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It looks like it was a busy weekend for Sandro Furieri and the rest of the <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/index" target="_blank">SpatiaLite</a> team as version 4.0 was announced on Sunday. There are a number of changes, so it's best to <a href="https://www.gaia-gis.it/fossil/libspatialite/wiki?name=switching-to-4.0" target="_blank">catch up on them</a> before switching over.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.manningltg.com/fixture_show.php?f_id=GCQ-164&amp;f_desc=Spatialite%20(Quartz%20Halogen)"><img alt="" height="300" src="http://www.manningltg.com/product_imgs/web/GCQ-164_1.jpg" title="Not this SpatiaLite" width="490" /></a><div style="text-align: center;font-size: 14px;">Not this SpatiaLite</div></div>


<p>I have a couple of Federal customers that are integrating SpatiaLite into their workflows so I'll need to take a day or so to assess impacts any impacts there. Looks like the perfect way to slide back into work after a long weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
