<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: GIS | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/gis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-19T22:38:09-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple Tile Viewer]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/04/25/simple-tile-viewer/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T14:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/04/25/simple-tile-viewer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We do a lot of tiles for various customers at <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">Zekiah</a>. Tiling is as much art as science and sometimes things go wrong so we have a range of utilities that we use to perform various kids of QA. Because the caches can be large, we usually want to perform a visual QA on the static tiles before pushing them up to wherever they are going to live full-time.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/cacheviewer2.png" /></p>

<p>In order to facilitate that, I wrote a very simple tile viewer using <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> and <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</a>. It uses a config file to get everything it needs to operate so we just make our changes there. This application currently only works with Web Mercator tiles but I'm working on adding support for WGS84. It also doesn't work with 'compact' tiles from ArcGIS Server. It obviously requires Node, and it also requires an <a href="https://npmjs.org/">NPM</a> install of the 'open' module to facilitate opening the browser.</p>

<p>Anything else you need to know is in the readme. I hope you find it useful. It can be <a href="https://github.com/geobabbler/cacheview">downloaded here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When Is a GeoPortal Not a GeoPortal?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/04/24/when-is-a-geoportal-not-a-geoportal/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-24T13:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/04/24/when-is-a-geoportal-not-a-geoportal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it's really a desktop application.</p>

<p>Over the past few weeks, I have been reading with conflicted agreement the posts of <a href="http://mapbrief.com/2013/02/21/the-waiting-is-the-hardest-part-why-map-portals-dont-work-part-v/">Brian Timoney</a> and <a href="http://geosprocket.blogspot.com/2013/04/toward-ideal-geoportal.html">Bill Morris</a> about the nature of geo-portals and what they should or should not be and do. I say that I am in conflicted agreement not because I take any issue with anything they have said. Their posts represent what should be considered best practices in terms of building web mapping applications. In Brian's posts, the counter-examples he highlights represent some of the worst practices to be avoided.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://blog.geomusings.com/images/posts/arcmap_browser.png" /></p>

<p>My conflict arises from the fact that, while I agree with the ideas that Brian and Bill put forward, I find myself working against them in my current work. In my <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/2013/04/10/hangouts-with-james-fee-developer-i-hardly-knew-her/">hangout with James Fee</a> a couple of weeks ago, I mentioned that I am working again (albeit temporarily) in the world of Silverlight. I am supporting a very large, complex Silverlight application that, as one of many functions, includes a mapping module that runs counter to almost every best practice espoused by Brian and Bill. And I am adding to it.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The main difference with this application is that it will never be a public-facing internet application. It is intended to be deployed to a limited user base in an intranet/extranet environment. One of the overarching goals is to deliver sophisticated analytical tools and a desktop-like experience to the user community. So why not simply deliver a desktop application, or a series of extensions to ArcGIS, or both?</p>

<p>The answer to that is simply "enterprise IT policy." This particular organization works under an IT policy framework that makes it nearly impossible to deploy custom desktop applications. This is not a unique situation as restrictive IT policies exist in many large organizations, especially Federal agencies. Some of that policy exists in the name of security, which is a laudable goal, but good developers with clear policy requirements, working in collaboration with IA staff, can secure an application regardless of how it is deployed. A larger driver is reduction of configuration management costs. It is simply expensive to identify specific users, ensure their systems meet proper specifications, deliver desktop tools to them, and sustain those tools over time. This, of course, has been one of advantages of web applications from the outset.  So "stuffing the desktop into the browser" looks like an attractive path and it is for development that must meet requirements within a budget and a schedule. Anything that reduces the friction of dealing with IT policy is a win.</p>

<p>This is all well and good within the confines of one's own intranet. What happens behind the firewall stays behind the firewall...except for when it doesn't. Poor application design is poor application design regardless of which side of the firewall on which it sits. When draconian IT policy enshrines the adoption of something-less-than-best practices, we all lose. Groupthink begins to set in and developers that spend their time building plugin-based, should-be-desktop applications on the intranet for a targeted audience of GIS users can begin to lose perspective on what makes a suitable interface for the general user. Eventually, those intranet practices will begin to be exposed on public-facing applications because many developers will continue to do what they have learned (and have been encouraged) to do.</p>

<p>Any enterprise that is sufficiently large enough to have instituted a heavy IT policy is probably engaged in some level of software development and/or customization. That policy should be flexible enough to enable users and developers to choose the right tool and/or architecture for the job, rather than turning one particular architecture (HTTP in this case) into a one-size-fits-all channel for inappropriately designed tools and practices.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SharpMap 1.0 RC1 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/28/sharpmap-1-dot-0-rc1-released/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T06:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/28/sharpmap-1-dot-0-rc1-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over on Google+, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/117900686009614580552/posts">Diego Guidi</a> let me know that the <a href="http://sharpmap.codeplex.com/releases/view/104098">SharpMap 1.0 Release Candidate has been released</a>. There was a time when I worked with, <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Ablog.geomusings.com&amp;q=sharpmap">and wrote about</a>, SharpMap a lot. During that entire time, the stable version of SharpMap sat at some version number that started with "0.9". The release of a 1.0 candidate is a signal that the project is moving forward.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://www.zekiah.com/sites/default/files/images/SharpMapSQL2008.preview.png" /></p>

<p>This is important because there are still an awful lot of .Net developers out there, especially in government shops that made a big Microsoft push in terms of infrastructure and training years ago. Of course, many of those shops are also committed to Esri technologies but SharpMap, while being a fully-functioning mapping/GIS library, also provides easy access to data sources not natively supported by Esri. Additionally, it is very easy to extend to support new or custom data sources and strightforward to <a href="http://www.zekiah.com/index.php?q=node/146">get SharpMap to play nicely in traditionally Esri-centric environments</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>At <a href="http://www.zekiah.com">my company</a> we've used SharpMap for just that for one of our key Navy customers. By building custom SharpMap data sources, we've been able to encapsulate business logic in Oracle, including the use of Oracle <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/shawty_ds/what-is-spatial-sql">Spatial SQL</a> to execute spatial analysis processes and deliver the results back to an Esri web client that is also interacting with ArcGIS Server for many standard functions. SharpMap enabled us to expose this logic through an HTTP+JSON interface while bypassing geodatabases, server object extensions, and other such cruft.</p>

<p>In recent years, other open-source .Net projects such as <a href="https://dotspatial.codeplex.com/">DotSpatial</a> have gained traction and that's good. The .Net environment remains in widespread use so it is useful to have open-source geospatial options for that platform. I'm happy to see SharpMap remaining an option in that space.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Early Bird Registration for FOSS4G-NA Closes Soon]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/27/early-bird-registration-for-foss4gna-closes-soon/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-27T13:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/27/early-bird-registration-for-foss4gna-closes-soon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/bitnerd">David Bitner</a> sent out a reminder that Early Bird reagistration for the <a href="http://foss4g-na.org/">FOSS4G North America</a> conference closes on 1 April 2013. After that, the price goes up by $50 US. You can register <a href="http://foss4gna.eventbrite.com/">online at EventBrite</a>.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/30/20060131_earthworm_hits_dirt.jpg" width="400" height="266"/></p>

<p>The <a href="http://foss4g-na.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/PreliminaryProgram.pdf">preliminary program</a> (PDF) for this year's event looks exceptional, building upon and potentially exceeding the outstanding quality of FOSS4G-NA 2012. I'll be sorry to miss the conference this year but will be looking forward to its social media exhaust.</p>

<p><sub><sup>Image by s shepherd schizoform on flickr <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC-BY-2.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</sup></sub></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Light Housekeeping]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/25/loose-ends/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-25T21:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/25/loose-ends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick note to tidy up some loose ends related to recent posts...</p>

<p>First, regarding the post "<a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/17/a-lazyweb-compendium-of-python-resources-for-beginners/">A #LazyWeb Compendium of Python Resources for Beginners</a>," the University of South Florida PyBulls Python interest group, as promised, compiled a list of Python resources and posted it <a href="https://github.com/PyBulls/learning-resources">on their GitHub page</a>. Thanks to them for their quick response.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://img.ehowcdn.com/article-new/ehow/images/a06/kv/li/proper-cutting-down-tree-chainsaw-800x800.jpg" /></p>

<p>Second, following up on the post "<a href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/03/20/the-best-thing-i-saw-at-tugis-2013/">The Best Thing I Saw at TUGIS 2013</a>," the data and workbooks for Dr. Arthur Lembo's introduction to open-source GIS have been made available. The data <a href="https://github.com/esrgc/qgistraining">can be found on GitHub</a> and the workbooks can be found on the <a href="http://www.esrgc.org/training/">Eastern Shore Regional GIS Cooperative web site</a>. Many thanks for contributing these resources.</p>

<p>These items are embedded in the comments for their respective posts but I thought it would be useful to call them out more prominently.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
