<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OSGEO | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/osgeo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-27T19:09:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maryland Department of Planning Bundles Property Data with QGIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/10/07/maryland-department-of-planning-bundles-property-data-with-qgis/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T12:38:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2013/10/07/maryland-department-of-planning-bundles-property-data-with-qgis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past week, I got an e-mail from Jim Cannistra, Director of Data Planning Services and the <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/home.shtml">Maryland Department of Planning</a> (MDP), alerting me to a new product available from MDP called <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/FINDERProduct.shtml">FINDER Quantum</a>. This product bundles Maryland property data and related products with <a href="http://qgis.org">QGIS</a> software to provide users with a fully-functional, free-standing system for interacting with the data. It is designed to replace an older, custom software product, capitalizing on an industry-standard open-source system.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>From the MDP site, the bundled data includes:</p>

<blockquote cite="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/FINDERProduct.shtml">The product DVD includes the State's computerized property (tax) maps; the x,y linkages (point or polygon) to the Parcel, Computer Assisted Mass Appraisal (CAMA) and Sale datasets; Parcel, CAMA and Sale data, including Sale data via download from the Subscriber Website, from the Maryland State Department of Assessments and Taxation (SDAT); reference grids including a grid for the property (tax) maps, an ADC map book grid, a grid for the Maryland State Highway Administration (SHA) road, stream and feature maps and a grid for USGS 7.5' Topographical quad maps; and additional SHA files including a digital centerline roads file, data derived from SHA digital grid maps, an SHA major roads file and a county boundary file.<br/>
<br/>
Also included are land use/land cover data; congressional and legislative district boundary files; census geography and census demographic data; ZIP code boundary files; Priority Funding Area (PFA) designations; floodplain data, including DFIRM data for selected jurisdictions; protected lands boundaries; watershed data; generalized zoning designations; sewer service area boundaries; public water service area boundaries for selected jurisdictions; National Register of Historic Places (NRHP) Maryland coverage; residential Sales x,y point and summary files derived from SDAT Parcel and Sale data; large-scale, high resolution color digital-ortho imagery and a custom Quantum GIS project file (.qgs).</blockquote>


<p>The MDP site indicates there is a <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/pdf/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/Finder/CstFnd.pdf">licensing fee</a> (PDF), which I assume is to cover the management of the data sets and the <a href="http://www.mdp.state.md.us/pdf/OurProducts/PropertyMapProducts/Finder/LicFnd.pdf">license agreement</a>, while acknowledging the GPL license of QGIS itself, seems to place the actual FINDER extension itself outide of any open-source license. (I am not a lawyer so I'll accept guidance on that interpretation.) That said, bundling QGIS with data that the statewide user community values and an application to help exploit it is a great way to get more users on board with QGIS.</p>

<p>To that end, users that choose to take advantage of FINDER Quantum will want to keep in mind that great <a href="http://www.esrgc.org/training/">QGIS-related resources</a> are available via <a href="http://www.salisbury.edu/geography/">Salisbury State University</a> and that training is also available from <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=14036437">Randal Hale</a> of <a href="http://www.northrivergeographic.com/introduction-to-quantum-gis">North River Geographics</a>. Once you have this powerful application installed, you can start to tap into a <a href="http://boundlessgeo.com/solutions/solutions-software/quantum-gis/">deep pool</a> of <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/search_profile">resources</a> to build your expertise.</p>

<p>So kudos to MDP for bundling their data with a powerful mapping, visualization, and analysis tool in QGIS. I hope that, in the near future, MDP considers making the FINDER application itself open-source but this is a great first step.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FOSS4G North America to Be Held In Washington, DC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/23/foss4g-north-america-to-be-held-in-washington-dc/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/23/foss4g-north-america-to-be-held-in-washington-dc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm quite happy to see (HT, <a href="http://blog.gisuser.com/2012/01/23/north-america-gets-their-own-foss4g-conference-in-d-c/" target="_blank">Glenn Letham</a>) that <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/" target="_blank">OSGEO</a> is inaugurating an annual <a href="http://foss4g-na.org/" target="_blank">FOSS4G North America</a> conference this year in Washington, DC on April 10-12, 2012.</p>

<p>DC is an appropriate place for this event because of the presence or arguably the single largest user of geospatial technology, the US Federal Government. I'm happy to see that <a href="http://twitter.com/Byrne_Tweets" target="_blank">Michael Byrne</a> is the keynote speaker as the <a href="http://broadbandmap.gov/" target="_blank">FCC National Broadband Map</a> has been a great success story in the use of open-source geospatial tools at the Federal level. I've been seeing more activity within the Federal Government recently but there's still a long way to go.</p>

<p>I know a lot of people in this area that couldn't make it out to Denver last year for FOSS4G. I hope many of them come to this edition to see the state of the art in open-source geospatial tools. I know this conference is targeted to North America as a whole but, if you are in the DC area and active with geospatial technology, FOSS4G North America should be on your calendar.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
