<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OSGEO | geoMusings]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/blog/categories/osgeo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-20T12:01:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Dollins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FOSS4G North America to Be Held In Washington, DC]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/23/foss4g-north-america-to-be-held-in-washington-dc/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.geomusings.com/2012/01/23/foss4g-north-america-to-be-held-in-washington-dc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm quite happy to see (HT, <a href="http://blog.gisuser.com/2012/01/23/north-america-gets-their-own-foss4g-conference-in-d-c/" target="_blank">Glenn Letham</a>) that <a href="http://www.osgeo.org/" target="_blank">OSGEO</a> is inaugurating an annual <a href="http://foss4g-na.org/" target="_blank">FOSS4G North America</a> conference this year in Washington, DC on April 10-12, 2012.</p>

<p>DC is an appropriate place for this event because of the presence or arguably the single largest user of geospatial technology, the US Federal Government. I'm happy to see that <a href="http://twitter.com/Byrne_Tweets" target="_blank">Michael Byrne</a> is the keynote speaker as the <a href="http://broadbandmap.gov/" target="_blank">FCC National Broadband Map</a> has been a great success story in the use of open-source geospatial tools at the Federal level. I've been seeing more activity within the Federal Government recently but there's still a long way to go.</p>

<p>I know a lot of people in this area that couldn't make it out to Denver last year for FOSS4G. I hope many of them come to this edition to see the state of the art in open-source geospatial tools. I know this conference is targeted to North America as a whole but, if you are in the DC area and active with geospatial technology, FOSS4G North America should be on your calendar.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
